<book id="Dt"> <chapter id="Dt 1"> <pericope>Preamble</pericope> <pa><vn id="Dt 1:1">These <sd>are</sd> the words that Moses spoke to all <sd>of</sd> Israel <im>on the other side of</im><n><io>Literally “in the beyond <sd>of</sd>”</io></n> the Jordan in the desert,<n><io>Or “the wilderness”</io></n> in the desert plateau<n><io>Or “desert plain”; others render this as a named location, “Arabah”</io></n> opposite Suph, between Paran and between Tophel and Laban and Hazeroth and Dizahab. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:2">It is <sd>a journey of</sd> <im>eleven days</im><n><io>Literally “one and ten days”</io></n> from Herob <im>by the way of Mount Seir</im><n><io>Literally “by the mountain of Seir”</io></n> up to Kadesh Barnea. </vn></pa> <pa><im><vn id="Dt 1:3">And it was</vn></im><n><io>Literally “and it happened” or “and then”</io></n><vn id="Dt 1:3"> in the fortieth year, on the eleventh month, on <sd>the</sd> first <sd>day</sd> of the month, Moses spoke to the <im>Israelites</im><n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> according to all that Yahweh had instructed him <sd>to speak</sd> to them. </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 1:4">This happened</vn></sd> <im><vn id="Dt 1:4">after defeating</vn></im><n><io>Literally “after he had struck down”</io></n><vn id="Dt 1:4"> Sihon king of the Amorites, who <sd>was</sd> reigning<n><io>Or “dwelling,” and in this context “reigning”</io></n> in Heshbon, and Og the king of Bashan, who <sd>was</sd> reigning<n><io>Or “dwelling,” and in this context “reigning”</io></n> in Ashtaroth in Edrei. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:5">On the other side of <n><io>Literally “in the beyond <sd>of</sd>”</io></n> the Jordan in the land of Moab Moses began to explain this law,<n><io>Hebrew <i>torah</i></io></n> <im>saying</im>:<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> </vn></pa>  <pericope>Historical Prologue</pericope> <pa><vn id="Dt 1:6">“Yahweh our God spoke to us at Horeb, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘You have stayed <im>long enough</im><n><io>Literally “much <sd>time</sd>”</io></n> at this mountain. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:7">Turn <sd>now</sd> and <im>move on</im>,<n><io>Literally “journey on with respect to yourselves” or “move yourselves out”</io></n> and go <sd>into</sd> the hill of the Amorites<n><io>Hebrew “Amorite”</io></n> and to all <sd>of</sd> the neighboring regions<n><io>Or “peoples”</io></n> in the Jordan <im>Valley</im><n><io>Literally “Arabah,” arid stretches of land.</io></n> in the hill country and in the Negev and in the coastal area along the sea, <sd>into</sd> the land of the Canaanites<n><io>Hebrew “Canaanite”</io></n> and <sd>into</sd> the Lebanon, as far as the great river Euphrates. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:8">Look, I have set the land <im>before you</im>;<n><io>Literally “before your face”</io></n> go and take possession of the land that Yahweh swore to your ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give <sd>it</sd> to them and to their offspring after them.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 1:9">“And I spoke to them at that time, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘I am not able to bear you alone. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:10">Yahweh your God has multiplied you, and look; you <sd>are</sd> today as the stars of the heaven <im>in number</im>.<n><io>Literally “with respect to multitude/abundance”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 1:11">Yahweh, the God of your ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> may he add to you as you are <sd>now</sd> a thousand times, and may he bless you just as he <im>promised you</im>.<n><io>Literally “spoke to you”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 1:12">How can I bear you <im>by myself</im>,<n><io>Literally “to me alone”</io></n> your burden and your load and your strife? </vn><vn id="Dt 1:13">Choose for yourselves <im>wise and discerning and knowledgeable men</im><n><io>Literally “men wise and discerning and knowledgeable”</io></n> for <sd>each of</sd> your tribes, and I will appoint them as your leaders.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 1:14">“And you answered me, and you said, ‘The thing you have said to do is good.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 1:15">And so I took the leaders of your tribes, wise and knowledgeable men, and <sd>then</sd> I appointed them as leaders over you <sd>as</sd> commanders of <sd>groups of</sd> thousands and commanders of <sd>groups of</sd> hundreds and commanders of <sd>groups of</sd> fifties and commanders of <sd>groups of</sd> tens <sd>as</sd> officials for your tribes. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:16">And at that time I instructed your judges, saying, ‘<im>hear out your fellow men</im>,<n><io>Literally “hear between your brothers,” with the idea of listening carefully in this context</io></n> and <sd>then</sd> judge fairly<n><io>Or “righteously”</io></n> between a man and between his brother and between <im>his opponent who is a resident alien</im>.<n><io>Literally “between his resident alien/non-Israelite who dwells temporarily among Israel”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 1:17">You must not <im>be partial</im><n><io>Literally “recognize faces”</io></n> <im>in your judgment</im>; <n><io>Literally “in the process of rendering a judgment”</io></n> hear <sd>out</sd> the small <sd>person</sd> as <sd>also</sd> the great <sd>person</sd>; <im>do not be intimidated by any person</im>,<n><io>Literally “do not fear before the faces of <sd>any</sd> man”</io></n> because the judgment <sd>is</sd> God’s; and the case that is too difficult<n><io>Or “hard”</io></n> for you, bring <sd>it</sd> to me, and I will hear it <sd>out</sd>.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 1:18">And so I instructed you at that time <sd>concerning</sd> all <sd>of</sd> the things that you should do. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 1:19">“Then we set out from Horeb, and we went <sd>through</sd> the whole <sd>of</sd> that great and terrible desert that you saw <sd>on</sd> the way <sd>to</sd> the hill country of the Amorites<n><io>Hebrew “Amorite”</io></n> as Yahweh our God had commanded us, and <sd>so</sd> we came up to Kadesh Barnea. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:20">I said to you, ‘<im>You have reached</im><n><io>Literally “You have come up to”</io></n> the hill country of the Amorites<n><io>Hebrew “Amorite”</io></n> that Yahweh our God <sd>is</sd> giving to us. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:21">See, Yahweh your God has set before you the land; go up and possess <sd>it</sd> as Yahweh the God of your ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> said to you; do not fear and do not be dismayed.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 1:22">“Then all of you approached me, and <sd>you</sd> said, ‘Let us send men <im>before us</im>,<n><io>Literally “before our faces” or “ahead of us”</io></n> and let them explore the land for us, and let them bring back <im>a report</im><n><io>Literally “a word”</io></n> to us <sd>concerning</sd> the way that <im>we should take</im><n><io>Literally “we should go up by it”</io></n> <sd>and concerning</sd> the cities that we shall come to.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 1:23">The plan was good <im>in my opinion</im>,<n><io>Literally “in my eyes”</io></n> and <sd>so</sd> I took from <sd>among</sd> you twelve men, <im>one from each tribe</im>.<n><io>Literally “man one from the tribe”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 1:24">And they <im>set out</im><n><io>Literally “turned”</io></n> and <im>went up into the hill country</im>,<n><io>Literally “went up toward the hill <sd>country</sd> mountain”</io></n> and they went up to the wadi<n><io>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</io></n> of Eschol, and they spied out <sd>the land</sd>. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:25">They took in their hands<n><io>Hebrew “hand”</io></n> <im>some of the fruit</im><n><io>Literally “from the fruit”</io></n> of the land, and they brought <sd>it</sd> down to us, and they brought to us back <im>a report</im>,<n><io>Literally “a word”</io></n> and they said, ‘The land that Yahweh our God <sd>is</sd> giving to us <sd>is</sd> good.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 1:26">But you were not willing to go up, and you rebelled against the <im>command</im><n><io>Literally “mouth”</io></n> of Yahweh your God. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:27">And you grumbled in your tents, and you said, ‘Because of the hatred of Yahweh <sd>toward</sd> us he has brought us out from the land of Egypt to give us into the hand of the Amorites<n><io>Hebrew “Amorite”</io></n> to destroy us. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:28">Where <sd>can</sd> we go up? Our brothers have <im>made our hearts melt</im>,<n><io>Literally “caused to melt our hearts”</io></n> <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> “The people are greater<n><io>Or “bigger”</io></n> and taller than we are,<n><io>Hebrew “than us”</io></n> <sd>and there are</sd> great fortified cities <sd>reaching</sd> up to heaven, and we saw the sons of the Anakites <sd>living</sd> there.” ’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 1:29">“And so I said to you, ‘Do not be terrified, and do not fear them. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:30">Yahweh your God, who is going <im>before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “to your faces”</io></n> will himself<n><io>The Hebrew pronoun indicates emphasis</io></n> fight for you, <im>just as</im><n><io>Literally “like all that”</io></n> he did for you in Egypt before your eyes, </vn><vn id="Dt 1:31">and <sd>just as he did</sd> in the wilderness<n><io>Or “desert”</io></n> when<n><io>Or “where”</io></n> you saw that<n><io>Or “how”</io></n> Yahweh your God carried you, just as someone<n><io>Or “a man”</io></n> carries his son, all <sd>along</sd> the way <sd>that</sd> you traveled until <im>you reached</im><n><io>Literally “you came”</io></n> this place.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 1:32">But through all of this you did not trust in Yahweh your God, </vn><im><vn id="Dt 1:33">who goes</vn></im><n><io>Literally “<sd>is</sd> the one going”</io></n> <im><vn id="Dt 1:33">before you</vn></im><n><io>Literally “before your faces”</io></n><vn id="Dt 1:33"> on your<n><io>Hebrew “the”</io></n> way, seeking a place for your encampment, in fire at night and in a cloud by day, to show you the way that <im>you should go</im>.<n><io>Literally “you should go in it”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 1:34">“Then Yahweh heard the sound of your words, and he was angry, and he swore, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 1:35">‘No one of these men<n><io>The beginning of an oath in Hebrew; the text emphatically denies anyone of that evil generation the privilege of seeing the promised land</io></n> of this evil generation will see the good land that I swore to give to your ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 1:36">except Caleb, the son of Jephunneh; he himself<n><io>Emphatic use of the pronoun</io></n> shall see it, and to him I will give the land upon which he has trodden and to his sons<n><io>Or “descendants”</io></n> because <im>he followed Yahweh unreservedly</im>.’<n><io>Literally “he filled <sd>his hands</sd> after Yahweh”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 1:37">Even with me Yahweh was angry because of you, saying, ‘Not even you shall enter there. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:38">Joshua, the son of Nun, <im>your assistant</im>,<n><io>Literally “the one standing before you”</io></n> will go there; encourage him because he will cause Israel to inherit it. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:39">And your little children, who you thought shall become plunder, and your sons, who do not today know good or bad, shall themselves<n><io>The Hebrew pronoun is used for emphasis</io></n> go there, and I will give it to them, and they shall take possession of it. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:40">But you turn and set out <sd>in the direction of</sd> the wilderness by way of the <im>Red Sea</im>.’<n><io>Literally “sea of reeds”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 1:41">“You replied and said to me, ‘We have sinned against Yahweh, <sd>and now</sd> we will go up and fight according to all that Yahweh our God commanded us’; and <sd>so</sd> each man fastened on <im>his battle gear</im>,<n><io>Literally “his vessels of battle”</io></n> and you regarded <sd>it</sd> as easy to go up <sd>into</sd> the hill country. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:42">So Yahweh said to me, ‘Say to them, “You shall not go up, and you shall not fight because I am not in your midst; you will be defeated <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “in the faces of your enemies”</io></n> your enemies.” ’ </vn><vn id="Dt 1:43">So I spoke to you, but you did not listen; you rebelled against the <im>command of Yahweh</im>;<n><io>Literally “mouth of Yahweh”</io></n> you behaved presumptuously, and you went up into the hill country. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:44">The Amorites living in the hill country went out <im>to oppose you</im><n><io>Literally “to meet you”</io></n> and chased you as <sd>a swarm of</sd> wild honey bees do; and <sd>so</sd> they <im>beat</im><n><io>Literally “cut”</io></n> you down in Seir as far as Hormah. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:45">So you returned and wept <im>before Yahweh</im>;<n><io>Literally “before the faces of Yahweh”</io></n> but Yahweh did not listen to your voice and did not pay <sd>any</sd> attention to you. </vn><vn id="Dt 1:46">You stayed in Kadesh many days; such were the days that you stayed <sd>there</sd>. </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 2"> <pa><vn id="Dt 2:1"> “<sd>Then</sd> we turned and set out <sd>toward</sd> the wilderness<n><io>Or “desert”</io></n> in the direction of the <im>Red Sea</im>,<n><io>Literally “sea of reeds”</io></n> as Yahweh told me, and we went around Mount Seir <sd>for</sd> many days. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:2">Yahweh spoke to me, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 2:3">‘<sd>Long</sd> enough you have been skirting this mountain; turn yourselves north, </vn><vn id="Dt 2:4">and instruct<n><io>Or “command”</io></n> the people, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> “You <sd>are</sd> about to cross <sd>through</sd> the territory of your brothers, the descendants<n><io>Or “sons”</io></n> of Esau, who are living in Seir; they will be afraid of you, and <sd>so</sd> be very careful. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:5">Do not get involved in battle<n><io>Or “provoke”</io></n> with them, for I will not give you any of their land, not even a foot’s breadth<n><io>Literally “a sole’s foot of space”</io></n> <sd>of it</sd>; since I have given Mount Seir <sd>as</sd> a possession for Esau. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:6">You shall buy food from them so that you may eat; and also you shall purchase water from them with money so that you may drink. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:7">The fact of the matter is, Yahweh your God has blessed you in <im>all the work you have done</im>;<n><io>Literally “the work of your hand”</io></n> he knows <im>your travels</im><n><io>Literally “your journeying”</io></n> <sd>with respect to</sd> this great wilderness; forty years Yahweh your God <sd>has been</sd> with you; you have not lacked a thing.” ’ </vn><vn id="Dt 2:8">And so we passed by our brothers, the descendants<n><io>Or “sons”</io></n> of Esau, who live in Seir, past the road of the Arabah,<n><io>Or “Jordan Valley” since the Arabah is an extension of it</io></n> from Elath and Ezion Geber, and we turned and traveled along the route of the desert<n><io>Or “wilderness”</io></n> of Moab. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 2:9">And Yahweh said to me, ‘You shall not attack Moab, and you shall not engage in war<n><io>Or “battle”</io></n> with them, for I will not give you any of his land <sd>as</sd> a possession; I have given Ar to the descendants<n><io>Or “sons”</io></n> of Lot <sd>as</sd> a possession.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 2:10">(The Emim previously lived in it, a people large,<n><io>Or “great” in the sense of influential</io></n> numerous, and tall, like the Anakites. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:11">They were reckoned also <sd>as</sd> Rephaim as the Anakites <sd>were</sd>; but the Moabites called them Emim. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:12">The Horites previously lived in Seir, but the descendants<n><io>Or “sons”</io></n> of Esau dispossessed them and destroyed them <im>from among themselves</im>,<n><io>Literally “from their presence”</io></n> as Israel did with respect to the land of their<n><io>Literally “its/his”</io></n> possession that Yahweh gave to them.) </vn><vn id="Dt 2:13">So <sd>now</sd> arise and cross over the wadi<n><io>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</io></n> of Zered yourselves; and <sd>so</sd> we crossed the wadi<n><io>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</io></n> of Zered. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:14">Now the <im>length of time</im><n><io>Literally “days”</io></n> that we had traveled from Kadesh Barnea until <sd>the time when</sd> we crossed the wadi<n><io>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</io></n> of Zered <sd>was</sd> thirty-eight years, until the perishing of all of that generation; <sd>that is</sd>, the men of war from the midst of the camp as Yahweh had sworn to them. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:15">The hand of Yahweh was against them to root them out from the midst of the camp until they perished completely. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 2:16">“<im>And then</im><n><io>Literally “And it happened”</io></n> when all the men of war<n><io>Or “battle”</io></n> <im>had died</im><n><io>Literally “had finished/completed to die”</io></n> from among the people, </vn><vn id="Dt 2:17">Yahweh spoke to me, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 2:18">‘You <sd>are</sd> about to cross over the boundary of Moab <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> at Ar. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:19">When you approach <im>the border of</im><n><io>Literally “opposite”</io></n> the <im>Ammonites</im>,<n><io>Literally “the sons/children of Ammon”</io></n> you shall not harass them, and you shall not get involved in battle with them, for I have not given the land of <im>the Ammonites</im><n><io>Literally “the sons/children of Ammon”</io></n> to you as a possession; because I have given it to the descendants<n><io>Or “sons”</io></n> of Lot <sd>as</sd> a possession. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:20">(It is also considered the land of Rephaim; Rephaim lived in it <im>previously</im>,<n><io>Literally “before”</io></n> and the Ammonites called them Zamzummim, </vn><vn id="Dt 2:21">a people great and numerous and as tall as the Anakites; Yahweh destroyed them from before them,<n><io>That is, the Ammonites</io></n> and they dispossessed them and settled in place of them, </vn><vn id="Dt 2:22">just as he did for the descendants<n><io>Or “sons”</io></n> of Esau, who live in Seir, when he destroyed the Horites from <im>before them</im><n><io>Literally “from the face/presence of them”</io></n> and dispossessed them, and <sd>then</sd> they settled in their<n><io>Hebrew “them”</io></n> place up to this day. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:23">And <sd>also</sd> the Avvites, who lived in villages as far as Gaza, <sd>and the</sd> Caphtorim, who came out from Caphtor, destroyed them and <sd>then</sd> settled in their place. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:24">Arise,<n><io>Or “Get up”</io></n> set out and cross <sd>over</sd> the wadi<n><io>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</io></n> of Arnon. Look! I have given Sihon the Amorite, the king of Heshbon, and his land into your hand; begin to take possession of <sd>it</sd>, and engage with him in battle. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:25">This day I will begin to place <im>the dread of you</im><n><io>Literally “your dread”</io></n> and the fear of you <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “upon the faces of”</io></n> the peoples under all the heavens. <sd>They</sd> will hear <im>the report about you</im>,<n><io>Literally “your report”</io></n> and <sd>so</sd> they will shake and tremble <im>because of you</im>.’ <n><io>Literally “from before you”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 2:26">“So I sent messengers from the wilderness<n><io>Or “desert”</io></n> of Kedemoth to Sihon king of Heshbon; <sd>I sent</sd> terms of peace, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 2:27">‘Let me cross through your land <sd>and</sd> <im>only along the road</im><n><io>Literally “in the road, in the road”</io></n> I will go; I will not turn aside to the right or <sd>to the</sd> left. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:28">Food for money you shall sell me, so that I may eat, and water for money you will give to me, so that I may drink; just let me cross on foot. </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 2:29">Just as</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 2:29"> the descendants<n><io>Or “the children/sons of”</io></n> of Esau did for me, who live in Seir, and the Moabites, who live in Ar, until I cross the Jordan into the land that Yahweh our God is giving to us.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 2:30">But Sihon king of Heshbon was not willing to let us cross through his <sd>territory</sd> because Yahweh your God hardened his spirit and <im>made him obstinate</im><n><io>Literally “made firm his heart”</io></n> <im>in order to give him</im><n><io>Literally “to give him,” indicating purpose</io></n> into your hand, <im>just as he has now done</im>.<n><io>Literally “as <sd>it is</sd> this day”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 2:31">Yahweh said to me, ‘Look! I have begun to give <im>over to you</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of you”</io></n> Sihon and his land; begin <im>to take possession of his land</im>.’<n><io>Literally, “take possession in order to possess his land”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 2:32">Then Sihon and all his people came out to meet us for battle at Jahaz. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:33">And so Yahweh our God gave him over <im>to us</im>,<n><io>Literally “before us”</io></n> and we struck him down, and his sons<n><io>Or “descendants”</io></n> and all of his people. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:34">So we captured all of his cities at that time, and we destroyed each town <sd>of</sd> males and the women and the children; we did not leave behind a survivor. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:35">We took only the livestock as spoil for ourselves,<n><io>Hebrew “us”</io></n> and <sd>also</sd> the booty of the cities that we had captured. </vn><vn id="Dt 2:36">From Aroer, which <sd>is</sd> on the edge of the wadi<n><io>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</io></n> of Arnon and the city that <sd>was</sd> in the wadi<n><io>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</io></n> on up to Gilead, <sd>there</sd> was not a city that was inaccessible to us; Yahweh our God gave <im>everything</im><n><io>Literally “the whole”</io></n> <im>to us</im>.<n><io>Literally “before us”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 2:37">Only the land of <im>the Ammonites</im><n><io>Literally “children/sons of Ammon”</io></n> you did not approach, <sd>all along</sd> the whole upper region of the Jabbok <im>River</im><n><io>Literally “wadi,” which here refers to a flowing river</io></n> and the towns of the hill country, <sd>according to all</sd> that Yahweh our God had instructed. </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 3"> <pa><vn id="Dt 3:1"> “Then we turned, and we went up the road to Bashan, and Og the king of Bashan came out to meet us, he and all <sd>of</sd> his army for the battle <sd>at</sd> Edrei. </vn><vn id="Dt 3:2">And Yahweh said to me, ‘You should not fear him, for I have given him and all <sd>of</sd> his army<n><io>Or “people”</io></n> and his land into your hand. And <sd>so</sd> you will do to him as you did to Sihon the king of the Amorites,<n><io>Hebrew “Amorite”</io></n> who <sd>was</sd> reigning in Heshbon.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 3:3">And <sd>so</sd> Yahweh our God also gave Og the king of Bashan, and all of his army<n><io>Or “people”</io></n> into our hand, and we struck him down until not a survivor remained to<n><io>Or “for”</io></n> him. </vn><vn id="Dt 3:4">And we captured all <sd>of</sd> his towns<n><io>Or “villages/cities <sd>small</sd>”</io></n> at that time; <sd>there</sd> was not a city that we did not take from them. </vn><vn id="Dt 3:5">All of these <sd>were</sd> fortified towns with high walls, gates, and bars,<n><io>Hebrew “bar”</io></n> <im>apart from</im><n><io>Literally “alone from”</io></n> very many <sd>of</sd> the villages of the open country. </vn><vn id="Dt 3:6">And <sd>so</sd> we destroyed them just as we had done to Sihon the king of Heshbon; <sd>we destroyed</sd> utterly each town of males, the women, and the little children. </vn><vn id="Dt 3:7">But all <sd>of</sd> the livestock and the booty of the towns we kept as spoil for ourselves.<n><io>Hebrew “us”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 3:8">“And so we took at that time the land from <im>the control of</im><n><io>Literally “the hand of”</io></n> <sd>the</sd> two kings of the Amorites<n><io>Hebrew “Amorite”</io></n> who <sd>were</sd> <im>on the other side of the Jordan</im>,<n><io>Literally “in the beyond of the Jordan”</io></n> from the wadi<n><io>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</io></n> of Arnon up to <im>Mount Hermon</im>.<n><io>Literally “the mountain of Hermon”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 3:9">(The Sidonians called Hermon ‘Sirion,’ and the Amorites called it ‘Senir.’) </vn><vn id="Dt 3:10">All of the towns of the plateau and the whole of Gilead and all of Bashan up to Salecah and Edrei, the towns of the kingdom of Og in Bashan. </vn><vn id="Dt 3:11">(For only Og, king of Bashan, was left from the remnant of the Rephaim. Indeed, his bedstead—it <sd>was</sd> a bedstead of iron. It is in Rabbah of the <im>Ammonites</im>.<n><io>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</io></n> Nine cubits <sd>is</sd> its length, and four cubits <sd>is</sd> its width according to the cubit of a man.) </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 3:12">And <sd>so</sd> we took possession of this land at that time, from Aroer, which <sd>is</sd> on the <sd>edge of the</sd> wadi<n><io>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</io></n> of Arnon, and <sd>also</sd> half of the hill country of Gilead and its towns I gave to the Reubenites<n><io>Hebrew “Reubenite”</io></n> and to the Gadites.<n><io>Hebrew “Gadite”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 3:13">And the remainder of Gilead and all of Bashan, the kingdom of Og, I gave to the half-tribe of Manasseh, the whole region of Argo. All of that <sd>area of</sd> Bashan was called <sd>the</sd> land of the Rephaim. </vn><vn id="Dt 3:14">Jair the descendant<n><io>Or “son”</io></n> of Manasseh acquired the whole region of Argob, up to the boundary of the Geshurites and the Maacathites, and he called it,<n><io>Hebrew “them”</io></n> <sd>that is</sd> Bashan, after his <sd>own</sd> name, Havvoth Jair, <im>as it still is today</im>.<n><io>Literally “up to this day”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 3:15">And <sd>also</sd> I gave Gilead to Makir. </vn><vn id="Dt 3:16">And to the Reubenites<n><io>Hebrew “Reubenite”</io></n> and to the Gadites<n><io>Hebrew “Gadite”</io></n> I gave, from Gilead up to the wadi<n><io>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</io></n> of Arnon, the middle of the wadi<n><io>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</io></n> <sd>as a</sd> boundary and up to the Jabbok <im>River</im>,<n><io>Literally “wadi,” which here refers to a flowing river</io></n> the boundary of the <im>Ammonites</im>.<n><io>Literally “sons/children of Ammon”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 3:17">And the <im>Jordan Valley</im><n><io>Literally “Arabah”</io></n> <sd>with</sd> the Jordan <sd>River as its</sd> boundary, from Kinnereth<n><io>Or “Chinnereth,” the Sea of Galilee</io></n> up to the Sea of the Arabah, the Salt Sea,<n><io>Or the Dead Sea</io></n> <sd>with</sd> the slopes of Pisgah toward the east. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 3:18">“And I charged you <sd>all</sd> at that time <sd>when I</sd> said, “Yahweh has given you—to <sd>all of</sd> you—this land to possess. All the <im>warriors</im><n><io>Literally “men of valor”</io></n> shall cross over, ready to fight, before your brothers, the <im>Israelites</im>.<n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 3:19">Only your wives and your little children and your livestock (I know that <im>you have much livestock</im>)<n><io>Literally “livestock much <sd>there is</sd> to you”</io></n> must stay in your towns that I have given you, </vn><vn id="Dt 3:20">until Yahweh shall give rest to your brothers as <sd>he did</sd> to you, and also they take possession <sd>of</sd> the land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to them beyond the Jordan; then they may return, each <sd>one</sd> to his possession that I have given to them. </vn><vn id="Dt 3:21">And I commanded Joshua at that time, saying, ‘Your eyes see all that Yahweh your God has done to these two kings; so Yahweh will do to all <sd>of</sd> the kingdoms where you are about to cross over to. </vn><vn id="Dt 3:22">You shall not fear them, for Yahweh your God is the <sd>one</sd> fighting for you. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 3:23">“And I pleaded with Yahweh at that time, saying, </vn><vn id="Dt 3:24">‘Lord Yahweh, you have begun to show your servant your greatness and your strong hand, for what<n><io>Hebrew “who”</io></n> god <sd>is there</sd> in the heaven or on the earth who can do according to your works and according to your mighty deeds? </vn><vn id="Dt 3:25">Let me cross over, please, and let me see the good land <im>that is beyond the Jordan</im>,<n><io>Literally “in the beyond of the Jordan”</io></n> this good hill country and Lebanon.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 3:26">But Yahweh was very angry with me because of you, and he would not listen to me, and Yahweh said, ‘<im>Enough of that from you</im>!<n><io>Literally “Much to you”</io></n> You shall not speak to me <sd>any</sd> longer about this matter! </vn><vn id="Dt 3:27">Go up <sd>to</sd> the top of Pisgah and <im>look around you</im><n><io>Literally “lift up your eyes”</io></n> toward the west, toward the north, and toward the east, and <im>view</im><n><io>Literally “look”</io></n> <sd>the land</sd> with your eyes, for you will not cross this Jordan. </vn><vn id="Dt 3:28">Now instruct Joshua and support him and encourage him because he himself<n><io>Emphatic use of the pronoun</io></n> will cross <sd>over</sd> before this people and enable them to inherit the land that you will see.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 3:29">So we remained in the valley opposite Beth Peor. </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 4"> <pericope>Introduction to the Stipulations</pericope> <pa><vn id="Dt 4:1">“Now, Israel, listen to the rules and to the regulations that I <sd>am</sd> teaching you to do, in order that you may live and you may go <sd>in</sd> and you may take possession of the land that Yahweh, the God of your ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> <sd>is</sd> giving to you. </vn><vn id="Dt 4:2">You must not add to the word that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you, and you shall not take away from it <sd>in order</sd> to keep<n><io>Or “observe”</io></n> the commands of Yahweh your God that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <sd>to observe</sd>. </vn><vn id="Dt 4:3">Your eyes have seen<n><io>Literally “your eyes the seeing what”</io></n> what Yahweh did with<n><io>Or “in”</io></n> <sd>the case of</sd> Baal Peor, for <im>each</im><n><io>Literally “every one <sd>of</sd>”</io></n> man that followed after Baal Peor Yahweh your God destroyed from your midst. </vn><vn id="Dt 4:4">But you, the <sd>ones</sd> holding fast to Yahweh your God, <sd>are</sd> all alive <im>today</im>.<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 4:5">See, I now teach<n><io>Or “I have taught” (compare NASB, NEB)</io></n> you rules and regulations <sd>just</sd> as Yahweh my God has commanded me, to observe <sd>them</sd> <sd>just</sd> so in the midst of the land where you <sd>are</sd> going, to take possession of it. </vn><vn id="Dt 4:6">And <im>you must observe them diligently</im>,<n><io>Literally “you must observe and you must do”</io></n> for that <sd>is</sd> your wisdom and your insight before the eyes of the people, who will hear all <sd>of</sd> these rules, and they will say, ‘Surely this great nation <sd>is</sd> a wise and discerning people.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 4:7">For what great nation <sd>has</sd> for it a god near to it as Yahweh our God, whenever<n><io>Literally “in every matter/every time we call ”</io></n> we call <sd>upon</sd> him? </vn><vn id="Dt 4:8">And what <sd>other</sd> great nation has for it<n><io>Literally “which/that <sd>is</sd> for him <sd>it</sd>”</io></n> just rules and regulations just like<n><io>Literally “as”</io></n> <im>this whole</im><n><io>Literally “all <sd>of</sd>”</io></n> law that I <sd>am</sd> setting <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> you <im>today</im>?<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 4:9">“However, <im>take care</im><n><io>Literally “watch”</io></n> for yourself and watch your inner self<n><io>Or “soul”</io></n> closely, so that you do not forget the things that your eyes have seen, so that they do not slip from your mind all the days of your life; and you shall make them known to your children and to <im>your grandchildren</im>.<n><io>Literally “the children of your children”</io></n> </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 4:10">Remember</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 4:10"> the day that you stood <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> Yahweh your God at Horeb <im>when Yahweh said to me</im>,<n><io>Literally “when to say Yahweh”</io></n> ‘Summon for me the people so that I can tell them my words, that they may learn to fear me all <sd>of</sd> the days they <sd>are</sd> alive on the earth and so <sd>that</sd> they may teach their children.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 4:11">And <sd>so</sd> you came near, and you stood under the mountain, and the mountain <sd>was</sd> burning with fire up to the heart of the heaven, <im>dark with a very thick cloud</im>.<n><io>Literally “darkness, cloud, and very thick darkness”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 4:12">And Yahweh spoke to you from the midst of the fire; <im>you heard</im><n><io>Literally “you <sd>were</sd> hearing”</io></n> a sound of words, but <im>you did not see</im><n><io>Literally “you were not seeing”</io></n> a form—only a voice. </vn><vn id="Dt 4:13">And he declared to you his covenant, <im>the Ten Commandments</im>,<n><io>Literally “the ten words”</io></n> which he charged you <im>to observe</im>,<n><io>Literally “to do”</io></n> and he wrote them on <sd>the</sd> two tablets of stone. </vn><vn id="Dt 4:14">And Yahweh charged me at that time to teach you rules and regulations <im>for your observation of them</im><n><io>Literally “for your doing them”</io></n> in the land that you <sd>are</sd> <im>about to cross into</im><n><io>Literally “about to cross into there”</io></n> to take possession of it. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 4:15">“So <im>you must be very careful for yourselves</im>,<n><io>Literally “watch yourselves diligently with respect to your souls”</io></n> because you did not see<n><io>Or “have not seen”</io></n> any form on the day Yahweh spoke to you at Horeb from the midst of the fire, </vn><vn id="Dt 4:16">so that you <sd>do</sd> not <im>ruin yourselves</im><n><io>Literally “corrupt yourselves”</io></n> and make for yourselves a divine image <sd>in</sd> a form of any image, a replica of male or female, </vn><vn id="Dt 4:17">a replica of any animal that <sd>is</sd> upon the earth, a replica of any winged bird that flies in the air, </vn><vn id="Dt 4:18">a replica of any creeping thing on the ground, a replica of any fish that <sd>is</sd> in the water <im>below</im><n><io>Literally “under”</io></n> the earth. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 4:19">And do this so that you do not lift</vn></im><n><io>Literally “And lest you lift up”</io></n><vn id="Dt 4:19"> your eyes <sd>toward</sd> heaven and <im>observe</im><n><io>Literally “see”</io></n> the sun and the moon and the stars, all the host of the heaven, and be led astray and bow down to them and serve them, things that Yahweh your God has allotted to all <sd>of</sd> the peoples under all <sd>of</sd> the heaven. </vn><vn id="Dt 4:20">But Yahweh has taken you and brought you out from the furnace of iron, from Egypt, to be a people of inheritance to<n><io>Or “for”; a people of inheritance = a people who is his very own possession</io></n> him, <im>as it is this day</im>.<n><io>Literally “as the day the this” = as you are now</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 4:21">“And Yahweh was angry with me <im>because of you</im>,<n><io>Literally “because of your matter”</io></n> and he swore <im>that I would not cross the Jordan</im><n><io>Literally “not I to cross the Jordan”</io></n> and <im>that I would not go to the good land</im><n><io>Literally “not <sd>I</sd> going to the land”</io></n> that Yahweh your God is giving you as an inheritance. </vn><vn id="Dt 4:22">For I <sd>am</sd> going to die in this land; I am not going to cross the Jordan, but you <sd>are</sd> going to cross, and you are going to take possession of this good land. </vn><vn id="Dt 4:23">Watch <sd>out</sd> for yourselves so that you do not forget the covenant of Yahweh your God that he had <im>made</im><n><io>Literally “cut”</io></n> with you and make for yourselves a divine image <sd>of</sd> the form of anything that Yahweh your God <im>has forbidden</im>,<n><io>Literally “has commanded you <sd>about</sd>”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 4:24">for Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> a devouring fire, a jealous<n><io>Or “zealous” or “impassioned”</io></n> God. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 4:25">“When you have had children and <im>grandchildren</im><n><io>Literally “children of children”</io></n> and you have grown old in the land and you act corruptly and you make a divine image <sd>of</sd> the form of anything and you do evil in the eyes of Yahweh your God, <sd>thus</sd> provoking him to anger, </vn><vn id="Dt 4:26">I call<n><io>Or “I shall call to witness”</io></n> to witness against you today the heaven and the earth, that you will perish soon and completely from the land that you <sd>are</sd> crossing the Jordan into it to take possession of it; <im>you will not live long on it</im>,<n><io>Literally “you will not extend days”</io></n> but you will be completely destroyed. </vn><vn id="Dt 4:27">And Yahweh will scatter you among the peoples, and you will be left <im>few in number</im><n><io>Literally “people of number,” as opposed to people without number</io></n> among the nations <im>to where Yahweh will lead you</im>.<n><io>Literally “<sd>he</sd> will lead Yahweh you there”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 4:28">And you will there serve gods <im>made by human hands</im>,<n><io>Literally “the work of the hands of human”</io></n> <sd>of</sd> wood and stone, <sd>gods</sd> that cannot see and cannot hear and cannot eat and cannot smell. </vn><vn id="Dt 4:29">But from there you shall seek Yahweh your God and will find him, if you seek him with all your heart and with all your soul.<n><io>Or “inner self”</io></n> </vn><im><vn id="Dt 4:30">In your distress</vn></im><n><io>Literally “In <sd>the</sd> distress for you”</io></n><vn id="Dt 4:30"> when<n><io>Hebrew “and”</io></n> all these things have found you in the <im>latter days</im>,<n><io>Literally “in the last of the days”</io></n> then<n><io>Hebrew “and”</io></n> you will return to Yahweh your God, and you will listen to his voice. </vn><vn id="Dt 4:31">For Yahweh your God is a compassionate God; he <im>will not abandon you</im>,<n><io>Literally “will not leave you alone”</io></n> and he will not destroy you, and he will not forget the covenant of your ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> that he swore to them. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 4:32">“Yes, ask, please, about former days that <im>preceded you</im><n><io>Literally “that <sd>they</sd> were to the face of you”</io></n> from the day that God created humankind on the earth; <sd>ask even</sd> from <sd>one</sd> end of the heaven up to the <sd>other</sd> end of heaven <im>whether anything ever happened</im><n><io>Literally “was it <sd>ever</sd>”</io></n> like this great thing or <im>whether anything like it was ever heard</im>.<n><io>Literally “was it <sd>ever</sd> heard as it”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 4:33">Has a people <sd>ever</sd> heard the voice of God speaking from the midst of the fire, <sd>just</sd> as you heard <sd>it</sd>, and lived? </vn><vn id="Dt 4:34">Or has a god <sd>ever</sd> attempted to go to take for himself<n><io>Hebrew “for him”</io></n> a nation from the midst of a nation, <sd>using</sd> trials and signs and wonders and war, with an outstretched arm and with great and awesome deeds, like all that Yahweh your God did for you in Egypt before your eyes? </vn><vn id="Dt 4:35">You <sd>yourselves</sd><n><io>Emphatic use of pronoun; plural meaning implied</io></n> were shown <sd>this wonder</sd> in order <sd>for you</sd> to acknowledge that Yahweh <sd>is</sd> the God;<n><io>The definite article indicates that Israel’s God is alone the true God and the one who revealed himself to them</io></n> there is no other <sd>God</sd> <im>besides him</im>.<n><io>Literally “except him” or “to him alone”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 4:36">From heaven he made you hear his voice to teach you, and on the earth he showed you his great fire, and you heard his words from the midst of the fire. </vn><vn id="Dt 4:37">And because he loved your ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> he chose their <im>descendants</im><n><io>Literally “seed”</io></n> after them. And he brought you forth from Egypt <im>with his own presence</im>,<n><io>Literally “with his faces”</io></n> by his great strength, </vn><vn id="Dt 4:38">to drive out nations greater and more numerous than you <im>from before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “from your face”</io></n> to bring you <sd>and</sd> to give to you their land <sd>as</sd> an inheritance, as <sd>it is</sd> this day. </vn><vn id="Dt 4:39">So you shall acknowledge <im>today</im>,<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> and <im>you must call to mind</im><n><io>Literally “you shall bring back to your heart”</io></n> that Yahweh <sd>is</sd> God in heaven above and on the earth beneath. There is no other <sd>God</sd>. </vn><vn id="Dt 4:40">And you shall keep his rules and his commandments that I am commanding you <im>today</im>,<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> <sd>so</sd> that <im>it may go well</im><n><io>Literally “he/it is good”</io></n> for you and for your children<n><io>Or “descendants”</io></n> after you, and so that <im>you may remain a long time</im><n><io>Literally “you may make long/prolong days”</io></n> on the land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you <sd>during</sd> all <sd>of</sd> those days.” </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 4:41">Then Moses set apart three cities <im>on the other side of the Jordan</im>,<n><io>Literally “<sd>in the</sd> beyond <sd>of</sd> the Jordan”</io></n> <im>toward the east</im>,<n><io>Literally “toward rising of the sun”</io></n> </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 4:42">in order for</vn></sd> <im><vn id="Dt 4:42">a manslayer</vn></im><n><io>Literally “a killer of a man”</io></n><vn id="Dt 4:42"> to flee there <sd>who</sd> has killed his neighbor <im>without intent</im><n><io>Literally “without <sd>previous</sd> knowledge”</io></n> and was not hating him <im>previously</im>,<n><io>Literally “<sd>the</sd> day before yesterday”</io></n> and <sd>so</sd> he could flee to one of these cities <im>and be safe</im>.<n><io>Literally “and live”</io></n> </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 4:43">He set apart</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 4:43"> Bezer in the wilderness<n><io>Or “desert”</io></n> in the land of the plateau of the Reubenites;<n><io>Hebrew “Reubenite”</io></n> Ramoth in Gilead of the Gadites,<n><io>Hebrew “Gadite”</io></n> and Golan in Bashan of the Manassites.<n><io>Hebrew “Manassite”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 4:44">Now this <sd>is</sd> the law<n><io>Hebrew “the <i>torah</i>” = teaching, instruction, law</io></n> that Moses set <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “before the faces of”</io></n> the <im>Israelites</im>;<n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 4:45">these are the legal provisions and the rules and the regulations that Moses spoke to the <im>Israelites</im><n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> <im>when they left Egypt</im>,<n><io>Literally “at their going out from Egypt”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 4:46">beyond the Jordan in the valley opposite Beth Peor in the land of Sihon the king of the Amorites,<n><io>Hebrew “Amorite”</io></n> who <sd>was</sd> reigning in Heshbon <sd>and</sd> whom Moses and the <im>Israelites</im><n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> defeated <im>when they came out of Egypt</im>.<n><io>Literally “at their going out from Egypt”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 4:47">And <sd>so</sd> they took possession of his land and the land of Og king of Bashan, the two kings of the Amorites<n><io>Hebrew “Amorite”</io></n> who <sd>were</sd> beyond the Jordan, <im>eastward</im>,<n><io>Literally “toward the rising of the sun”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 4:48">from Aroer, which <sd>is</sd> on the bank of the wadi<n><io>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</io></n> of Arnon and as far as Mount Sirion; that <sd>is</sd>, Hermon, </vn><vn id="Dt 4:49">and all <sd>of</sd> the Arabah<n><io>Or “valley” in this instance</io></n> beyond the Jordan, eastward, and as far as the Sea of the Arabah<n><io>Commonly known today as the Dead Sea</io></n> under the slopes of Pisgah. </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 5"> <pericope>Basic Stipulations</pericope> <pa><vn id="Dt 5:1">And <sd>then</sd> Moses summoned all <sd>of</sd> Israel and said to them, “Hear, Israel, the rules and the regulations that I <sd>am</sd> speaking in your ears <im>today</im>,<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> and you shall learn them, and <im>you must observe them diligently</im>.<n><io>Literally “you shall observe them carefully to do them”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 5:2">Yahweh our God made a covenant with us at Horeb. </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 5:3">It was</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 5:3"> not with our ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> <sd>that</sd> Yahweh made this covenant, <sd>but with</sd> these <sd>of</sd> us <sd>who are</sd> here alive today. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 5:4">Face to face</vn></im><n><io>Literally “Faces to faces”</io></n><vn id="Dt 5:4"> Yahweh spoke with you at the mountain from the midst of the fire. </vn><vn id="Dt 5:5">I was standing <im>between Yahweh and you</im><n><io>Literally “between Yahweh and between you”</io></n> at that time to report<n><io>Or “declare”</io></n> to you the word of Yahweh, for you were afraid because of <im>the presence of</im><n><io>Literally “the faces of”</io></n> the fire, and <sd>so</sd> you <sd>did</sd> not go up the mountain. <im>He said</im>,<n><io>Literally “To say”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 5:6">‘I <sd>am</sd> Yahweh your God, who brought you out from the land of Egypt, from the house of slavery. </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 5:7">There</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 5:7"> shall not be for you other gods <im>besides me</im>.<n><io>Literally “before my face”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 5:8">‘You shall not make for yourself a divine image of any <sd>type</sd> of form that <sd>is</sd> in the heaven above or that <sd>is</sd> on the earth beneath or that <sd>is</sd> in the water under the earth. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 5:9">‘You shall not bow down to them, and you shall not serve them, for I, Yahweh your God, <sd>am</sd> a jealous God, punishing the guilt of fathers upon <sd>their</sd> children and upon <sd>the</sd> third and upon <sd>the</sd> fourth generation of <sd>those</sd> hating me, </vn><vn id="Dt 5:10">but showing loyal love to thousands of <sd>those who</sd> love me and of <sd>those who</sd> keep my commandments. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 5:11">‘You shall not take up the name of Yahweh your God for <sd>a</sd> worthless purpose, for Yahweh will not leave unpunished <sd>anyone</sd> who uses his name for <sd>a</sd> worthless purpose. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 5:12">‘Observe the <im>Sabbath day</im><n><io>Literally “the day of the Sabbath”</io></n> to make it holy,<n><io>Or “to sanctify it”</io></n> <sd>just</sd> as Yahweh your God has commanded you. </vn><vn id="Dt 5:13">Six days you shall work, and you shall do all <sd>of</sd> your work, </vn><vn id="Dt 5:14">but the seventh day <sd>is</sd> <sd>a</sd> Sabbath unto Yahweh your God; you shall not do any work, or your son, or your daughter, or your slave, or your slave woman, or your ox, or your donkey, or any of your domestic animals, or your <sd>resident</sd> alien who <sd>is</sd> in your <im>towns</im>,<n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> so that your slave and your slave woman may rest as you <sd>rest</sd>. </vn><vn id="Dt 5:15">And you shall remember that you were a slave in the land of Egypt, and Yahweh your God brought you out with a strong hand and with an outstretched arm; therefore, Yahweh your God commanded you to keep <im>the Sabbath</im>.<n><io>Literally “the day of the Sabbath”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 5:16">‘Honor your father and your mother, as Yahweh your God commanded you, so that it will be good for you<n><io>Or “it may go well for you”</io></n> <im>in the land</im><n><io>Literally “on the ground”</io></n> that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 5:17">‘You shall not murder. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 5:18">‘And you shall not commit adultery. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 5:19">‘And you shall not steal. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 5:20">‘And you shall not falsely bear evidence against your neighbor. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 5:21">‘And you shall not covet the wife of your neighbor, and you shall not crave the house of your neighbor, his field or his slave or his slave woman or his ox and his donkey or anything <im>that belongs to your neighbor</im>.’<n><io>Literally “that <sd>is</sd> for your neighbor”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 5:22">“These words Yahweh spoke to your whole assembly at the mountain from the midst of the fire and the very thick cloud <sd>with</sd> a loud voice, and <im>he did not add anything</im>,<n><io>Literally “and not he added”</io></n> and <sd>then</sd> he wrote them on two tablets of stone and gave them to me. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 5:23">And then</vn></im><n><io>Literally “And it happened”</io></n> <im><vn id="Dt 5:23">when you heard</vn></im><n><io>Literally “and as/when you heard” or “<sd>at</sd> the moment of your hearing”</io></n><vn id="Dt 5:23"> the voice from the midst of the darkness, and <sd>as</sd> the mountain <sd>was</sd> burning with fire, and <sd>and</sd> all the heads of your tribes and your elders approached me, </vn><vn id="Dt 5:24">you said, ‘Look, Yahweh our God has shown us his glory and his greatness, and we have heard his voice from the midst of the fire; this day we have seen<n><io>Or “saw”</io></n> that God can speak with a human being, <im>yet he remains alive</im>.<n><io>Literally “and <sd>he</sd> lives”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 5:25">And so then why shall we die, for this great fire will consume us if <im>we continue</im><n><io>Literally “we do again to hear”; or “we are doing again to hear”</io></n> to hear the voice of Yahweh our God <sd>any</sd> longer, and <sd>so</sd> we shall die? </vn><vn id="Dt 5:26">For who <sd>is there of</sd> all flesh who has heard the voice of the living God speaking from the midst of the fire as we <sd>have heard it</sd> <im>and remained alive</im>?<n><io>Literally “and lives”</io></n> </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 5:27">You</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 5:27"> go near and hear <im>everything</im><n><io>Literally “all of <sd>that</sd> which”</io></n> that Yahweh our God will say; and <sd>then</sd> you tell us all that Yahweh our God tells you, and we will listen, and we will do <sd>it</sd>.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 5:28">“And Yahweh heard the sound of your words <im>when you spoke to me</im>,<n><io>Literally “in/at you to speak to me”</io></n> and Yahweh said to me, ‘I have heard the sound of the words of this people that they have spoken to you; <sd>they</sd> are right <sd>with respect to</sd> all that they have spoken. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 5:29">If only</vn></im><n><io>Literally “Who gives/will give”</io></n> <im><vn id="Dt 5:29">they had such a mind</vn></im><vn id="Dt 5:29">’;<n><io>Literally “<sd>it</sd> would be their heart this to them”</io></n> <sd>that is</sd>, to fear me and to keep all my commandments <im>at all times</im>,<n><io>Literally “all the days”</io></n> so that <im>it will go well</im><n><io>Literally “he/it is good”</io></n> for them and for their children <im>forever</im>.<n><io>Literally “to eternity”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 5:30">Go! Say to them, “Return to your tents.” </vn><vn id="Dt 5:31">But you stand here with me, and let me tell you all <sd>of</sd> the commandments and the rules and the regulations that you shall teach them, so that they may do <sd>them</sd> in the land that I <sd>am</sd> giving to them to take possession of it.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 5:32">“<sd>So</sd> you must be careful to do <sd>just</sd> as Yahweh your God commanded you; you shall not turn <sd>to the</sd> right or <sd>to the</sd> left. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 5:33">In exactly the path</vn></im><n><io>Literally “In all the way/path”</io></n><vn id="Dt 5:33"> that Yahweh your God has commanded, you must go, so that you may live and <im>it will go well</im><n><io>Literally “and good <sd>it is</sd>”</io></n> for you and <im>you may live long</im><n><io>Literally “you may make long”</io></n> in the land that you will take possession of.” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 6"> <pericope>Detailed Stipulations</pericope> <pa><vn id="Dt 6:1">“Now this <sd>is</sd> the commandment, the rules and the regulations, that Yahweh your God charged to teach <sd>to</sd> you <sd>for you</sd> <im>to observe</im><n><io>Literally “to do”</io></n> in the land that you <sd>are</sd> about to cross <sd>over</sd> into<n><io>Or “there”</io></n> to take possession of it, </vn><vn id="Dt 6:2">so that you may revere Yahweh your God by keeping all his statutes and his commandments that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you, you and your children and <im>grandchildren</im>,<n><io>Literally “the children of your children”</io></n> all the days of your life and so you may live long<n><io>Literally “they may be long your days”</io></n> <sd>lives</sd>. </vn><vn id="Dt 6:3">And you shall hear, Israel, and be careful to observe <sd>these instructions</sd>, so that <im>it may go well for you</im><n><io>Literally “it/he may be good”</io></n> and that you may multiply greatly, <sd>just</sd> as Yahweh, the God of your ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> <im>promised</im><n><io>Literally “spoke”</io></n> you, <sd>in</sd> a land with milk and honey. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 6:4">“Hear, Israel, Yahweh our God, Yahweh is unique.<n><io>Or “one”; or possibly “one Lord”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 6:5">And you shall love Yahweh your God with all of your heart<n><io>Or “mind”</io></n> and with all of your soul<n><io>Or “inner self”</io></n> and with all of your might. </vn><vn id="Dt 6:6">And these words that I am commanding you <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> shall be on<n><io>Or “in”</io></n> your heart.<n><io>Or “mind”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 6:7">And you shall recite them to your children, and you shall talk about them at <sd>the time of</sd> your living in your house and at <sd>the time of</sd> your going on the road and at <sd>the time of</sd> your lying down and at <sd>the time of</sd> your rising <sd>up</sd>. </vn><vn id="Dt 6:8">And you shall bind them as a sign on your hand, and they shall be as an emblem between your eyes. </vn><vn id="Dt 6:9">And you shall write them on the doorframe of your house and on your gates. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 6:10">“And then it will happen <sd>that</sd> when Yahweh your God will bring you to the land that he swore to your ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give to you large and fine cities that you did not build, </vn><vn id="Dt 6:11">and houses full of all <sd>sorts</sd> of good things<n><io>Hebrew “thing”</io></n> that you did not fill, and hewn cisterns that you did not hew, vineyards and olive groves that you did not plant, and <im>you have eaten your fill</im>,<n><io>Literally “you have eaten and you are satisfied”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 6:12">then take care for yourself, so that you <sd>do</sd> not forget Yahweh, who brought you out from the land of Egypt from the house of slavery. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 6:13">“You shall fear Yahweh your God, and you shall serve him, and by his name you shall swear. </vn><vn id="Dt 6:14">You shall not go after other gods from the gods of the peoples who <sd>are</sd> all around you, </vn><vn id="Dt 6:15">for Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> a jealous god in your midst, <im>so that the anger of Yahweh your God would be kindled</im>,<n><io>Literally “so that not/lest the nose of Yahweh your God would become hot”</io></n> and he would destroy you from the face of the earth. </vn><vn id="Dt 6:16">You shall not put Yahweh your God to <sd>the</sd> test, as you tested <sd>him</sd> at Massah. </vn><vn id="Dt 6:17">You shall diligently keep the commandments of Yahweh your God and his legal provisions and his rules that he has commanded you. </vn><vn id="Dt 6:18">And you shall do <sd>what is</sd> right and good in the eyes of Yahweh, so that <im>it shall go well</im><n><io>Literally “he/it shall be good”</io></n> for you and <sd>so that</sd> you may go and you may take possession of the good land that Yahweh swore for your ancestors,<n><io>Or “your fathers”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 6:19">by driving out all <sd>of</sd> your enemies <im>before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “the face of you”</io></n> <sd>just</sd> as Yahweh <im>has promised</im>.<n><io>Literally “had spoken”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 6:20">“When your child<n><io>Or “son”</io></n> asks you in the future, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘What <sd>is the meaning of</sd> the legal provisions and the rules and the regulations that Yahweh our God commanded for you?’ </vn><vn id="Dt 6:21">Then you shall say to your child,<n><io>Or “son”</io></n> ‘We were slaves of Pharaoh in Egypt, and Yahweh brought us out from Egypt with a strong hand. </vn><vn id="Dt 6:22">And Yahweh gave great and awesome signs and wonders in Egypt against Pharaoh and against his entire household <im>in our presence</im>.<n><io>Literally “before our eyes”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 6:23">But <sd>he</sd> brought us out from there in order to bring us <sd>here</sd> to give us the land that he swore to our ancestors.<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 6:24">And <sd>so</sd> Yahweh commanded us to observe all <sd>of</sd> these rules <sd>and</sd> to revere Yahweh our God <im>for our benefit</im><n><io>Literally “for good for us”</io></n> <im>all the days that we live</im>,<n><io>Literally “all the days for our living”</io></n> <im>as it is today</im>.<n><io>Literally “as the day the this”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 6:25">And it shall be righteousness for us if we diligently observe <sd>and</sd> do all <sd>of</sd> this commandment <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “in the faces of”</io></n> Yahweh our God, as he has commanded us.’ </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 7"> <pa><vn id="Dt 7:1"> “When Yahweh your God brings you into the land that you <sd>are</sd> about to enter <im>into it</im><n><io>Literally “there”</io></n> to take possession of it, and he drives<n><io>Or “he will drive out”</io></n> out many nations <im>before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “from your faces”</io></n> the Hittites<n><io>Hebrew “Hittite”</io></n> and the Girgashites<n><io>Hebrew “Girgashite”</io></n> and the Amorites<n><io>Hebrew “Amorite”</io></n> and the Canaanites<n><io>Hebrew “Canaanite”</io></n> and the Hivites<n><io>Hebrew “Hivite”</io></n> and the Jebusites,<n><io>Hebrew “Jebusite”</io></n> seven nations mightier and more numerous than you, </vn><vn id="Dt 7:2">and Yahweh your God will give them <im>over to you</im><n><io>Literally “to your faces” or “before you”</io></n> and you defeat them, you must <im>utterly destroy them</im>;<n><io>Literally “set them aside for destruction”</io></n> you shall not make a covenant with them, and you shall not show mercy <sd>to them</sd>. </vn><vn id="Dt 7:3">And you shall not intermarry with them; you shall not give your daughter to their son; and you shall not take his daughter for your son.<n><io>Grammatically singular pronominal suffixes here can also be rendered “their”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 7:4">For their<n><io>Or “his”</io></n> sons and daughters will cause your son<n><io>Or “sons”</io></n> to turn away <im>from following me</im>,<n><io>Literally from “behind/after me”</io></n> and <sd>so</sd> they will serve other gods, and <im>the anger of Yahweh would be kindled</im><n><io>Literally “and <sd>it</sd> would become hot the nose of Yahweh”</io></n> against you, and he would quickly destroy you. </vn><vn id="Dt 7:5">But this is what you must do to them: you shall break down their altars, and their stone pillars you shall smash, and their Asherah poles you shall hew down, and you shall burn their idols with fire. </vn><vn id="Dt 7:6">For you <sd>are</sd> a holy people for Yahweh your God; Yahweh your God has chosen you to be for him a people, a treasured possession from <sd>among</sd> all the peoples that <sd>are</sd> on the face<n><io>Or “surface”</io></n> of the earth. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 7:7">“Yahweh loved you and chose you not <im>because of your great number</im><n><io>Literally “from your multitude/abundance”</io></n> exceeding all <sd>other</sd> peoples, for you <sd>are</sd> fewer than all of the peoples, </vn><vn id="Dt 7:8">but<n><io>Or “for”</io></n> <im>because of</im><n><io>Literally “from”</io></n> the love of Yahweh <sd>for</sd> you and because of his keeping <sd>of</sd> the sworn oath that he swore to your ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> Yahweh brought you <sd>out</sd> with a strong hand and redeemed you from the house of slavery, from the hand of Pharaoh, the king of Egypt. </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 7:9">So</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 7:9"> know that Yahweh your God, he <sd>is</sd> God, the trustworthy God, maintaining his<n><io>Hebrew “the”</io></n> covenant and his<n><io>Hebrew “the”</io></n> loyal love with those who love him and with those who keep his commandments to a thousand generations,<n><io>Hebrew “generation”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 7:10">but repaying those<n><io>Hebrew “the one”</io></n> who hate him <im>in their own person</im><n><io>Literally “to their faces”</io></n> to destroy them;<n><io>Hebrew “him”; “them” in sense</io></n> he is not slow with those who hate him <im>in their own person</im>;<n><io>Literally “to their faces”</io></n> he repays them.<n><io>Hebrew “him”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 7:11">And <sd>so</sd> you shall keep the commandment and the rules and the regulations that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> to observe them. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 7:12">“<im>And then</im><n><io>Literally “And it will happen”</io></n> because you listen <sd>to</sd> these regulations and you diligently keep and you do them, then Yahweh your God will maintain his<n><io>Hebrew “the”</io></n> covenant and his<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> loyal love that he swore to your ancestors.<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 7:13">And he will love you, and he will bless you, and he will multiply you, and he will bless the fruit of your womb and the fruit of your soil, your grain, your wine, and your olive oil, and <sd>newborn</sd> calves of your cattle, and the <sd>newborn</sd> lambs<n><io>Or “increase of”</io></n> of your flocks in the land that he swore to your ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> to give you. </vn><vn id="Dt 7:14">You shall be blessed more than all of the peoples; among you there shall not be sterility and bareness, even<n><io>Hebrew “and”</io></n> among domestic animals.<n><io>Hebrew “animal”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 7:15">And Yahweh will turn away from you all the illness and all the harmful diseases of Egypt that you experienced; he will not lay them on you, but he will lay them on all <sd>of</sd> those who hate you. </vn><vn id="Dt 7:16">And you shall devour all of the peoples <sd>that</sd> Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you; <im>you shall not pity them</im>,<n><io>Literally “your eye shall not take pity on them”</io></n> and you shall not serve their gods, <sd>which</sd> will be a snare for you. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 7:17">“If you think in your heart, ‘These nations <sd>are</sd> more numerous than I, so how can I dispossess them?’ </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 7:18">then remember</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 7:18"> you must not be afraid of them; you must well remember what Yahweh your God did to Pharaoh and to all <sd>of</sd> Egypt: </vn><vn id="Dt 7:19">the great trials that your eyes saw and the signs and the wonders and the <sd>workings of</sd> the strong hand and the outstretched arm <sd>by</sd> which Yahweh your God brought you out; so Yahweh your God will do to all <sd>of</sd> the peoples <im>because of whom</im><n><io>Literally “from them”</io></n> you <sd>are</sd> in fear <im>before them</im>.<n><io>Literally “from their presence”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 7:20">And, moreover, Yahweh your God will send the hornets<n><io>Hebrew “hornet”</io></n> among them until <sd>both</sd> the survivors and the fugitives <im>are destroyed</im><n><io>Literally “the destroying of”</io></n> <im>before you</im>.<n><io>Literally “from your faces”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 7:21">You must not <sd>be in dread</sd> from the presence of them, because Yahweh your God, <sd>who is</sd> in your midst, <sd>is</sd> a great and awesome God. </vn><vn id="Dt 7:22">And Yahweh your God will clear away these nations <im>from before you</im><n><io>Literally “from your faces”</io></n> little by little; you will not be able to finish them off quickly, <im>lest</im><n><io>Literally “so that not”</io></n> the <im>wild animals</im><n><io>Literally “animals of the field”</io></n> <im>multiply</im><n><io>Literally “will become numerous”</io></n> <im>against you</im>.<n><io>Literally “on you”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 7:23">But Yahweh your God will <im>give them to you</im>,<n><io>Literally “give them to your face”</io></n> and he will throw them into great panic <im>until they are destroyed</im>.<n><io>Literally “until their destroying”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 7:24">And he will give their kings into your hand, and you shall blot out their names<n><io>Hebrew “name”</io></n> from under the heaven; anyone will not <sd>be able to</sd> stand <im>against you</im><n><io>Literally “in your faces”</io></n> <im>until you destroy them</im>.<n><io>Literally “until your destroying them”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 7:25">You shall burn the images of their gods with fire; you shall not covet <sd>the</sd> silver or gold <sd>that is</sd> on them, and <sd>so</sd> you take <sd>it</sd> for yourself, so that you are not ensnared by it, for it <sd>is</sd> a detestable thing to Yahweh your God. </vn><vn id="Dt 7:26">And you must not bring a detestable thing into your house, or you will become a thing devoted to destruction like it; you must utterly detest it, and you must utterly abhor it, for it <sd>is</sd> <sd>an</sd> object devoted to destruction. </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 8"> <pa><vn id="Dt 8:1"> “All of the commandments<n><io>Or “every commandment”</io></n> that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you today you must diligently observe, so that you may live and multiply, and you may go and take possession of the land that Yahweh swore to your ancestors.<n><io>Or “your fathers”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 8:2">And you shall remember all <sd>of</sd> the way that Yahweh your God led you <sd>during</sd> these forty years in the desert in order to humble you and to test you to know what <sd>is</sd> in your heart, whether you would <sd>diligently</sd> keep his commandments or not. </vn><vn id="Dt 8:3">And he humbled you and let you go hungry, and <sd>then</sd> he fed you with that which you did not know nor did your ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> know, in order to make you know that not by bread alone but by all <sd>that</sd> goes out<n><io>Or “by all <sd>of</sd> the going out of”</io></n> of the mouth of Yahweh humankind shall live. </vn><vn id="Dt 8:4">Your clothing did not wear out <im>on you</im>,<n><io>Literally “from on you”</io></n> and your feet did not swell <sd>during</sd> these forty years. </vn><vn id="Dt 8:5">And you should know with your heart that as a man disciplines his son, <sd>so</sd> Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> disciplining you.<n><io>Or “has disciplined you”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 8:6">So you must keep the commandments of Yahweh your God by walking in his ways and by fearing him. </vn><vn id="Dt 8:7">For Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> bringing you to a good land <sd>with</sd> streams of water, springs and underground water, welling up in the valleys<n><io>Hebrew “valley”</io></n> and in the hills,<n><io>Hebrew “hill”</io></n> </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 8:8">to</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 8:8"> a land of wheat and barley and vines<n><io>Hebrew “vine”</io></n> and fig trees<n><io>Hebrew “fig tree”</io></n> and pomegranate trees,<n><io>Hebrew “pomegranate tree”</io></n> a land of olive trees,<n><io>Hebrew “olive tree”</io></n> olive oil and honey; </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 8:9">to</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 8:9"> a land where you may eat food in it <im>without scarcity</im>;<n><io>Literally “not in scarcity”</io></n> you will not find anything lacking in it, a land where its stones <sd>are</sd> iron and from its mountains you can mine copper. </vn><vn id="Dt 8:10">And you will eat, and <im>you will be satisfied</im>,<n><io>Literally “you will eat your fill”</io></n> and you will bless Yahweh your God because <sd>of</sd> the good land that he has given to you. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 8:11">“Take care for yourself so that you not forget Yahweh your God <sd>by</sd> not keeping his commandments and his regulations and his statutes that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>today</im>,<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 8:12">lest <sd>when</sd> you have eaten and you are satisfied and you have built good houses and you live <sd>in them</sd>, </vn><vn id="Dt 8:13">and your herds and your flocks have multiplied, and <im>you have accumulated silver and gold</im>,<n><io>Literally “and silver and gold has multiplied for you”</io></n> and all that <im>you have</im><n><io>Literally “is for you”</io></n> has multiplied, </vn><vn id="Dt 8:14">then your heart <im>becomes proud</im><n><io>Literally “raises up”</io></n> and you forget Yahweh your God, <im>the one who brought you out</im><n><io>Literally “the one bringing you out”</io></n> from the land of Egypt, from the house of slavery, </vn><vn id="Dt 8:15">the one leading you in the great and terrible desert <sd>infested</sd> with <im>dangerous</im><n><io>Literally “burning”</io></n> snakes<n><io>Hebrew “snake”</io></n> and scorpions<n><io>Hebrew “scorpion”</io></n> and parched ground, where there is<n><io>Or “was”</io></n> no water, <sd>and</sd> the one bringing out water for you from flint rock, </vn><vn id="Dt 8:16">the one <im>feeding you</im><n><io>Literally “causing you to eat”</io></n> manna in the desert, <sd>food</sd> that your ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> did not know, in order to humble you and in order to test you <sd>so that he could</sd> do good to you <im>in the future</im>.<n><io>Literally “in the end/later”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 8:17">And you may think<n><io>Or “say”</io></n> in your heart, ‘My strength and the might of my hand <im>acquired this wealth for</im><n><io>Literally “gave this wealth to”</io></n> me.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 8:18">But you must remember Yahweh your God, for he <sd>is</sd> the <sd>one</sd> giving you strength to acquire wealth in order to confirm his covenant that he swore to your ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> <im>as it is today</im>.<n><io>Literally “as the day the this”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 8:19">And it will happen <sd>that</sd> if you indeed forget Yahweh your God and you go after other gods and you serve them and you bow down before them, I warn you today that you will surely perish. </vn><vn id="Dt 8:20">As <sd>with</sd> the nations that Yahweh <sd>is</sd> destroying <im>before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “from your faces”</io></n> so you shall perish because you would not obey the voice of Yahweh your God. </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 9"> <pa><vn id="Dt 9:1"> “Hear, Israel, you <sd>are</sd> about to cross the Jordan today to go to dispossess nations larger and more numerous than you, great cities fortified <im>with high walls</im>,<n><io>Literally “in heaven/the sky”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 9:2">a great and tall people, the sons of <sd>the</sd> Anakites, whom you know and <sd>of whom you</sd> have heard <sd>it said</sd>, ‘Who could stand before the sons of Anak?’ </vn><vn id="Dt 9:3">You should know <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> that Yahweh your God is the one crossing <im>ahead of you</im><n><io>Literally “to your faces”</io></n> <sd>as</sd> a devouring fire; he will destroy them, and he will subdue them before you; so you will dispossess them, and you will destroy them quickly, <im>just as</im><n><io>Literally “as that”</io></n> Yahweh <im>promised</im><n><io>Literally “spoke”</io></n> you. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 9:4">“You shall not say <im>to yourself</im><n><io>Literally “in your heart”</io></n> <im>when Yahweh your God is driving them out</im><n><io>Literally “at the driving out of Yahweh, your God, them”</io></n> <im>before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “from before your faces”</io></n> <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘Because of my righteousness Yahweh brought me to take possession of this land’; but because of the wickedness of these nations Yahweh <sd>is</sd> driving them out <im>before you</im>.<n><io>Literally “from your faces”</io></n> </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 9:5">It is</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 9:5"> not because of your righteousness and because of the uprightness of your heart <sd>that</sd> you <sd>are</sd> coming to take possession of their land, but because of the wickedness of these nations Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> driving them <im>before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “from your faces”</io></n> and in order to confirm the <im>promise</im><n><io>Literally “word”</io></n> that Yahweh swore to your ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 9:6">“So you should understand that <sd>it is</sd> not because of your righteousness <sd>that</sd> Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving you this good land to take possession of it, because <im>you are a stubborn people</im>. <n><io>Literally “a people stiff of neck you”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 9:7">Remember, <im>do not forget</im>,<n><io>Literally “not you shall forget”</io></n> that you provoked Yahweh your God in the desert, <sd>and</sd> from the day that you went out from the land of Egypt until <im>you came to this place</im><n><io>Literally “your coming up to this place the this” = until arrived at this location</io></n> you were rebelling against Yahweh. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 9:8">“And <sd>remember</sd> at Horeb you provoked Yahweh, and Yahweh became angry <sd>enough</sd> to destroy you. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 9:9">When I went up the mountain</vn></im><n><io>Literally “In/At my going up the mountain”</io></n><vn id="Dt 9:9"> to receive <im>the stone tablets</im>,<n><io>Literally “the tablets of stones”</io></n> the tablets of the covenant that Yahweh <im>made</im><n><io>Literally “cut”</io></n> with you, and remained on the mountain forty days<n><io>Hebrew “day”</io></n> and forty nights,<n><io>Hebrew “night”</io></n> I did not eat food and I did not drink water. </vn><vn id="Dt 9:10">And Yahweh gave me the two tablets of stone written with the finger of God, and on them <sd>was writing</sd> according to all the words that Yahweh spoke with you at the mountain, from the midst of the fire on the day of the assembly. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 9:11">And then</vn></im><n><io>Literally “And it happened”</io></n><vn id="Dt 9:11"> at the end of forty days<n><io>Hebrew “day”</io></n> and forty nights,<n><io>Hebrew “night”</io></n> Yahweh gave me the two tablets of stone, the tablets of the covenant. </vn><vn id="Dt 9:12">And Yahweh said to me, ‘Come <sd>now</sd>, go down quickly from this mountain because your people behave corruptly whom you brought out from Egypt, <sd>for</sd> they turned quickly from the way that I commanded them <sd>to follow</sd>; they have made for themselves a cast image.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 9:13">And Yahweh spoke to me, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘I have seen this people, and look! <im>They are a stubborn people</im>.<n><io>Literally “It is a people stiff of neck”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 9:14">Leave me alone, and let me destroy them, and let me blot out their name from under heaven, and let me make you into a nation mightier and more numerous than they!’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 9:15">“And I turned, and I went down the mountain, as the mountain was burning with fire, and the two tablets of the covenant <sd>were</sd> in my two hands. </vn><vn id="Dt 9:16">And I looked,<n><io>Or “saw”</io></n> and indeed you had sinned against Yahweh your God; you <sd>had</sd> made for yourselves an image of a calf <sd>of</sd> cast metal; <n><io>Or “molten calf”</io></n> you <sd>had</sd> turned quickly from the way that Yahweh had commanded <sd>for</sd> you. </vn><vn id="Dt 9:17">And I took hold of the two tablets, and I threw them out <im>of</im><n><io>Literally “from”</io></n> my two hands and smashed them before your eyes. </vn><vn id="Dt 9:18">And <sd>then</sd> I lay prostrate <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> Yahweh, as earlier, forty days<n><io>Hebrew “day”</io></n> and forty nights;<n><io>Hebrew “night”</io></n> I did not eat food and I did not drink water because of all your sins that you committed, by doing evil in the eyes of Yahweh <sd>and so</sd> provoking him. </vn><vn id="Dt 9:19">For <im>I was in dread</im><n><io>Literally “I dreaded”</io></n> from <sd>being in</sd> the presence of the anger and the wrath <sd>with</sd> which Yahweh was angry with you <sd>so as</sd> to destroy you, but Yahweh listened to me also <im>at that time</im>.<n><io>Literally “the occurrence the that”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 9:20">And with Aaron Yahweh was <im>angry enough</im><n><io>Literally “very angry”</io></n> to destroy him, and I prayed also for Aaron at that time. </vn><vn id="Dt 9:21">And your sinful thing that you had made, the molten calf, I took and I burned it with fire, and I crushed it, grinding it thoroughly until it was crushed to dust, and I threw its dust into <im>the stream that flowed down the mountain</im>.<n><io>Literally “the stream the <sd>one</sd> going down from the mountain”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 9:22">“And <sd>also</sd> at Taberah and at Massah and at Kibroth Hattaavah you provoked Yahweh to anger. </vn><vn id="Dt 9:23">And when Yahweh sent you <sd>out</sd> from Kadesh Barnea, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘Go up and take possession of the land that I have given you,’ you rebelled against the command of Yahweh your God, and you did not believe him, and you did not listen to his voice. </vn><vn id="Dt 9:24">You have been rebellious toward Yahweh <im>from the day I have known you</im>.<n><io>Literally “from the day of my knowing you”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 9:25">“And I lay prostrate before Yahweh through forty days,<n><io>Hebrew “day”</io></n> and through forty nights<n><io>Hebrew “night”</io></n> I prostrated myself, because Yahweh intended to kill you. </vn><vn id="Dt 9:26">And I prayed to Yahweh, and I said, ‘Lord Yahweh, you must not destroy your people and your inheritance whom you redeemed in your greatness,<n><io>Or “your great act”</io></n> whom you brought out from Egypt with a strong hand. </vn><vn id="Dt 9:27">Remember your servants, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob; you must not <im>pay attention to</im><n><io>Literally “turn toward”</io></n> the stubbornness of this people, to their wickedness and to their sin, </vn><vn id="Dt 9:28">lest <sd>the people of</sd> the land from which you brought us out from there say, “Because Yahweh was not able to bring them to the land that he <im>promised</im><n><io>Literally “spoken”</io></n> to them and because of his hatred <sd>toward</sd> them, he has brought them out to kill them in the desert.” </vn><vn id="Dt 9:29">For they <sd>are</sd> your people and your inheritance whom you brought with your great power and with your outstretched arm.’ </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 10"> <pa><vn id="Dt 10:1"> “At that time Yahweh said to me, ‘Carve for yourself two tablets of stone <sd>just</sd> as the former <sd>ones</sd>, and come up the mountain to me, and you shall make for yourself an ark of wood. </vn><vn id="Dt 10:2">And I will write on the tablets the words that were on the former <sd>tablets</sd>, which you smashed, and you must put them in the ark.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 10:3">And <sd>so</sd> I made an ark <im>of acacia wood</im>,<n><io>Literally “of wood of acacia trees”</io></n> and I carved two tablets of stone like the former <sd>ones</sd>, and I went up the mountain <sd>with</sd> the two tablets in my hand. </vn><vn id="Dt 10:4">And he wrote upon the tablets <im>according to the first writing</im>,<n><io>Literally “as the writing the first”</io></n> the ten words that Yahweh spoke to you on the mountain from the midst of the fire on the day of the assembly, and Yahweh gave them to me. </vn><vn id="Dt 10:5">And I turned, and I came down from the mountain, and I put the tablets in the ark that I had made, and they are there, <sd>just</sd> as Yahweh commanded me. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 10:6">“And the <im>Israelites</im><n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> journeyed from <sd>the</sd> wells of Bene-Yaqan <sd>to</sd> Moserah; there Aaron died and was buried, and Eleazar, his son, served as a priest in place of him. </vn><vn id="Dt 10:7">From there they journeyed to Gudgodah, and from Gudgodah to Jotbathah, a land <sd>flowing with</sd> streams of water. </vn><vn id="Dt 10:8">At that time Yahweh set apart the tribe of Levi to carry the ark of the covenant of Yahweh to stand <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “the faces of”</io></n> Yahweh, to serve him and to bless <sd>the people</sd> in his name until this day. </vn><vn id="Dt 10:9">Therefore <im>there was not</im><n><io>Literally “it/he was not”</io></n> for Levi an allotment or an inheritance <sd>along</sd> with his brothers; <sd>rather</sd> Yahweh <sd>is</sd> his inheritance <sd>just</sd> as Yahweh your God <im>promised</im><n><io>Literally “spoke”</io></n> to him. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 10:10">And I stayed on the mountain <sd>just</sd> as <sd>during</sd> the former forty days<n><io>Hebrew “day”</io></n> and forty nights,<n><io>Hebrew “night”</io></n> and Yahweh listened to me also on that occasion;<n><io>Or “occurrence” or “that time”</io></n> Yahweh was not willing to destroy you. </vn><vn id="Dt 10:11">And Yahweh said to me, ‘Come, continue<n><io>Literally “Arise, go”</io></n> your journey <im>before the people</im>, <n><io>Literally “in the faces of the people”</io></n> so that you may go and take possession of the land that I swore to their ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> to give to them.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 10:12">And now, Israel, what <sd>is</sd> Yahweh your God asking<n><io>Or “requiring”</io></n> from you, except<n><io>Or “but only”</io></n> to revere Yahweh your God, to go<n><io>Or “to walk”</io></n> in all his ways and to love him and to serve Yahweh your God with all your heart and with all your soul,<n><io>Or “inner self”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 10:13">to keep the commandments of Yahweh and his statutes that I am commanding you today <im>for your own good</im>.<n><io>Literally “for good to you”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 10:14">Look! For to Yahweh your God <im>belong</im><n><io>Literally “is”</io></n> heaven and the <im>highest heavens</im>,<n><io>Literally “heavens of the heavens”</io></n> the earth and all that <sd>is</sd> in it. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 10:15">Yet</vn></im><n><io>Literally “Only”</io></n><vn id="Dt 10:15"> to your ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> Yahweh was very attached, <sd>so as to</sd> love them, and <sd>so</sd> he chose their offspring after them, <sd>namely</sd> you, from all the peoples, as it is <im>today</im>.<n><io>Literally “the day the this”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 10:16">So you shall circumcise the foreskin of your heart, and <im>do not be stubborn</im>.<n><io>Literally “your neck you shall not make stiff <sd>any</sd> longer”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 10:17">For Yahweh your God, he <sd>is</sd> God of the gods and Lord of the lords, the great and mighty God, the awesome <sd>one</sd> who <im>is not partial</im>,<n><io>Literally “<sd>does</sd> not lift up faces”</io></n> and he does not take bribes. </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 10:18">And he</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 10:18"> executes justice for the orphan and widow, and <sd>he is</sd> one who loves <sd>the</sd> alien, to give to them food and clothing. </vn><vn id="Dt 10:19">And you shall love the alien, for you were aliens in the land of Egypt. </vn><vn id="Dt 10:20">Yahweh your God, you shall revere him, you shall serve him, and to him you shall cling, and by his name you shall swear. </vn><vn id="Dt 10:21">He <sd>is</sd> your praise, and he <sd>is</sd> your God, who has done with you these great and awesome <sd>things</sd> that your eyes have seen. </vn><vn id="Dt 10:22">With <sd>only</sd> seventy persons your ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> went down to Egypt, but now Yahweh your God has made you as the stars of the heaven <im>with respect to multitude</im>.<n><io>Literally “as far as number”</io></n> </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 11"> <pa><vn id="Dt 11:1"> “And you shall love Yahweh your God, and you shall keep his obligations and his statutes and his regulations and his commandments <im>always</im>.<n><io>Literally “all <sd>of</sd> the days”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 11:2">And you shall realize <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> that <sd>it is</sd> not <sd>with</sd> your children who have not known and who have not seen the discipline of Yahweh your God—his greatness, his strong hand, and his outstretched arm, </vn><vn id="Dt 11:3">and his signs and his deeds that he did in the midst of Egypt to Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, and to all <sd>of</sd> his land, </vn><vn id="Dt 11:4">and what he did to the army of Egypt and to their horses and to their chariots, <sd>and</sd> how he made the water of the <im>Red Sea</im><n><io>Literally “sea of reed”</io></n> flow over them, <im>when they pursued after them</im>,<n><io>Literally “in/at their pursuing after them”</io></n> and so Yahweh has destroyed them, <im>as is the case today</im>,<n><io>Literally “until the day the this”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 11:5">and what he did to you in the desert until you came up to this place, </vn><vn id="Dt 11:6">and what he did to Dathan and to Abiram, the sons of Eliab, the son of Reuben, how the earth opened its mouth wide and swallowed them, their households and their tents, and all <sd>of</sd> the living creatures<n><io>Hebrew “creature”</io></n> that <sd>were</sd> in their possession <sd>and that were</sd> <im>following along with them</im><n><io>Literally “in their feet” = “living things traveling along with them”</io></n> in the midst of all <sd>of</sd> Israel. </vn><vn id="Dt 11:7">The fact of the matter is, <im>your own eyes have seen</im><n><io>Literally “your eyes that are seeing”</io></n> all <sd>of</sd> the great deeds<n><io>Hebrew “deed”</io></n> of Yahweh that he did. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 11:8">“And you must keep all <sd>of</sd> the commandments<n><io>Hebrew “commandment”</io></n> that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>today</im>,<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> so that you may have strength and <sd>you may</sd> go and <sd>you may</sd> take possession of that land <im>to which you are crossing</im><n><io>Literally “you are crossing there”</io></n> to take possession of it, </vn><vn id="Dt 11:9">so that <im>you may live long</im><n><io>Literally “you may make long days”</io></n> on the land that Yahweh swore to your ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> to give <sd>it</sd> to them and to their offspring, a land flowing with milk and honey. </vn><vn id="Dt 11:10">For the fact is <sd>that</sd> the land <im>that you are about to go into</im><n><io>Literally “you are about to go there”</io></n> to take possession of it <sd>is</sd> not like the land of Egypt, <sd>from</sd> which you have <im>come out of</im>,<n><io>Literally “come out from there”</io></n> where you sow your seed and you give water by <sd>your</sd> foot, <im>as in a vegetable garden</im>.<n><io>Literally “as <sd>the</sd> garden of <sd>the</sd> vegetables”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 11:11">But the land that you <sd>are</sd> about to cross into to take possession of it <sd>is</sd> a land of hills and valleys, <sd>and</sd> by the rain of the heaven it drinks water, </vn><vn id="Dt 11:12">a land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> caring for it; continually the eyes of Yahweh your God <sd>are</sd> on it, from the beginning of the year up to the end of <sd>the</sd> year. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 11:13">“And it will happen <sd>that</sd> if you listen carefully to my commandments that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>today</im>,<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> to love Yahweh your God, and to serve him with all <sd>of</sd> your heart and with all <sd>of</sd> your soul,<n><io>Or “inner self”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 11:14">then ‘I will send the rain for your land in its season, early rain and later rain, and you will gather your grain and your wine and your olive oil. </vn><vn id="Dt 11:15">And I will give vegetation in your field for your livestock, and <im>you will eat your fill</im>.’<n><io>Literally “you will eat and you will be satisfied”</io></n> </vn><im><vn id="Dt 11:16">Take care</vn></im><n><io>Literally “Watch for yourself”</io></n><vn id="Dt 11:16"> so that your heart is not easily deceived, and you turn away, and you serve other gods, and you bow down to them. </vn><vn id="Dt 11:17">And <sd>then</sd> <im>the anger of Yahweh will be kindled against you</im>,<n><io>Literally “the nose of Yahweh become hot against you”</io></n> and he will shut up the heavens,<n><io>Or “sky”</io></n> and there shall not be rain, and <sd>so</sd> the ground will not give its produce, and you will perish quickly from the good land that Yahweh <sd>is</sd> giving to you. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 11:18">“And you shall put these, my words, on your heart and on your inner self,<n><io>Or “soul”</io></n> and you shall bind them as a sign on your hand and let them be as an emblem between your eyes. </vn><vn id="Dt 11:19">And you shall teach them to your children<n><io>Or “sons”</io></n> by talking about them when you sit in your house and when you travel on the road and when you lie down and when you get up. </vn><vn id="Dt 11:20">And you shall write them on the doorframes of your house and on your gates, </vn><vn id="Dt 11:21">so that <sd>they</sd> may multiply your days and the days of your children on the land that Yahweh swore to your ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> to give <sd>it</sd> to them <im>as long as heaven endures over the earth</im>.<n><io>Literally “like the days of heaven above the earth”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 11:22">Yes, if you diligently keep all<n><io>Or “every one of”</io></n> this commandment that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>to observe it</im>, <n><io>Literally “to do it”</io></n> by loving Yahweh your God <im>by walking in</im><n><io>Literally “to walk in”</io></n> all his ways and by holding fast to him, </vn><vn id="Dt 11:23">then Yahweh will drive out all <sd>of</sd> these nations <im>before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “to the face of you”</io></n> and you will dispossess nations larger and more numerous than you. </vn><vn id="Dt 11:24">Every place on which the sole of your foot treads, it shall be yours; your boundary shall be from the desert and Lebanon from the river, the river Euphrates, on up to the western sea.<n><io>That is, the Mediterranean Sea</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 11:25">No one can take a stand <im>against you</im>;<n><io>Literally “to your faces”</io></n> your dread and your fear Yahweh your God will put on the <im>surface</im><n><io>Literally “faces”</io></n> of all the land <im>where you tread</im>,<n><io>Literally “which you tread in it”</io></n> <sd>just</sd> as he <im>promised</im><n><io>Literally “spoke”</io></n> to you. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 11:26">“See, I am setting <im>before you</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of you”</io></n> <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> a blessing and a curse: </vn><vn id="Dt 11:27">the blessing, if you listen to the commandments of Yahweh your God that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>today</im>,<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 11:28">and the curse, if you <sd>do</sd> not listen to the commandments of Yahweh your God, but <sd>rather</sd> you turn from the way that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> to go after other gods that you have not known. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 11:29">“And it will happen <sd>that</sd> when Yahweh your God has brought you to <im>the land that you are going to</im>,<n><io>Literally “the land that you are going there”</io></n> to take possession of it, then<n><io>Hebrew “and”</io></n> you shall pronounce the blessing on Mount Gerizim and the curse on Mount Ebal. </vn><vn id="Dt 11:30">(Are they not beyond the Jordan, <im>toward the west</im>,<n><io>Literally “after the way of the descent of the sun”</io></n> in the land of the Canaanites living in the Jordan Valley,<n><io>Hebrew “in the Arabah”</io></n> opposite Gilgal beside the terebinth<n><io>Or “oaks”</io></n> of Moreh?) </vn><vn id="Dt 11:31">For you are <sd>now</sd> about to cross the Jordan to go to take possession of the land that Yahweh, your God, <sd>is</sd> giving to you, and you will take possession of it and live in it, </vn><vn id="Dt 11:32">and you must diligently <im>observe</im><n><io>Literally “observe to do”</io></n> all the rules and the regulations that I <sd>am</sd> setting <im>before you</im><n><io>Literally “before your face”</io></n> <im>today</im>.”<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 12"> <pericope>Detailed Stipulations: Purity and Unity</pericope> <pa><vn id="Dt 12:1">“These <sd>are</sd> the rules and the regulations <im>that you must diligently observe</im><n><io>Literally “that you must observe to do”</io></n> in the land that Yahweh, <sd>the</sd> God of your ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> has given to you to take possession of it, <sd>during</sd> all the days that you <sd>are</sd> living on the land. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 12:2">You must completely demolish all <sd>of</sd> the places there where <sd>they</sd> served their gods, <sd>that is</sd>, the nations whom you <sd>are</sd> about to dispossess, on the high mountains, and on the hills and under each leafy green tree.<n><io>Or “spreading tree”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 12:3">And you shall break down their altars, and you shall smash their stone pillars, and their Asherah poles you must burn with fire, and the images of their gods you shall hew down, and you shall blot out their names from that place. </vn><vn id="Dt 12:4">You shall not worship Yahweh your God like this. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 12:5">But only</vn></im><n><io>Literally “But if”</io></n><vn id="Dt 12:5"> to the place that Yahweh your God will choose from all <sd>of</sd> your tribes to place his name there as his dwelling shall you seek, and there you shall go. </vn><vn id="Dt 12:6">And you shall bring there your burnt offerings and your sacrifices and your tithes and <im>your donations</im><n><io>Literally “the contributions of your hand”</io></n> and your votive gifts and your freewill offerings and the firstling of your herd and your flock. </vn><vn id="Dt 12:7">And you shall eat there <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “before the faces of”</io></n> Yahweh your God, and you shall rejoice <im>in all your endeavors</im>,<n><io>Literally “in all <sd>of</sd> the sending of your hand”</io></n> you and your family <sd>in</sd> which Yahweh your God has blessed you. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 12:8">“You must not do <sd>just</sd> as we <sd>are</sd> doing here <im>today</im>,<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> <im>each according to all that is right in his eyes</im>.<n><io>Literally “each <sd>man</sd> all of the right in his eyes”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 12:9">For you have not come up to now to the resting place and to the inheritance that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you. </vn><vn id="Dt 12:10">But you will cross the Jordan, and you will settle in the land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving you as an inheritance, and he will give rest to you from all your enemies from all around, and you will live securely, </vn><im><vn id="Dt 12:11">and then</vn></im><n><io>Literally “and it will happen”</io></n> <sd><vn id="Dt 12:11">at</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 12:11"> the place that Yahweh your God will choose, to let his name dwell there, there you shall bring all <sd>the things</sd> I <sd>am</sd> commanding you, your burnt offerings and your sacrifices, your tithes and <im>your donations</im>,<n><io>Literally “the contribution of your hand”</io></n> and all <sd>of</sd> the choice <sd>things</sd>, your votive gifts that you vow to Yahweh. </vn><vn id="Dt 12:12">And you shall rejoice <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “the face of”</io></n> Yahweh your God, you and your sons and your daughters and your slaves and your slave women and the Levite who <sd>is</sd> in your <im>towns</im>,<n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> because there is not for him a plot of ground and an inheritance with you. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 12:13">“Take care for yourself so that you do not offer your burnt offerings at <sd>just</sd> any place that you happen to see, </vn><im><vn id="Dt 12:14">but only</vn></im><n><io>Literally “but <sd>only</sd> if”</io></n><vn id="Dt 12:14"> at the place that Yahweh will choose among one of your tribes; there you shall offer your burnt offerings, and there you shall do all <sd>the things</sd> that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 12:15">“But <im>whenever you desire</im><n><io>Literally “in all the wanting of your soul/inner self”</io></n> you may slaughter, and you may eat meat according to the blessing of Yahweh your God that he has given to you in all <sd>of</sd> your <im>towns</im>;<n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> the unclean and the clean may eat it <sd>just</sd> as <sd>they would</sd> the gazelle and as the deer. </vn><vn id="Dt 12:16">Only the blood you must not eat, <sd>but</sd> on the ground you must pour it like water. </vn><vn id="Dt 12:17">You are not allowed to eat in your <im>towns</im><n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> the tithe of your grain and your wine and your olive oil and the firstborn of your herd and your flock and all <sd>of</sd> your votive gifts that you vowed and your freewill offering and <im>your donations</im>.<n><io>Literally “the contribution of your hand”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 12:18">But only <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “before the face of”</io></n> Yahweh your God you shall eat it, at the place that Yahweh your God will choose,<n><io>Hebrew “choose it”</io></n> you and your son and your daughter and your slave and your slave woman and the Levite who <sd>is</sd> in your <im>towns</im>,<n><io>Literally “gate”</io></n> and you must rejoice <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “before the face of”</io></n> your God <im>in all your undertakings</im>.<n><io>Literally “in all <sd>of</sd> the sending of your hand”</io></n> </vn><im><vn id="Dt 12:19">Take care</vn></im><n><io>Literally “Watch for yourself”</io></n><vn id="Dt 12:19"> so that you do not neglect the Levite all <sd>of</sd> your days on your land. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 12:20">“When Yahweh your God enlarges your territory <sd>just</sd> as he has <im>promised</im><n><io>Literally “spoken”</io></n> to you, and you say ‘I want to eat <sd>some</sd> meat,’ <im>because you want it</im>,<n><io>Literally “because your soul/inner self desires it”</io></n> <im>whenever you desire</im><n><io>Literally “at/in all the wanting of your soul/inner self”</io></n> you may eat meat. </vn><vn id="Dt 12:21">If the place that<n><io>Or “where”</io></n> Yahweh your God will choose to put his name there is <sd>too</sd> far from you, and you slaughter any of your herd and any of your flock that Yahweh has given to you <sd>just</sd> as I have commanded you, then you may eat whenever you desire in your <im>towns</im>.<n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 12:22">Surely <sd>just</sd> as the gazelle and the deer is eaten, so <sd>both</sd> the unclean and the clean together may eat it. </vn><vn id="Dt 12:23">Only, be sure not to eat the blood, because the blood is the life, and you shall not eat the life with the meat. </vn><vn id="Dt 12:24">You shall not eat it, <sd>but</sd> on the ground you shall pour it out like water. </vn><vn id="Dt 12:25">You shall not eat it, so that <im>it will go well</im><n><io>Literally “it/he is good”</io></n> for you <sd>and</sd> your children after you, because <sd>then</sd> you will <sd>be</sd> doing what is<n><io>Hebrew “the”</io></n> right in the eyes of Yahweh. </vn><vn id="Dt 12:26">Only your holy objects <im>that are yours</im><n><io>Literally “that are for you”</io></n> and your votive gifts you must carry and you must bring to the place that Yahweh will choose. </vn><vn id="Dt 12:27">And you shall offer your burnt offerings, the flesh and the blood on the altar of Yahweh your God, and the blood of your sacrifices you shall pour out on the altar of Yahweh your God, but the meat you may eat. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 12:28">Be careful to obey</vn></im><n><io>Literally “Watch carefully and listen”</io></n><vn id="Dt 12:28"> all these things that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you, so that <im>it will go well</im><n><io>Literally “he/it is good”</io></n> for you and for your children after you <im>forever</im>,<n><io>Literally “until ever”</io></n> because then you will <sd>be</sd> doing what is<n><io>Hebrew “the”</io></n> good and right<n><io>Hebrew “the right”</io></n> in the eyes of Yahweh your God. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 12:29">“When Yahweh your God has cut off the nations whom you <sd>are</sd> <im>about to go to</im>,<n><io>Literally “about to go to there”</io></n> to dispossess them <im>before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “from the face of you”</io></n> and you have dispossessed them, and you live in their land, </vn><im><vn id="Dt 12:30">take care</vn></im><n><io>Literally “Watch for yourself”</io></n><vn id="Dt 12:30"> so that you are not ensnared <im>into imitating them</im><n><io>Literally “after them”</io></n> after their being destroyed from <im>before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “from the face of you”</io></n> and so that you not enquire concerning their gods, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘How did these nations serve their gods, and <sd>thus</sd> <im>I myself</im><n><io>Emphatic use of the pronoun</io></n> want to do also.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 12:31">You must not do so toward Yahweh your God, because of every detestable thing they have done for their gods Yahweh hates, for even their sons and their daughters they would burn in the fire to their gods. </vn><n><io><ci title="BibleLEB2: Dt 12:32–13:18">Deuteronomy 12:32–13:18 </ci>in the English Bible is 13:1–19 in the Hebrew Bible</io></n><vn id="Dt 12:32"> All of the things<n><io>Hebrew “thing”</io></n> that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you, <im>you must diligently observe</im>;<n><io>Literally “you must observe to do <sd>it</sd>”</io></n> you shall not add to it, and you shall not take away from it.” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 13"> <pa><vn id="Dt 13:1"> “If a prophet stands up in your midst or a dreamer of dreams<n><io>Hebrew “dream”</io></n> and he gives to you a sign or wonder, </vn><vn id="Dt 13:2">and the sign or<n><io>Hebrew “and”</io></n> the wonder comes <sd>about</sd> that he spoke<n><io>Or “promised/declared”</io></n> to you, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘Let us go after other gods (those whom you have not known), and let us serve them,’ </vn><vn id="Dt 13:3">you must not listen to the words of that prophet or to that dreamer, for Yahweh your God <im>is testing you to know whether you love</im><n><io>Literally “a testing of Yahweh your God concerning you <sd>in order</sd> to know whether there is you loving”</io></n> Yahweh your God with all of your heart and with all <sd>of</sd> your inner self.<n><io>Or “soul”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 13:4">You shall go after Yahweh your God, and him you shall revere, and his commandment you shall keep, and to his voice you shall listen, and him you shall serve, and to him you shall hold fast. </vn><vn id="Dt 13:5">But that prophet or the dreamer of that dream shall be executed, for he spoke falsely about Yahweh your God, the <sd>one</sd> bringing you out from the land of Egypt and the <sd>one</sd> redeeming you from the house of slavery, in order to seduce you from the way that Yahweh your God commanded you to go in it; so <sd>in this way</sd> you shall purge the evil from your midst. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 13:6">“If your brother, the son of your mother or your son or your daughter <im>or your wife whom you embrace</im><n><io>Literally “or the wife of your embrace”</io></n> or <im>your intimate friend</im><n><io>Literally “your friend who is like your soul/inner self”</io></n> in secrecy <im>says</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘Let us go and let us serve other gods!’ <sd>gods</sd> that you and your ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> have not known, </vn><vn id="Dt 13:7">from <sd>among</sd> the gods of the people who are around you, <im>those near you or those far from you</im>,<n><io>Literally “the near ones to you or the distant ones from you”</io></n> from <sd>one</sd> end of the earth and up to the <sd>other</sd> end of the earth, </vn><vn id="Dt 13:8">you must not give in to him, and you shall not listen to him, and your eye shall not take pity on him, and you shall not have compassion, and you shall not cover <sd>up</sd><n><io>Or “conceal” him</io></n> for him. </vn><vn id="Dt 13:9">But you shall certainly kill him; your hand shall be first against him to kill him and next the hand of all <sd>of</sd> the people. </vn><vn id="Dt 13:10">And you shall stone him with stones and let him die, for he tried to seduce you from Yahweh your God, the <sd>one</sd> bringing you from <sd>the</sd> land of Egypt, from the house of slavery. </vn><vn id="Dt 13:11">And all <sd>of</sd> Israel shall hear, and they shall fear, and <im>they shall not continue to act</im><n><io>Literally “they shall not add to do”</io></n> according to this evil thing in your midst. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 13:12">“If you hear in one of your towns which Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you to live in, <sd>someone</sd> <im>saying that</im><n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> </vn><im><vn id="Dt 13:13">worthless men</vn></im><n><io>Literally “sons of Belial”</io></n><vn id="Dt 13:13"> have gone out from your midst and have seduced the inhabitants of their town, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘Let us go and serve other gods!’ whom you have not known, </vn><vn id="Dt 13:14">then you shall inquire and examine and interrogate thoroughly, and, look! <sd>It is</sd> true; the thing has actually been done, this detestable thing in your midst, </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 13:15">then</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 13:15"> you shall certainly strike down the inhabitants of that town with the <im>edge</im><n><io>Literally “mouth”</io></n> of <sd>the</sd> sword; you shall destroy it and everything in it, its domestic animals with <sd>the</sd> <im>edge</im><n><io>Literally “mouth”</io></n> of <sd>the</sd> sword. </vn><vn id="Dt 13:16">And <sd>then</sd> you shall gather all of its booty into the middle of its public square, and you shall burn the town and all <sd>of</sd> its war-booty totally for Yahweh your God, and it shall be <im>a pile of rubble forever</im>;<n><io>Literally “a tell/ruin forever”</io></n> it shall not be built again. </vn><vn id="Dt 13:17">And let not something cling to your hand from the things devoted to destruction, so that Yahweh may turn back <im>from his burning anger</im>,<n><io>Literally “from the burning of his nose”</io></n> and he may show compassion to you and he may <sd>continue</sd> to show compassion and <sd>so</sd> multiply you <im>just as he swore</im><n><io>Literally “as that he swore”</io></n> to your ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 13:18">if you listen to the voice of Yahweh your God, to keep all <sd>of</sd> his commandments that I <sd>am</sd> commanding <sd>to</sd> you <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> <sd>so as</sd> to do the right <sd>thing</sd> in the eyes of Yahweh your God.” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 14"> <pa><vn id="Dt 14:1"> “You <sd>are</sd> children<n><io>Or “sons”</io></n> of Yahweh your God; <sd>therefore</sd> you must not gash<n><io>Or “cut”</io></n> yourself, and <im>you must not make your forehead bald</im><n><io>Literally “you shall not make/place baldness between your eyes”</io></n> for <sd>the</sd> dead. </vn><vn id="Dt 14:2">For you <sd>are</sd> a people holy to Yahweh your God, and you Yahweh has chosen to be a treasured possession from <sd>among</sd> all <sd>of</sd> the peoples that are on the surface<n><io>Or “face”</io></n> of the earth. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 14:3">You shall not eat any detestable thing. </vn><vn id="Dt 14:4">These are the animals you may eat: ox, sheep, goats,<n><io>Literally “small livestock of the sheep and a small livestock of the goats”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 14:5">deer, gazelle, roebuck, wild goat, ibex, antelope, and mountain sheep. </vn><vn id="Dt 14:6">And any animal having a split hoof<n><io>Or “divides the hoof”</io></n> and <sd>so</sd> <im>a dividing of the hoof into two parts</im><n><io>Literally “a dividing cleft <sd>creating</sd> two hoofs”</io></n> <im>and that chews the cud</im><n><io>Literally “and that brings up the cud”</io></n> among the animals<n><io>Hebrew “animal”</io></n>—that <sd>animal</sd> you may eat. </vn><vn id="Dt 14:7">Only these you may not eat from <im>those chewing the cud</im><n><io>Literally “bringing up the cud”</io></n> and from <im>those having a division of the hoof</im>:<n><io>Literally “those having a division of the hoof divided”</io></n> the camel and the hare and the coney, because <im>they chew the cud</im>,<n><io>Literally “they bringing up of the cud”</io></n> but they <sd>do</sd> not divide the hoof; they are <sd>therefore</sd> unclean for you. </vn><vn id="Dt 14:8">And <sd>also</sd> the pig <im>because it has a division of the hoof</im><n><io>Literally “because a division of the hoof”</io></n> <im>but does not chew the cud</im>;<n><io>Literally “but not a <sd>chewing</sd> cud”</io></n> it <sd>is</sd> unclean for you; from their meat you shall not eat, and you shall not touch their <im>carcasses</im>.<n><io>Literally “dead body”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 14:9">“This <sd>is what</sd> you shall eat from all that <sd>is</sd> in the water: <im>everything</im><n><io>Literally “all <sd>of</sd> that”</io></n> <im>that has fins and scales</im><n><io>Literally “for it <sd>is</sd> fins and scales,” showing possession of these features</io></n> you may eat. </vn><vn id="Dt 14:10">But <im>anything that does not have</im><n><io>Literally “all <sd>of</sd> that there is not for it,” showing lack of possession of these features</io></n> fins and scales, you may not eat, <sd>for</sd> it <sd>is</sd> unclean for you. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 14:11">“All <sd>of</sd> <sd>the</sd> birds <sd>that</sd> <sd>are</sd> clean you may eat. </vn><vn id="Dt 14:12">Now these <sd>are</sd> the ones you shall not eat <im>any of them</im>:<n><io>Literally “from them”</io></n> the eagle and the vulture and the short-toed eagle,<n><io>This list of birds is difficult to translate since the terms are not definitely known: e.g., some translations render the last bird as a “buzzard” (NASV); other translations give different names for all three: griffon vulture, black vulture, bearded vulture (NEB)</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 14:13">and the red kite<n><io>Various options are available: large bird, kite, red kite, glede, buzzard</io></n> and the black kite or <im>any kind of falcon</im>,<n><io>Literally “or the falcon according to its kind”; other options for falcon: bird, falcon, kite (others as carrion-bird), vulture, crow or raven, buzzard</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 14:14">and any <sd>kind</sd> of crow<n><io>Or others translate as “raven”</io></n> according to its kind, </vn><vn id="Dt 14:15">and the <im>ostrich</im><n><io>Literally “daughter of the ostrich”; others “desert owl”</io></n> and the short-eared owl and the seagull<n><io>Or “long-eared owl”</io></n> and the hawk according to its kind, </vn><vn id="Dt 14:16">the little owl and the great owl and the barn owl,<n><io>Or “white owl”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 14:17">and the desert owl<n><io>Or “large bird” or “horned-owl”</io></n> and the carrion vulture<n><io>Or “large bird”</io></n> and the cormorant,<n><io>Or “large bird,” or “fisher-owl”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 14:18">and the stork and the heron according to its kind and the hoopoe and the bat. </vn><vn id="Dt 14:19">And <sd>also</sd> all <sd>of</sd> <im>the winged insects</im>;<n><io>Literally “the swarmer<sd>s</sd> of the flyer<sd>s</sd>” or “all the swarms <sd>of things</sd> that fly”</io></n> they <sd>are</sd> unclean for you; you shall not eat <sd>them</sd>. </vn><vn id="Dt 14:20">You may eat any clean bird. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 14:21">“You shall not eat any carcass;<n><io>Or “corpse”</io></n> you may give it to the alien who <sd>is</sd> in your <im>towns</im>,<n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> and he may eat it, or you may sell <sd>it</sd> to a foreigner, for you <sd>are</sd> a holy people for Yahweh your God; you may not boil a kid in its mother’s milk. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 14:22">“Certainly you must give a tithe <sd>of</sd> all the yield of your seed, <im>which comes forth from your field year after year</im>.<n><io>Literally “the going forth of the field year <sd>by</sd> year”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 14:23">And you shall eat <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “before the faces of”</io></n> Yahweh your God in the place that he will choose to make to dwell his name there the tithe of your grain, your wine and your olive oil and the firstling of your herd and your flock, so that you may learn to revere Yahweh your God <im>always</im>.<n><io>Literally “all of the days”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 14:24">But if <im>the distance is too great for you</im>,<n><io>Literally “<sd>it</sd> is great from you the journey that”</io></n> <sd>so</sd> that you are not able to transport<n><io>Or “carry”</io></n> it, because the place that Yahweh your God will choose to set his name there, it is <sd>too</sd> far from you, when Yahweh your God will bless you, </vn><vn id="Dt 14:25">then <sd>in that case</sd> <im>you may exchange for money</im>,<n><io>Literally “you may give it <sd>in</sd> for the money/silver”</io></n> and you shall take<n><io>Or “bind”</io></n> the money to your hand and go to the place that Yahweh your God will choose. </vn><vn id="Dt 14:26">You may spend the money for anything <im>that you desire</im>,<n><io>Literally “that your soul/inner self desires”</io></n> for oxen or for sheep or for wine or for strong drink or for anything <im>that you desire</im>,<n><io>Literally “that your soul/inner self desires”</io></n> and you shall eat <sd>it</sd> there <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> Yahweh your God, and you shall rejoice, you and your household. </vn><vn id="Dt 14:27">And <sd>as to</sd> the Levite who <sd>is</sd> in your <im>towns</im>,<n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> you shall not neglect him, because there is not a plot of ground for him and an inheritance <sd>along</sd> with you. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 14:28">“At the end of three years you shall bring out all <sd>of</sd> the tithe of your yield for that year, and you shall store <sd>it</sd> in your <im>towns</im>.<n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 14:29">And <sd>so</sd> the Levite may come, because there is no plot of ground for him or an inheritance with you, and the alien <sd>also may come</sd> and the orphan and the widow that <sd>are</sd> in your <im>towns</im>,<n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> and <im>they may eat their fill</im>,<n><io>Literally “they may eat and they may be satisfied”</io></n> so that Yahweh your God may bless you in all <sd>of</sd> the work of your hand that you undertake.” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 15"> <pa><vn id="Dt 15:1"> “At the end of seven years you shall grant <sd>a</sd> remission of debt. </vn><vn id="Dt 15:2">And this <sd>is</sd> the manner of the remission of debt: every <im>creditor</im><n><io>Literally “owner of the loan of his hand”</io></n> shall remit his claim that he holds against his neighbor, and he shall not exact payment <sd>from</sd> his brother because there<n><io>Hebrew “it”</io></n> <sd>a</sd> remission of debt has been proclaimed unto<n><io>Hebrew “for”</io></n> Yahweh. </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 15:3">With respect to</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 15:3"> the foreigner you may exact payment, but <im>you must remit</im><n><io>Literally “your hand shall remit”</io></n> what shall be <sd>owed</sd> to you <sd>with respect to</sd> your brother. </vn><vn id="Dt 15:4">Nevertheless, there<n><io>Hebrew “it”</io></n> shall not be among you a poor <sd>person</sd>, because Yahweh will certainly bless you in the land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you <sd>as</sd> an inheritance, to take possession of it. </vn><vn id="Dt 15:5">If only you listen well to the voice of Yahweh your God <im>by observing diligently</im><n><io>Literally “to observe <sd>so as</sd> to do”</io></n> all of these commandments<n><io>Hebrew “commandment”</io></n> that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>today</im>.<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 15:6">When Yahweh your God has blessed you, <sd>just</sd> as he <im>promised</im><n><io>Literally “spoke”</io></n> to you, then you will lend to many nations, but you will not borrow <sd>from them</sd>, and you will rule over many nations, but they will not rule over you. </vn><vn id="Dt 15:7">If <sd>there</sd> is a poor <sd>person</sd> among you from <sd>among</sd> one of your brothers in one of your <im>towns</im><n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you, you shall not harden your heart, and you shall not shut your hand toward <im>your brother who is poor</im>.<n><io>Literally “from among your brothers, the poor one”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 15:8">But you shall certainly open your hand for him, and <im>you shall willingly lend</im><n><io>Literally “lending you shall lend”</io></n> <sd>to</sd> him enough to meet his need, <im>whatever it is</im>.<n><io>Literally “whatever is lacking for him”</io></n> </vn><im><vn id="Dt 15:9">Take care</vn></im><n><io>Literally “Watch for yourself”</io></n><vn id="Dt 15:9"> so that there<n><io>Hebrew “it”</io></n> will not be <im>a thought of wickedness</im><n><io>Literally “a thing in your heart wickedness”</io></n> in your heart, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘The seventh year, the year of the remission of debt is near,’ <im>and you view your needy neighbor with hostility</im>,<n><io>Literally “is bad your eye against your brother who is needy”</io></n> and <sd>so</sd> you <sd>do</sd> not give to him, and he might cry <sd>out</sd> against you to Yahweh, and <im>you would incur guilt against yourself</im>.<n><io>Literally “it will be against you a sin”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 15:10">By all means you must give to him, and <im>you must not be discontented</im><n><io>Literally “and not shall be bad/evil your heart at/when”</io></n> at your giving to him, because on account of this <sd>very</sd> thing, Yahweh your God will bless you in all your work and <im>in all that you undertake</im>.<n><io>Literally “in all <sd>of</sd> the sending/putting forth of your hand”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 15:11">For the poor<n><io>Or “the needy person”</io></n> will not cease to be <im>among you</im><n><io>Literally “from the midst of “</io></n> <sd>in</sd> the land; therefore I <sd>am</sd> commanding you, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘You shall willingly open your hand to your brother, to your needy and to your poor <sd>that are</sd> in your land.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 15:12">If your relative<n><io>Or “brother”</io></n> who is a Hebrew man or a Hebrew woman is sold to you, and <sd>he or she</sd> has served you six years, then in the seventh year you shall send that person <sd>out</sd> <im>free</im>.<n><io>Literally “free from with you”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 15:13">And when you send him <sd>out</sd> free from you, you shall not send him <sd>away</sd> empty-handed. </vn><vn id="Dt 15:14">You shall generously supply him from <sd>among</sd> your flocks and from your threshing floor and from your press; <sd>according to</sd> that <sd>with which</sd> Yahweh your God has blessed you, you shall give to him. </vn><vn id="Dt 15:15">And remember that you were a slave in the land of Egypt, and Yahweh your God redeemed you; therefore I <sd>am</sd> commanding you thus <im>today</im>.<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 15:16">And then <sd>if</sd> it will happen <sd>that</sd> he says to you, ‘<im>I do not want to go out</im><n><io>Literally “I will not go out”</io></n> from you,’ because he loves you and your family, because it is good for him <sd>to be</sd> with you; </vn><vn id="Dt 15:17">then you shall take an awl, and you shall thrust <sd>it</sd> through his earlobe and into the door, and he shall be to you <im>a slave forever</im>;<n><io>Literally “a slave of eternity”</io></n> and you shall also do likewise for your slave woman. </vn><vn id="Dt 15:18">It shall not be hard in your eyes <im>when you send him forth free</im>,<n><io>Literally “in/at you to send him forth free from <sd>being</sd> with you”</io></n> because for six years he has served you <sd>worth</sd> twice the wage of a hired worker; and Yahweh your God will bless you <im>in whatever you will do</im>.<n><io>Literally “in all <sd>of</sd> that you will do”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 15:19">“Every firstling male that is born of your herd and of your flock you shall consecrate to Yahweh your God; you shall not do work with the firstling of your ox, and you shall not shear the firstling of your flock. </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 15:20">Rather</vn></sd> <im><vn id="Dt 15:20">before Yahweh</vn></im><n><io>Literally “in the face of Yahweh”</io></n><vn id="Dt 15:20"> your God you shall eat it year by year at the place Yahweh will choose, you and your household. </vn><vn id="Dt 15:21">But if there is a physical defect in it, <sd>such as</sd> lameness or blindness, any serious defect, you shall not sacrifice it to Yahweh your God. </vn><vn id="Dt 15:22">In your <im>towns</im><n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> you shall eat it, the unclean and the clean together <sd>may eat it</sd>, <sd>just</sd> as <sd>they eat</sd> the gazelle and as <sd>they eat</sd> the deer. </vn><vn id="Dt 15:23">But you shall not eat its blood; you shall pour it on the ground like water.” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 16"> <pa><vn id="Dt 16:1"> “Observe the month of Abib, and you shall keep <sd>the</sd> Passover to Yahweh your God, for in the month of Abib Yahweh your God brought you out from Egypt <sd>by</sd> night. </vn><vn id="Dt 16:2">And you shall offer the Passover sacrifice to Yahweh your God <sd>from among</sd> <sd>your</sd> flock and herd at the place that Yahweh will choose, to let his name dwell there. </vn><vn id="Dt 16:3">You shall not eat <im>with it</im><n><io>Literally “in addition to” or “upon it”</io></n> anything leavened; seven days you shall eat <im>with it</im><n><io>Literally “in addition to” or “upon it”</io></n> unleavened bread of affliction, because in haste you went out from the land of Egypt, so that you will remember the day of your going out from the land of Egypt all the days of your life. </vn><vn id="Dt 16:4">And leaven shall not be seen with<n><io>Or “for”</io></n> you in any of your territory<n><io>Or “all <sd>of</sd>” your territory</io></n> for seven days, and none of the meat that you will slaughter on the evening on the first day shall remain overnight until morning. </vn><vn id="Dt 16:5">You are not allowed to offer the Passover sacrifice in one of your <im>towns</im><n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> that Yahweh your God is giving to you, </vn><vn id="Dt 16:6">but only at the place that Yahweh your God will choose, to let his name dwell there; you shall offer the Passover sacrifice <im>in the evening at sunset</im>,<n><io>Literally “in the evening as the sun goes/sets”</io></n> <sd>at the</sd> designated time<n><io>The Hebrew word here indicates the specific time that God had chosen to bring Israel out of Egypt</io></n> of your going out from Egypt. </vn><vn id="Dt 16:7">And you shall cook, and you shall eat <sd>it</sd> at the place that Yahweh your God will choose; and you may turn in the morning and go to your tents. </vn><vn id="Dt 16:8">Six days you shall eat unleavened bread, and on the seventh day <sd>there shall be</sd> an assembly for Yahweh your God; you shall not do work. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 16:9">“You shall count <sd>off</sd> seven weeks for you; <im>from the time you begin to harvest the standing grain</im><n><io>Literally “from the beginning of <sd>the</sd> sickle against the standing grain”</io></n> you shall begin to count seven weeks. </vn><vn id="Dt 16:10">And <sd>then</sd> you shall celebrate the Feast of Weeks for Yahweh your God with the measure of the freewill offering of your hand that you shall give <sd>just</sd> as Yahweh your God has blessed you. </vn><vn id="Dt 16:11">And you shall rejoice before Yahweh your God, you and your son and your daughter and your slave and your slave woman and the Levite that <sd>is</sd> in your <im>towns</im><n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> and the alien and the orphan and the widow who are in your midst in the place that Yahweh your God will choose to let his name dwell there. </vn><vn id="Dt 16:12">And you shall remember that you were a slave in Egypt, and <sd>so</sd> <im>you shall diligently observe</im><n><io>Literally “you shall observe and do”</io></n> these rules. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 16:13">“You shall celebrate the Feast of Booths for yourselves<n><io>Hebrew “for you”</io></n> seven days <im>at the gathering in of the produce</im><n><io>Literally “at your gathering <sd>of the produce</sd>”</io></n> from your threshing floor and from your press; </vn><vn id="Dt 16:14">and you shall rejoice at your feast, you and your son and your daughter and your slave and your slave woman and the Levite and the orphan and the widow that <sd>are</sd> in your <im>towns</im>.<n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 16:15">Seven days you shall celebrate <sd>your</sd> feast to Yahweh your God at the place Yahweh will choose, for Yahweh your God shall bless you in all of your produce<n><io>Or “increase”</io></n> and in all <sd>of</sd> the work of your hand, and you shall surely <sd>be</sd> rejoicing.<n><io>Or “joyful”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 16:16">Three times in the year all <sd>of</sd> your males shall appear <im>before </im><n><io>Literally “with the face of”</io></n> Yahweh your God at the place that he will choose, at the Feast of Unleavened Bread and at the Feast of Weeks and at the Feast of Booths, and they shall not appear <im>before Yahweh</im><n><io>Literally “with the face of Yahweh”</io></n> empty-handed. </vn><vn id="Dt 16:17">Each <sd>person</sd> <im>shall give as he is able</im>,<n><io>Literally “according to the gift of his hand”</io></n> <sd>that is</sd>, according to the blessing of Yahweh your God that he has given to you. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 16:18">“You shall appoint judges and officials for you in all your <im>towns</im><n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you throughout your tribes, and you shall render <sd>for</sd> the people <im>righteous judgments</im>.<n><io>Literally “a judgment <sd>based on</sd> righteousness”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 16:19">You shall not subvert<n><io>Or “distort/pervert”</io></n> justice; you shall not <im>show partiality</im>;<n><io>Literally “recognize faces”</io></n> and you shall not take a bribe, for the bribe makes blind <sd>the</sd> eyes of <sd>the</sd> wise and misrepresents <sd>the</sd> words of <sd>the</sd> righteous. </vn><vn id="Dt 16:20">Justice, only justice<n><io>Literally “justice justice”</io></n> you shall pursue, so that you may live, and you shall take possession of the land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you. </vn><vn id="Dt 16:21">You shall not plant for yourselves<n><io>Hebrew “for/to you” but with collective meaning</io></n> <im>an Asherah pole</im><n><io>Literally “an Asherah of any wood/tree”</io></n> beside the altar of Yahweh your God that you make for yourselves.<n><io>Hebrew “for/to you” but with collective meaning</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 16:22">And you shall not set up for yourselves a stone pillar, <sd>a thing</sd> that Yahweh your God hates. </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 17"> <pa><vn id="Dt 17:1"> “You shall not sacrifice to Yahweh your God an ox or sheep <im>that has a physical defect</im><n><io>Literally “that is on it a physical defect”</io></n> <im>of anything seriously wrong</im>,<n><io>Literally “of any thing bad/evil”</io></n> for that <sd>is</sd> a detestable thing to Yahweh your God. </vn><vn id="Dt 17:2">If <sd>there</sd> is found in one of your <im>towns</im><n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you a man or a woman that does evil in the eyes of Yahweh your God to transgress his covenant </vn><vn id="Dt 17:3">and by going and serving other gods and <sd>so</sd> he bows down to them and to the sun or to the moon or to any <sd>of</sd> the host of heaven <im>which I have forbidden</im>,<n><io>Literally “which not I <sd>have</sd> commanded”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 17:4">and it is reported to you or you hear <sd>about it</sd> and you enquire <sd>about it</sd> thoroughly and, indeed,<n><io>Or “look!”</io></n> <sd>the</sd> trustworthiness of the deed<n><io>Hebrew “the thing”</io></n> <sd>has</sd> been established, it <im>has occurred</im>,<n><io>Literally “has been done”</io></n> this detestable thing, in Israel, </vn><vn id="Dt 17:5">then you shall bring out that man or that woman who has<n><io>Hebrew “have”</io></n> done this evil thing to your gates; that is, the man or the woman, and you shall stone them with stones <im>to death</im>.<n><io>Literally “and <sd>so</sd> they die”</io></n> </vn><im><vn id="Dt 17:6">On the evidence of</vn></im><n><io>Literally “By the mouth of”</io></n><vn id="Dt 17:6"> two or three witnesses <im>the person shall be put to death</im>.<n><io>Literally “he/she shall be put to death, the dead person”</io></n> The person<n><io>Hebrew “he/she”</io></n> shall not be put to death by the mouth of one witness. </vn><vn id="Dt 17:7">The hand of the witnesses shall be first against the person<n><io>Hebrew “him”</io></n> to kill the person,<n><io>Hebrew “him”</io></n> and afterward the hands<n><io>Hebrew “hand”</io></n> <sd>of</sd> all the people, and <sd>so</sd> you shall purge the evil from your midst. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 17:8">“<im>If a matter is too difficult for you</im>,<n><io>Literally “If is difficult/wonderful from you a thing for judgment”</io></n> <sd>for example disputes</sd> between blood and blood,<n><io>Or “between one homicide and another”</io></n> between legal claim and legal claim<n><io>Or “one kind of lawsuit and another”</io></n> and between assault and assault<n><io>Or “one kind of abuse and another”</io></n> <sd>and between</sd> matters of discernment in your <im>towns</im>,<n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> then you shall get up and you shall go to the place that Yahweh your God will choose; </vn><vn id="Dt 17:9">then you shall go to the priests and the Levites and to the judge who will be <sd>in office</sd> in those days, and you shall enquire, and they shall announce to you <im>the verdict</im>.<n><io>Literally “the word of the decision”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 17:10">“And <im>you shall carry out exactly the decision</im><n><io>Literally “and you shall do according to the mouth of the word”</io></n> that they announced to you from that place that Yahweh will choose, and <im>you shall diligently observe</im><n><io>Literally “and you shall observe and do”</io></n> according to all that they instruct you. </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 17:11">And so</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 17:11"> according to <im>the instruction of the law</im><n><io>Literally “mouth of the law”</io></n> that they teach you and according to the decisions that they say to you, you shall do; you shall not turn from the word that they tell you to the right or <sd>to the</sd> left. </vn><vn id="Dt 17:12">And the man who treats with contempt<n><io>Or “acts presumptuously”</io></n> <sd>so as</sd> not to listen to the priest <sd>who</sd> <sd>is</sd> standing to minister on behalf of Yahweh your God or to the judge, that man shall die; so you shall purge the evil from Israel. </vn><vn id="Dt 17:13">And all the people will hear and will be afraid, and they will not behave presumptuously again. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 17:14">“When you have come to that land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you and you have taken possession of it and you have settled in it, and you say, ‘I will set over me a king like all the nations that <sd>are</sd> around me,’ </vn><vn id="Dt 17:15">indeed, you may set a king over you whom Yahweh your God will choose, from the midst of your countrymen<n><io>Or “brothers”</io></n> you must set a king over you; you are not allowed to appoint over you a man, a foreigner, who <sd>is</sd> not your countryman.<n><io>Or “brother”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 17:16">Except, he may <im>not make numerous</im><n><io>Literally “not multiply”</io></n> for himself horses, and he may not allow the people to <sd>to go</sd> to Egypt <im>in order to increase horses</im>,<n><io>Literally “in order to make numerous horse”</io></n> for Yahweh has said to you that <im>you may never return</im>.<n><io>Literally “not you may do again to return”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 17:17">And he must not <im>acquire many</im><n><io>Or “make numerous”</io></n> wives for himself, so that his heart <sd>would</sd> turn aside; and <im>he must not accumulate silver and gold for himself excessively</im>.<n><io>Literally “gold and silver not he must make numerous for him very”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 17:18">“<im>And then</im><n><io>Literally “And it shall happen”</io></n> <im>when he is sitting</im><n><io>Literally “as/when his sitting”</io></n> on the throne of his kingdom, then he shall write for himself a copy of this law on a scroll <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> the Levitical priests. </vn><vn id="Dt 17:19">And it shall be with him, and he shall read it<n><io>Hebrew “in it”</io></n> all the days of his life, so that he may learn to revere Yahweh your God by <im>diligently observing</im><n><io>Literally “by keeping ... to do them”</io></n> all the word of this law and these rules, </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 17:20">so as</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 17:20"> not to exalt his heart above his countrymen<n><io>Or “brothers”</io></n> and not to turn aside from the commandment to the right or to the left, so that <im>he may reign long over his kingdom</im>,<n><io>Literally “he may make long <sd>his</sd> days over his kingdom”</io></n> he and his children in the midst of Israel.” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 18"> <pa><vn id="Dt 18:1"> “And there shall not be for the Levitical priests, the whole tribe of Levi, a plot of ground and an inheritance with Israel, <sd>rather</sd> they may eat an offering made by fire <sd>as</sd> their inheritance,<n><io>The meaning of the Hebrew text here is uncertain; possibly it reads: “<sd>rather</sd> an offering by fire then they will eat as <sd>their</sd> inheritance/patrimony”</io></n> for Yahweh. </vn><vn id="Dt 18:2">And there shall not be for them<n><io>Hebrew “him”</io></n> an inheritance <sd>of land</sd> in the midst of his brothers; <sd>rather</sd> Yahweh is his inheritance, <sd>just</sd> as he <im>promised</im><n><io>Literally “spoke”</io></n> to them.<n><io>Hebrew “him”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 18:3">Now this shall be the share of the priest from the people, from <im>those who sacrifice the sacrifice</im>,<n><io>Literally “the sacrificers of the sacrifice”</io></n> <sd>whether it is</sd> an ox, sheep, or goat, and they shall give the priest the shoulder and the jawbones and the stomach. </vn><vn id="Dt 18:4">The firstfruits<n><io>Hebrew “firstfruit”</io></n> of your grain, your wine, and your olive oil and the firstfruits<n><io>Hebrew “firstfruit”</io></n> of the fleece of your sheep you shall give to him. </vn><vn id="Dt 18:5">For Yahweh your God has chosen him from <sd>among</sd> all your tribes to stand to minister in the name of Yahweh, he and his sons <im>forever</im>.<n><io>Literally “all <sd>of</sd> the days”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 18:6">And if a<n><io>Hebrew “the”</io></n> Levite comes from one of your <im>towns</im><n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> from <im>anywhere in Israel</im><n><io>Literally “all <sd>of</sd> Israel”</io></n> where he is residing, <im>he may come whenever he desires</im>,<n><io>Literally “he may come in all the desire of his soul/inner self”</io></n> to the place that Yahweh will choose, </vn><vn id="Dt 18:7">and he may minister in the name of Yahweh his God, <sd>just</sd> like all his brothers, <im>the Levites who stand there</im><n><io>Literally “the Levites the ones standing there”</io></n> <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> Yahweh. </vn><vn id="Dt 18:8">They shall eat <im>equal portions</im>,<n><io>Literally “a portion like a portion”</io></n> apart from what he may receive from the sale of his patrimony.<n><io>Hebrew meaning of these phrases/words is not certain; also could translate as “except <sd>what they receive</sd> from the sale of their fathers’ <sd>estates</sd>” (NASB); or “what he may inherit from his father’s family”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 18:9">“When you come to the land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you, you must not learn to do like the detestable practices of those nations. </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 18:10">There</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 18:10"> shall not be found among you one who makes his son or his daughter go through the fire, <sd>or</sd> <im>one who practices divination</im>,<n><io>Literally “a diviner of divination”</io></n> <sd>or</sd> an interpreter of signs,<n><io>Or “soothsayer”</io></n> or an augur,<n><io>Or “an interpreter of omens”</io></n> or sorcerer, </vn><vn id="Dt 18:11">or one who casts magic spells, or one who consults <sd>a</sd> spirit of the dead,<n><io>Or “medium”</io></n> or spiritist, or one who inquires of the dead.<n><io>Or “necromancer”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 18:12">For everyone doing these <sd>things</sd> <sd>is</sd> detestable to Yahweh, and because of these detestable things Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> driving them out from <im>before you</im>.<n><io>Literally “the face of you”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 18:13">You must be blameless before Yahweh your God. </vn><vn id="Dt 18:14">For these nations that you <sd>are</sd> about to dispossess listen to interpreters of signs<n><io>Or “practice witchcraft”</io></n> and to diviners, but Yahweh your God has not allowed you to do the same. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 18:15">“Yahweh your God will raise up for you a prophet like me from your midst, from your countrymen,<n><io>Or “your brothers”</io></n> <sd>and</sd> to him you shall listen. </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 18:16">This is</vn></sd> <im><vn id="Dt 18:16">according to all that you asked</vn></im><n><io>Literally “<sd>just</sd> as all <sd>of</sd> that you asked”</io></n><vn id="Dt 18:16"> from Yahweh your God at Horeb, on the day of the assembly, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘<im>I do not want again to hear</im><n><io>Literally “not I want to do again to hear”</io></n> the voice of Yahweh my God, <sd>and</sd> I do not want to see again this great fire, so that I may not die!’ </vn><vn id="Dt 18:17">And Yahweh said to me, ‘They are right <sd>in</sd> what they have said. </vn><vn id="Dt 18:18">I will raise up a prophet for them <im>from among their countrymen</im><n><io>Literally “from the midst of their brothers”</io></n> like you, and I will place<n><io>Or “give”</io></n> my words into his mouth, and he shall speak to them <im>everything that I command him</im>.<n><io>Literally “all <sd>of</sd> what I command him”</io></n> </vn><im><vn id="Dt 18:19">And then</vn></im><n><io>Literally “And it will happen”</io></n><vn id="Dt 18:19"> the man that will not listen to my words that he shall speak in my name, I will hold accountable. </vn><vn id="Dt 18:20">However, the prophet that behaves presumptuously by speaking a word in my name that I have not commanded him to speak, and who speaks in the name of other gods, then that prophet shall die.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 18:21">And if you say <im>to yourself</im>,<n><io>Literally “in your heart”</io></n> ‘How can we know the word that Yahweh has not spoken to him?’ </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 18:22">Whenever</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 18:22"> what the prophet spoke in the name of Yahweh, the thing does not take place and <sd>does</sd> not come <sd>about</sd>, that <sd>is</sd> the thing that Yahweh has not spoken to him.<n><io>Or “that Yahweh has not spoken it”</io></n> Presumptuously the prophet spoke it; you shall not fear that<n><io>Hebrew “the”</io></n> prophet.” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 19"> <pa><vn id="Dt 19:1"> “When Yahweh your God has <im>exterminated</im><n><io>Literally “cut off”</io></n> the nations <sd>concerning whom</sd> Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you their land, and you have dispossessed them, and you have settled in their towns and in their houses, </vn><vn id="Dt 19:2">you shall set apart three cities for you in the midst of your land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you to take possession of it. </vn><vn id="Dt 19:3">You shall prepare the roads<n><io>Hebrew “road”</io></n> for yourselves, and you shall divide the regions of your land into thirds that Yahweh your God gives you as a possession, so that <im>it will be available for any manslayer to flee there</im>.<n><io>Literally “it shall be to flee there all/anyone killing”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 19:4">“Now this <sd>is</sd> the case of the manslayer who may flee there and live <sd>there</sd> who has killed his neighbor <im>unintentionally</im>,<n><io>Literally “with no knowledge”</io></n> and he did not hate him <im>previously</im>.<n><io>Literally “from yesterday <sd>and the</sd> day before”</io></n> </vn><im><vn id="Dt 19:5">For example</vn></im><vn id="Dt 19:5">,<n><io>Literally “And as”</io></n> when somebody goes with his neighbor into the forest to cut wood, and the iron <sd>head</sd> slips from the handle <sd>of the tool</sd> and strikes his neighbor and he dies, <sd>then</sd> he may flee to one of these cities, and <sd>so</sd> he may live. </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 19:6">He does this</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 19:6"> lest the avenger of blood might pursue after the killer, because <im>he is hot with anger</im><n><io>Literally “is hot his heart”</io></n> and he overtakes him, because it is a long distance <sd>to the city of refuge</sd>, and <sd>so</sd> <im>he kills him</im>,<n><io>Literally “he strikes him down as to his life/soul”</io></n> but <im>he did not deserve a death sentence</im>,<n><io>Literally “for him there was not a judgment of death”</io></n> because he <sd>was</sd> not hating him <im>before</im>.<n><io>Literally “from yesterday <sd>and the</sd> day before”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 19:7">Therefore I <sd>am</sd> commanding you, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘You shall set apart three cities.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 19:8">Then if Yahweh your God enlarges your territory <sd>just</sd> as he swore to your ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> and gives<n><io>Hebrew “will give”</io></n> to you all the land that he <im>promised</im><n><io>Literally “spoke”</io></n> to give to your ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 19:9">then</vn></sd> <im><vn id="Dt 19:9">if you diligently observe this entire commandment</vn></im><n><io>Literally “if you observe all <sd>of</sd> the commandment the this to do it”</io></n><vn id="Dt 19:9"> that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> by loving Yahweh your God and by going<n><io>Or “walking”</io></n> in his ways <im>at all times</im>,<n><io>Literally “all <sd>of</sd> the days”</io></n> then you shall add three more cities for yourselves to these three. </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 19:10">Do this</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 19:10"> so that innocent blood will not be shed<n><io>Hebrew “is not shed”</io></n> in the midst of your land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you <sd>as an</sd> inheritance and <sd>thereby</sd> bloodguilt would be on you.<n><io>Hebrew “shall be on you,” but conditional sense of imperfect is clear</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 19:11">But if someone hates<n><io>Hebrew “<sd>is</sd> hating”</io></n> his neighbor and lies in wait for him and rises up<n><io>Or “gets up”</io></n> against him <im>and murders him</im>,<n><io>Literally “and strikes him mortally <sd>with regard to his life</sd> and he dies”</io></n> and <sd>the murderer</sd> flees to one of these cities, </vn><vn id="Dt 19:12">then the elders of his city shall send and take him from there, and they shall give him into the hand of the avenger of blood, and he shall be put to death. </vn><vn id="Dt 19:13">Your eye shall not take pity on him, and you shall purge the guilt of innocent blood from Israel, <im>so that good will be directed toward you</im>.<n><io>Literally “and good shall be for you” or “it shall be good for you”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 19:14">“You shall not move the boundary <sd>marker</sd> of your neighbor that <im>former generations</im><n><io>Literally “the first settlers/ancestors”</io></n> set up on your property in the land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you to take possession of it. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 19:15">The testimony of a single witness may not be used to convict</vn></im><n><io>Literally “Not shall get up <sd>only</sd> a single witness against a man”</io></n> <sd><vn id="Dt 19:15">with respect to</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 19:15"> any crime and for any wrongdoing in any offense that a person<n><io>Hebrew “he”</io></n> committed; on the <im>evidence</im><n><io>Literally “mouth”</io></n> of two witnesses or on the <im>evidence</im><n><io>Literally “mouth”</io></n> of three witnesses <im>a charge shall be sustained</im>.<n><io>Literally “shall be established a case/charge”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 19:16">If <im>a malicious witness</im><n><io>Literally “a witness of violence”</io></n> gets up <im>to accuse</im><n><io>Literally “against”</io></n> anyone to testify against him falsely, </vn><vn id="Dt 19:17">then the two men <im>to whom the legal dispute pertains</im><n><io>Literally “who for them <sd>are</sd> the legal dispute”</io></n> shall stand <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> Yahweh, <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> the priests and the judges who are <sd>in office</sd> in those days. </vn><vn id="Dt 19:18">Then judges shall make a thorough inquiry, and <sd>if</sd> it turns out<n><io>Or “in fact”</io></n> that the witness is a false witness <sd>and</sd> he testified falsely against his brother, </vn><vn id="Dt 19:19">then you shall do to him as he meant<n><io>Or “planned”</io></n> to do to his brother, and so you shall purge the evil from your midst. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 19:20">And the rest</vn></im><n><io>Literally “and those remaining”</io></n><vn id="Dt 19:20"> shall hear and shall fear, and <im>they shall not continue to do such a thing again</im><n><io>Literally “and they shall not do again to do again”</io></n> as this evil thing in your midst. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 19:21">You must show no pity</vn></im><vn id="Dt 19:21">:<n><io>Literally “And not take pity your eye”</io></n> life for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot.” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 20"> <pa><vn id="Dt 20:1"> “If you go out to war against your enemies and you see a horse and a chariot, <im>an army</im><n><io>Literally “a people”</io></n> larger that you, you shall not be afraid because of them; for Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> with you, the one who brought you from the land of Egypt. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 20:2">And then</vn></im><n><io>Literally “And it will happen”</io></n><vn id="Dt 20:2"> when you approach the battle, then the priest shall come near and speak to the troops. </vn><vn id="Dt 20:3">And he shall say to them, ‘Hear, Israel, you are near <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> to the battle against your enemies; <im>do not lose heart</im>;<n><io>Literally “do not be faint/tender-hearted”</io></n> you shall not be afraid, and you shall not panic, and you shall not be terrified <im>because of them</im>,<n><io>Literally “from their faces”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 20:4">for Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> going with you to fight for you against your enemies to help you.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 20:5">And the officials shall speak to the troops, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘Who <sd>is</sd> the man who has built a new house and has not dedicated it? Let him go and return to this house, so that he does not die in battle and <im>another man</im><n><io>Literally “a man other”</io></n> dedicates it. </vn><vn id="Dt 20:6">And who <sd>is</sd> the man that has planted a vineyard and has not enjoyed it? Let him go and let him return to his house, so that he does not die in battle and <im>another man</im><n><io>Literally “a man other”</io></n> enjoys it. </vn><vn id="Dt 20:7">And who <sd>is</sd> the man who got engaged to a woman and <sd>has</sd> not married her? Let him go and let him return to his house, so that he does not die in battle and <im>another man</im><n><io>Literally “a man other”</io></n> marries her.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 20:8">And the officials shall continue to speak to the troops, and they shall say, ‘<im>What man</im><n><io>Literally “Who is the man”</io></n> is afraid <im>and disheartened</im>?<n><io>Literally “and soft/weak of the heart”</io></n> Let him go, and let him return to his house, and let him not cause the heart of his brothers to melt<n><io>The verb has a causal meaning here</io></n> like his.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 20:9">And <im>when the officials have finished speaking</im><n><io>Literally “it will happen as to finish the officials to speak”</io></n> to the army troops, then they shall appoint commanders of divisions at the head of the troops. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 20:10">“When you approach a city to fight against it, <im>you must offer it peace</im>.<n><io>Literally “you should call it for peace”</io></n> </vn><im><vn id="Dt 20:11">And then</vn></im><n><io>Literally “And it will happen”</io></n><vn id="Dt 20:11"> if <im>they accept your terms of peace</im><n><io>Literally “if peace they reply to you”</io></n> and <im>they surrender to you</im>,<n><io>Literally “they open to you”</io></n> <im>and then</im><n><io>Literally “and it will happen”</io></n> all the people <im>inhabiting it</im><n><io>Literally “being found in it”</io></n> shall be forced labor for you, and they shall serve you. </vn><vn id="Dt 20:12">But if they <im>do not accept your terms of peace</im><n><io>Literally “not they make peace with you”</io></n> and they want to make war with you, then you shall lay siege against it.<n><io>That is, the city</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 20:13">And Yahweh your God will give it into your hand, and you shall kill all its males with the <im>edge</im><n><io>Literally “mouth”</io></n> of <sd>the</sd> sword. </vn><vn id="Dt 20:14">Only the women and the little children and the domestic animals<n><io>Hebrew “animal”</io></n> and all that shall be in the city, all of its spoil you may loot for yourselves, and you may enjoy the spoil of your enemies that Yahweh you God has given to you. </vn><vn id="Dt 20:15">Thus you shall do to all the far<n><io>Or “distant”</io></n> cities from you, which <sd>are</sd> not from the cities of these nations located <im>nearby</im>.<n><io>Literally “here”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 20:16">But from the cities of these peoples that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you as an inheritance, you shall not let anything live that breathes.<n><io>Or “is alive”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 20:17">Rather, you shall utterly destroy them, the Hittites<n><io>Hebrew “Hittite”</io></n> and the Amorites,<n><io>Hebrew “Amorite”</io></n> the Canaanites<n><io>Hebrew “Canaanite”</io></n> and the Perizzites,<n><io>Hebrew “Perizzite”</io></n> the Hivites,<n><io>Hebrew “Hivite”</io></n> and the Jebusites,<n><io>Hebrew “Jebusite”</io></n> <sd>just</sd> as Yahweh your God has commanded you, </vn><vn id="Dt 20:18">so that they may not teach you to do like all their detestable things that they do for their gods and <sd>thereby</sd> you sin against Yahweh your God. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 20:19">“If<n><io>Or “when”</io></n> you besiege a town <sd>for</sd> many days to make war against it <sd>in order to</sd> seize it, you shall not destroy its trees by wielding an ax against them,<n><io>Hebrew “it”</io></n> for you may eat from them,<n><io>Hebrew “it”</io></n> and <sd>so</sd> you must not cut them<n><io>Hebrew “it”</io></n> down. Are the trees of the field humans that they should come in siege <im>against you</im>?<n><io>Literally “from your face”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 20:20">Only<n><io>Or “But”</io></n> the trees<n><io>Hebrew “tree”</io></n> that you know <im>are not fruit trees</im><n><io>Literally “not a tree of food”</io></n> you may destroy and you may cut down, and you may build siege works against that city that is making war with you <im>until it falls</im>.”<n><io>Literally “it to fall”</io></n> </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 21"> <pa><vn id="Dt 21:1"> “If someone slain is found in the land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you to take possession of it <sd>and</sd> <sd>is</sd> lying in the field, <sd>and</sd> it is not known who <im>killed him</im>,<n><io>Literally “struck/smote him”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 21:2">then your elders and your judges shall go out and shall measure <sd>the distance</sd> to the cities that <sd>are</sd> around the slain one. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 21:3">And then</vn></im><n><io>Literally “And it will happen”</io></n><vn id="Dt 21:3"> the nearest city to the slain one, the elders of that city shall take a heifer of the herd that has not been worked with <sd>in the field</sd>, that has not pulled a yoke, </vn><vn id="Dt 21:4">and the elders of that city shall bring the heifer down to a <im>wadi that flows with water all year</im><n><io>Literally “an ever-flowing wadi”</io></n> and <sd>that</sd> has not been plowed and has not been sown; <sd>then</sd> <im>there they shall break the neck of the heifer in the wadi</im>.<n><io>Literally “they shall break there <sd>the neck</sd> with respect to the heifer in the ever-flowing wadi”; the Hebrew verb carries the meaning “to break the neck of”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 21:5">Then the priests, the descendants<n><io>Or “sons”</io></n> of Levi, shall come near, for Yahweh your God has chosen them to bless in the name of Yahweh, and every legal dispute and every <sd>case of</sd> assault will be <im>subject to their ruling</im>.<n><io>Literally “on their mouth”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 21:6">And all of the elders of that city nearest to the slain person shall wash their hands over the heifer <sd>with</sd> the broken neck in the wadi.<n><io>A valley that is dry most of the year, but contains a stream during the rainy season</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 21:7">And they shall declare, and they shall say, ‘Our hands did not shed this blood, and our eyes did not see <sd>what was done</sd>. </vn><vn id="Dt 21:8">Forgive your people, Israel, whom you redeemed, Yahweh, and <sd>do</sd> not <im>allow</im><n><io>Literally “place/put”</io></n> the guilt of innocent blood in the midst of your people Israel, and let them be forgiven <sd>with regard to</sd> blood.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 21:9">And <sd>so</sd> you shall purge the innocent blood from your midst, because you must do the right thing in the eyes of Yahweh. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 21:10">“When you go out for battle against your enemies, and Yahweh your God gives them into your hand, and you lead the captives<n><io>Hebrew “his captive” but singular pronoun refers to the many captives taken with plural sense</io></n> away, </vn><vn id="Dt 21:11">and you see among the captives<n><io>Hebrew “captive”</io></n> a woman beautiful in appearance, and you become attached to her and you want to take her as <sd>a</sd> wife, </vn><vn id="Dt 21:12">then you shall bring her into your household, and she shall shave her head, and she shall trim her nails. </vn><vn id="Dt 21:13">And she shall remove the clothing of her captivity from her, and she shall remain in your house, and she shall mourn her father and her mother <im>a full month</im>,<n><io>Literally “a month of days”</io></n> and after this <im>you may have sex with her</im>,<n><io>Literally “you may go into her”</io></n> and you may marry her, and she may <im>become your wife</im>.<n><io>Literally “become for you as wife”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 21:14">And then if you do not take delight in her, then you shall let her go <im>to do whatever she wants</im>,<n><io>Literally “according to her desire/soul”</io></n> but you shall not treat her as a slave, since you have dishonored<n><io>Or “humbled”</io></n> her. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 21:15">“If a man has two wives, <sd>and</sd> the one <sd>is</sd> loved and the <sd>other</sd> one <sd>is</sd> disliked and the one loved and the one that is disliked have borne for him sons, if it happens <sd>that</sd> the firstborn son <im>belongs to the one that is disliked</im>,<n><io>Literally “is to the wife who is hated”</io></n> </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 21:16">nevertheless</vn></sd> <im><vn id="Dt 21:16">it will be the case that</vn></im><n><io>Literally “it will happen”</io></n><vn id="Dt 21:16"> on the day of bestowing his inheritance upon his sons, he will not be allowed to treat as <sd>the</sd> firstborn son the son of the beloved <sd>wife</sd> <im>in preference to</im><n><io>Literally “over the faces of”</io></n> the son of the disliked <sd>wife</sd>, <sd>who is</sd> the firstborn <sd>son</sd>. </vn><vn id="Dt 21:17">But he shall acknowledge the firstborn son of the disliked <sd>wife</sd> <im>by giving</im><n><io>Literally “to give”</io></n> him a double portion of <im>all that he has</im>,<n><io>Literally “all that is found for him”</io></n> for he <sd>is</sd> the firstfruit of his vigor;<n><io>Or “the beginning of his strength”</io></n> to him <sd>is</sd> the legal claim of the birthright.<n><io>Or “the just claim of the firstborn”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 21:18">“<im>If a man has a stubborn and rebellious son</im><n><io>Literally “If shall be for a man, a son stubborn and rebellious”</io></n> <sd>who</sd> <im>does not listen to</im><n><io>Literally “<sd>and</sd> there is no listening/obedience”</io></n> the voice of his father and to the voice of his mother, and they discipline him, and he does not obey<n><io>Or “listen to”</io></n> them, </vn><vn id="Dt 21:19">then his father and his mother shall take hold of him, and they shall bring him out to the elders of his city and to the gate of his <im>town</im>,<n><io>Literally “place”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 21:20">and they shall say to the elders of his city, ‘This our son <sd>is</sd> stubborn and rebellious; <im>he does not obey us</im>,<n><io>Literally “there is no listening to our voice”</io></n> <sd>and</sd> he is a glutton and a drunkard.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 21:21">Then all the men of his city shall stone him with stones and let him die; and so you shall purge the evil from your midst, and all of Israel will hear, and they will fear. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 21:22">“And <im>if a man commits a sin punishable by death</im>,<n><io>Literally “when shall be against a man a sin of judgment of death”</io></n> and <sd>so</sd> he is put to death and you hang him on a tree, </vn><vn id="Dt 21:23">his dead body shall not hang on the tree, but certainly you shall bury him on that day, for cursed by God <sd>is</sd> one that is <sd>being</sd> hung; so you shall not defile your land<n><io>Or “ground”</io></n> that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you <sd>as an</sd> inheritance.” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 22"> <pa><vn id="Dt 22:1"> “You shall not watch the ox of your neighbor or his sheep or goat straying and ignore them; certainly you shall return them to your neighbor. </vn><vn id="Dt 22:2">And if your countryman<n><io>Or “brother”</io></n> <sd>is</sd> not near you or you do not know <im>who he is</im>,<n><io>Literally “him”</io></n> then you shall bring it <im>to your household</im>,<n><io>Literally “to the midst of your house”</io></n> and it shall be<n><io>Or “remain”</io></n> with you <im>until your countryman seeks after it</im>,<n><io>Literally “the seeking of your countryman after it”</io></n> and you shall return it to him. </vn><vn id="Dt 22:3">And thus <sd>also</sd> you shall do regarding<n><io>Or “to”</io></n> his donkey, and thus you shall do concerning<n><io>Or “to”</io></n> his garment, and so you shall do with respect to<n><io>Or “to”</io></n> all <sd>of</sd> the lost property of your countryman<n><io>Or “brother”</io></n> that is lost from him and you find it; you are not allowed to withhold help. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 22:4">“You shall not see the donkey of your neighbor or his ox fallen on the road and you ignore them; certainly you must help them <sd>get</sd> up <sd>along</sd> with him. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 22:5">“The apparel of a man shall not be <sd>put</sd> on<n><io>Literally “on”</io></n> a woman, and a man shall not wear the clothing of a woman, because everyone who does these things is detestable to Yahweh your God. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 22:6">“If a bird’s nest is found <im>before you</im><n><io>Literally “before your face”</io></n> on the road in any tree or on the ground, <sd>and there are</sd> chicks or eggs, and the mother <sd>is</sd> lying down on the chicks or the eggs, you shall not take the mother along with the young; </vn><vn id="Dt 22:7">you shall certainly let the mother go, but you may take the young for yourselves;<n><io>Hebrew “for you”</io></n> <sd>do this</sd> <im>so that it may go well</im><n><io>Literally “he/it is good”</io></n> for you and <im>you may live long in the land</im>.<n><io>Literally “and you may make long/extend days”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 22:8">“When you build a new house then<n><io>Hebrew “and”</io></n> you shall make a parapet wall<n><io>Or “fence/rail”</io></n> for your roof, so that you will not bring bloodguilt on your house <im>if anyone should fall from it</im>.<n><io>Literally “if should fall the falling from it”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 22:9">“You shall not sow your vineyard <sd>with</sd> differing kinds <sd>of seed</sd>, so that you shall not forfeit <im>the whole harvest</im>,<n><io>Literally “the entire fullness”</io></n> <sd>both</sd> the seed that you sowed and the yield of the vineyard. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 22:10">“You shall not plow with an ox and with a donkey <sd>yoked</sd> together. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 22:11">“You shall not wear woven material <sd>made of</sd> wool and linen <sd>mixed</sd> together. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 22:12">“You shall make tassels for yourselves<n><io>Hebrew “for you”</io></n> on the four corners of your clothing with which you cover <sd>yourself</sd>. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 22:13">“If a man takes a woman and <im>he has sex with her</im>,<n><io>Literally “and he goes unto her”</io></n> but <sd>he</sd> then <im>dislikes her</im>,<n><io>Literally “hates her”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 22:14">and <im>he accuses her falsely</im>,<n><io>Literally “he puts to her deeds of words”</io></n> and <im>he defames her</im>,<n><io>Literally “he brings forth against her a bad name”</io></n> and he says ‘This woman I took and I lay with her and <im>I discovered that she was not a virgin</im>,’<n><io>Literally “I found not with her virginity”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 22:15">then <sd>in defense</sd> the father of the young woman shall take, along with her mother, and <sd>together</sd> they must bring out the <sd>evidence of</sd> the virginity of the young woman <sd>to display it</sd> to the elders of the city <im>at the city gate</im>.<n><io>Literally “toward the city gate”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 22:16">And <sd>then</sd> the father of the young woman shall say to the elders, ‘I gave my daughter to this man as wife, but he <sd>now</sd> <im>dislikes</im><n><io>Literally “hates”</io></n> her, </vn><vn id="Dt 22:17">and now look <im>he has accused her falsely</im>,<n><io>Literally “he put deeds of words”</io></n> saying, “I did not find <im>your daughter a virgin</im>,”<n><io>Literally “to your daughter virginity”</io></n> but here <sd>is</sd> <sd>evidence of</sd> the virginity of my daughter’; and they shall spread the cloth <sd>out</sd> <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> the elders of the city. </vn><vn id="Dt 22:18">Then the elders of that city shall take the man, and they shall discipline him. </vn><vn id="Dt 22:19">Then they shall fine him <sd>a</sd> hundred <sd>shekels of</sd> silver, and they shall give <sd>them</sd> to the father of the young woman, for <im>he defamed an Israelite young woman</im>,<n><io>Literally “for he brought out a bad name against the virgin of Israel”</io></n> and <im>she shall become his wife</im>;<n><io>Literally “and for him she shall become as wife”</io></n> he will not be allowed <im>to divorce her</im><n><io>Literally “to send her out”</io></n> all his days. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 22:20">“But if <im>this charge</im><n><io>Literally “the thing”</io></n> was true, <im>and the signs of virginity were not found</im><n><io>Literally “and they were not found <sd>evidence of</sd> virginity”</io></n> for the young woman, </vn><vn id="Dt 22:21">and <sd>then</sd> they shall bring out the young woman to the doorway of the house of her father, and the men of her city shall stone her with stones, and she shall die, because she did a disgraceful thing in Israel <im>by playing the harlot</im><n><io>Literally “to play the harlot/to prostitute <sd>herself</sd>”</io></n> <sd>in</sd> the house of her father, and so you shall purge the evil from your midst. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 22:22">“If a man is found lying <im>with a married woman</im>,<n><io>Literally “with a woman, a young woman of a husband”</io></n> then they shall both die; <im>both of them</im>,<n><io>Literally “also/even the two of them”</io></n> the man who lay with the woman and the woman <sd>also</sd>, so you shall purge the evil from Israel. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 22:23">“If it happens <sd>that</sd> a young woman, a virgin, <sd>is</sd> engaged to a man, <sd>and</sd> a man finds her in the town and lies with her, </vn><vn id="Dt 22:24">then you shall bring out <im>both of them</im><n><io>Literally “the two of them”</io></n> to the gate of that city, and you shall stone them with stones so that they shall die, the young woman because she did not cry out in the town, and the man because<n><io>Literally “because of the fact that”</io></n> he violated his neighbor’s wife; and so you shall purge the evil from your midst. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 22:25">“But if the man finds the young engaged woman in the field and the man overpowers her and <im>he has sex with her</im>,<n><io>Literally “he lies down with her”</io></n> then the man only<n><io>Or “alone”</io></n> must die who lay<n><io>Or “slept”</io></n> with her. </vn><vn id="Dt 22:26">But you shall not do anything<n><io>Hebrew “a thing”</io></n> to the young woman, <sd>for</sd> there is not <sd>reckoned</sd> against<n><io>Hebrew “to”</io></n> the young woman <im>a sin deserving death</im>;<n><io>Literally “a sin of death”</io></n> <im>it is similar to when</im><n><io>Literally “for as that”</io></n> a man rises up against his neighbor and murders him, <im>a fellow human being</im>,<n><io>Literally “a soul/individual person”</io></n> <sd>just</sd> so <sd>is</sd> this <im>case</im>,<n><io>Literally “thing/matter”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 22:27">for he found her in the field, the engaged young woman cried out, but there was no<n><io>Hebrew “there was not”</io></n> rescuer <im>to help her</im>.<n><io>Literally “for her”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 22:28">“If a man finds a young woman, a virgin <sd>who</sd> is not engaged, and he seizes her and <im>he has sex with her</im><n><io>Literally “he lies with her”</io></n> and they are caught, </vn><vn id="Dt 22:29">then <im>the man who lay with her</im><n><io>Literally “the man the <sd>one</sd> lying with her”</io></n> shall give to the father of the young woman fifty <sd>shekels</sd> of silver, and she shall become <im>his wife</im><n><io>Literally “for/as a wife”</io></n> <im>because</im><n><io>Literally “in place of”</io></n> he violated her, and he is not allowed to divorce her <im>during his lifetime</im>.<n><io>Literally “all <sd>of</sd> his days”</io></n> </vn><n><io><ci title="BibleLEB2: Dt 22:30–23:25">Deuteronomy 22:30–23:25 </ci>in the English Bible is 23:1–26 in the Hebrew Bible</io></n><vn id="Dt 22:30"> A man may not take the wife of his father, and <sd>so</sd> <im>he may not dishonor his father</im>.<n><io>Literally “not he may reveal the skirt of the garment of his father”</io></n> </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 23"> <pa><vn id="Dt 23:1"> “No man <im>with crushed testicles</im><n><io>Literally “bruised of crushing”</io></n> or <sd>whose</sd> <im>male organ is cut off</im><n><io>Literally “cut off of male organ”</io></n> may come into the assembly of Yahweh. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 23:2">An illegitimate child may not come into the assembly of Yahweh; even <sd>to</sd> the tenth generation none <im>of his descendants</im><n><io>Literally “to him”</io></n> may come into the assembly of Yahweh. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 23:3">An Ammonite or a Moabite may not come into the assembly of Yahweh; even <sd>to</sd> the tenth generation none <im>of his descendants</im><n><io>Literally “to him”</io></n> may come into the assembly of Yahweh <im>forever</im>,<n><io>Literally “until eternity”</io></n> </vn><im><vn id="Dt 23:4">because</vn></im><n><io>Literally “because of the event when”</io></n><vn id="Dt 23:4"> they did not come to meet you with food and with water <im>when you came out of Egypt</im>,<n><io>Literally “at your going out of Egypt”</io></n> and <sd>also</sd> <im>because</im><n><io>Literally “because of the event when”</io></n> they<n><io>Hebrew “he,” but with plural meaning</io></n> hired Balaam, son of Beor, from Pethor, in Aram Naharaim<n><io>Or “Mesopotamia” = “between the rivers”</io></n> <sd>to act</sd> against you to curse you. </vn><vn id="Dt 23:5">But Yahweh your God was not willing to listen to Balaam, and Yahweh your God turned the curse into a blessing for you, because Yahweh your God loved you. </vn><vn id="Dt 23:6">You shall not promote their welfare or their prosperity all your days <im>forever</im>.<n><io>Literally “until eternity”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 23:7">“You shall not abhor an Edomite, because he <sd>is</sd> your brother; you shall not abhor an Egyptian because you were an alien in his land. </vn><vn id="Dt 23:8">The children<n><io>Or “sons”</io></n> <sd>that</sd> are born to them <sd>in</sd> the third generation may come <im>representing them</im><n><io>Literally “for them” or possibly “become members of”</io></n> in the assembly of Yahweh. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 23:9">“If<n><io>Or “when”</io></n> you go out to encamp against your enemies, then you shall guard against <sd>doing</sd> anything evil. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 23:10">“If <sd>there</sd> is among you a man that is not clean because of a seminal emission <im>during the night</im>,<n><io>Literally “of the night”</io></n> he shall go outside the camp; he shall not come within the camp. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 23:11">And then</vn></im><n><io>Literally “And it will happen/come about that”</io></n><vn id="Dt 23:11"> toward the <im>coming</im><n><io>Literally “turning”</io></n> of the evening, he shall bathe with<n><io>Hebrew “in” but this is instrumental use of this preposition</io></n> water, and at the going down<n><io>The verb can mean “coming/going” and here it means “going”</io></n> of the sun, he may come to the midst of the camp. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 23:12">“And there shall be for you a designated place outside the camp; <im>and you shall go there to relieve yourself</im>,<n><io>Literally “and you shall go out there, outside <sd>to relieve yourself</sd>”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 23:13">and a digging tool<n><io>Or “spade”</io></n> shall <sd>be included</sd> in addition to your <sd>other</sd> utensils<n><io>Hebrew “utensil”</io></n> for yourself; <im>and then</im><n><io>Literally “and it will happen”</io></n> <im>when you relieve yourself</im><n><io>Literally “at your sitting”</io></n> outside <sd>the camp</sd> you shall dig with it, and <sd>then</sd> you shall turn, and you shall cover your excrement. </vn><vn id="Dt 23:14">For Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> walking about in the midst of your camp to deliver you and <im>to hand your enemies over to you before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “to give your enemies to the face of you”</io></n> and so let your camp be holy, so that he shall not see in it <im>anything indecent</im>,<n><io>Literally “nakedness of a thing”</io></n> and he shall turn away <im>from going with you</im>.<n><io>Literally “from behind/after you”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 23:15">“And you shall not hand over a slave to his master who has escaped <sd>and fled</sd> to you from his master. </vn><vn id="Dt 23:16">He shall reside with you in your midst in the place that he chooses in one of <im>your towns wherever he pleases</im>;<n><io>Literally “in your gates good for him”</io></n> you shall not oppress him. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 23:17">“No woman <im>of Israel</im><n><io>Literally “from the daughters of Israel”</io></n> shall be a temple prostitute, and no man <im>of Israel</im><n><io>Literally “from the sons of Israel”</io></n> shall be a male shrine prostitute. </vn><vn id="Dt 23:18">You may not bring the <im>hire</im><n><io>Literally “gift”</io></n> of a prostitute or <im>the earnings of a male prostitute</im><n><io>Literally “the earnings of a dog”</io></n> <sd>into</sd> the house of Yahweh your God, for any vow offerings, because <im>both</im><n><io>Literally “both, the two of them”</io></n> are a detestable thing to Yahweh your God. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 23:19">“<im>You shall not charge your brother interest on money</im>,<n><io>Literally “You shall not lend on interest to your brother, interest of money”</io></n> interest on<n><io>Hebrew “of”</io></n> food, or interest on<n><io>Hebrew “of”</io></n> anything that one could lend<n><io>Or “can lend”</io></n> on interest. </vn><vn id="Dt 23:20">You may lend on interest to the foreigner, but to your countryman<n><io>Or “brother”</io></n> you may not lend on interest, so that Yahweh your God may bless you <im>in all your undertakings</im><n><io>Literally “in all the sending<sd>s</sd> out of your hand”</io></n> in <im>the land where you are going</im>,<n><io>Literally “the land that you <sd>are</sd> going there”</io></n> <im>in order to take possession of it</im>.<n><io>Literally “to take possession”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 23:21">“<im>When you make a vow</im><n><io>Literally “When/if you vow a vow”</io></n> to Yahweh your God, you shall not postpone <im>fulfillment of it</im>,<n><io>Literally “to fulfill it”</io></n> <sd>for</sd> certainly Yahweh your God shall require it from you and <sd>if postponed</sd> <im>you will incur guilt</im>.<n><io>Literally “it shall become against you <sd>as</sd> sin”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 23:22">And <im>if you refrain from vowing</im>,<n><io>Literally “if you refrain to make a vow”</io></n> <im>you shall not incur guilt</im>.<n><io>Literally “it shall not become against you <sd>as</sd> sin”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 23:23">The utterance of your lips <im>you must perform diligently</im><n><io>Literally “you must observe and you shall do”</io></n> <sd>just</sd> as you have vowed freely to Yahweh your God whatever <sd>it was</sd> that you promised<n><io>Or “spoke”</io></n> with your mouth. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 23:24">“When<n><io>Or “If”</io></n> you come into the vineyard of your neighbor, then you may eat grapes <im>as you please</im><n><io>Literally “according to your desire”</io></n> and <im>until you are full</im>,<n><io>Literally “to your satiation”</io></n> but you shall not put <sd>any</sd> into your container. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 23:25">“When<n><io>Or “If”</io></n> you come into the standing grain of your neighbor, then you may pluck ears with your hand, but you may not <im>swing</im><n><io>Literally “wave”</io></n> a sickle among the standing grain of your neighbor.” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 24"> <pa><vn id="Dt 24:1"> “When<n><io>Or “If”</io></n> a man takes a wife and he marries her <im>and then</im><n><io>Literally “and it will happen”</io></n> <im>she does not please him</im>,<n><io>Literally “if not she finds favor in his eyes”</io></n> because he found <im>something objectionable</im><n><io>Literally “shameful/repulsive thing”</io></n> and writes her a letter of divorce and puts <sd>it</sd> in her hand and sends her <sd>away</sd> from his house, </vn><vn id="Dt 24:2">and she goes from his house, and she goes <sd>out</sd> and becomes <sd>a wife</sd> <im>for another man</im>,<n><io>Literally “for a man other”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 24:3">and <sd>then</sd> the second man dislikes her and he writes her a letter of divorce and places <sd>it</sd> into her hand and sends her from his house, or if the second man dies who took her <im>to himself</im><n><io>Literally “to for him”</io></n> as a wife, </vn><vn id="Dt 24:4">her first husband who sent her <sd>away</sd> is not allowed <im>to take her again</im><n><io>Literally “to return to take her”</io></n> to become a wife to him after she has <im>been defiled</im>,<n><io>Literally “become unclean”</io></n> for that <sd>is</sd> a detestable thing <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> Yahweh, and <sd>so</sd> you shall not mislead into sin the land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you <sd>as an</sd> inheritance. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 24:5">“When<n><io>Or “If”</io></n> a man takes a new wife he shall not go out with the army, and <im>he shall not be obligated with anything</im>;<n><io>Literally “he shall not come across <sd>come over</sd> upon him to anything”</io></n> he shall be free from obligation, <im>to stay at home</im><n><io>Literally “for his house”</io></n> for one year, and he shall bring joy <sd>to</sd> his wife that he took. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 24:6">“A person<n><io>Hebrew “he”</io></n> shall not take<n><io>Or “require”</io></n> a pair of millstones or an upper millstone, for <im>he is taking necessities of life as a pledge</im>.<n><io>Literally “for a life <sd>he</sd> is taking as a pledge”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 24:7">“If a man is <im>caught</im><n><io>Literally “found”</io></n> kidnapping somebody from <sd>among</sd> his countrymen,<n><io>Or “brothers”</io></n> the <im>Israelites</im>,<n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> and he treats him as a slave or he sells him, then that kidnapper shall die, and <sd>so</sd> you shall purge the evil <im>from among you</im>.<n><io>Literally “from your midst”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 24:8">Be watchful<n><io>Or “Be careful”</io></n> <im>with respect to</im><n><io>Literally “against”</io></n> <sd>an</sd> outbreak of <sd>any</sd> infectious skin disease, by being very careful and by acting<n><io>Or “doing”</io></n> according to all that the priests and the Levites have instructed you, <sd>just</sd> as I have commanded them, <im>so you shall diligently observe</im>.<n><io>Literally “<sd>so</sd> you shall observe to do”</io></n> </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 24:9">So</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 24:9"> remember what Yahweh your God did to Miriam on the journey <im>when you went out from Egypt</im>.<n><io>Literally “in you to go out from Egypt”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 24:10">“When you make a loan to your neighbor, a loan of any kind, you shall not go into his house <im>to take his pledge</im>.<n><io>Literally “to pledge <sd>with respect to</sd> his pledge”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 24:11">You shall wait outside, and the man <sd>to</sd> whom you <sd>are</sd> lending, he shall bring the pledge outside to you. </vn><vn id="Dt 24:12">And if <sd>he is</sd> a needy man, you shall not sleep in his pledge.<n><io>“His pledge” refers to “a garment given as pledge”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 24:13">You shall certainly return the pledge to him <im>as the sun sets</im>,<n><io>Literally “as/at the moment of the going <sd>out</sd> of the sun”</io></n> so that he may sleep in his cloak and may bless you, and it shall be <sd>considered</sd> righteousness <im>on your behalf</im><n><io>Literally “to you”</io></n> <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> Yahweh your God. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 24:14">“You shall not exploit a hired worker, <sd>who is</sd> needy and poor, from among your fellow men or from <sd>among</sd> your aliens<n><io>Hebrew “alien”</io></n> who are in your land <sd>and</sd> in your <im>towns</im>.<n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 24:15">On his day you shall give his wage, and the sun shall not go <im>down</im>,<n><io>Literally “over him”</io></n> because <sd>he is</sd> poor and <im>his life depends on it</im>;<n><io>Literally “and to him it is a lifting up with respect to his life/soul”</io></n> <sd>do this</sd> so that he does not cry out against you to Yahweh, <im>and you incur guilt</im>.<n><io>Literally “and it becomes against you <sd>as</sd> sin</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 24:16">“Fathers shall not be put to death because of <sd>their</sd> children, and children shall not be put to death because of <sd>their</sd> fathers; each one shall be put to death for his <sd>own</sd> sin. </vn><vn id="Dt 24:17">You shall not subvert the rights of an alien <sd>or</sd> an orphan, and you shall not take as pledge <sd>the</sd> garment of a widow. </vn><vn id="Dt 24:18">And you shall remember that you were a slave in Egypt and <sd>that</sd> Yahweh your God redeemed you from there; therefore I <sd>am</sd> commanding you to do this commandment. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 24:19">“When<n><io>Or “If”</io></n> you reap your harvest in your field and you forget a sheaf in the field, you shall not return to get it, for it shall be for the alien, for the orphan, and for the widow, so that Yahweh your God may bless you in all the work of your hands. </vn><vn id="Dt 24:20">When you beat off the fruit of your olive trees you shall not search through the branches afterward, for it<n><io>That is, what is left</io></n> shall be for the alien, for the orphan, and for the widow. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 24:21">When you harvest <sd>grapes</sd>, you shall not glean your vineyards <im>again</im>;<n><io>Literally “behind/after you”</io></n> it<n><io>That is, what is left</io></n> shall be for the alien, for the orphan, and for the widow. </vn><vn id="Dt 24:22">And you shall remember that you were a slave in the land of Egypt, therefore I <sd>am</sd> commanding you to do this thing.” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 25"> <pa><vn id="Dt 25:1"> “When a legal dispute <im>takes place</im><n><io>Literally “shall be”</io></n> between men and they come near to the court, and <sd>the judges</sd> judge <sd>with respect to</sd> them, then they shall declare the righteous <sd>to be</sd> in the right and they shall condemn the wicked, </vn><vn id="Dt 25:2">then it will happen if the guilty <sd>one</sd> <im>deserves beating</im>,<n><io>Literally “<sd>is</sd> a son <sd>of</sd> beating”</io></n> then the judge shall make him lie, and he shall beat him <im>before him</im>,<n><io>Literally “to the face of him”</io></n> <im>according to</im><n><io>Literally “as”</io></n> <im>the prescribed number of lashes proportionate to the offense</im>.<n><io>Literally “as is sufficient/necessary, with respect to number, for his wickedness/wicked behavior”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 25:3">He may beat him <sd>with</sd> forty lashes, and he shall not do more <sd>than these</sd>, so that he <sd>will</sd> not beat more in addition to these many blows,<n><io>Hebrew “blow”</io></n> and your countryman<n><io>Or “brother”</io></n> would be<n><io>Hebrew “is”</io></n> degraded before your eyes. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 25:4">“You shall not muzzle an ox <im>when he is threshing</im>.<n><io>Literally “at his threshing”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 25:5">“When brothers dwell together and one of them dies and has no son, the wife of the deceased shall not become the wife of a <im>man of another family</im>;<n><io>Others: “strange man,” “man outside the family” (NEB)</io></n> her brother-in-law <im>shall have sex with her</im>,<n><io>Literally “shall go to her”</io></n> and he shall take her <im>to himself</im><n><io>Literally “to/for him”</io></n> as <sd>a</sd> wife, and he shall perform his duty as <sd>a</sd> brother-in-law <sd>with respect to</sd> her. </vn><vn id="Dt 25:6">And then the firstborn that she bears <im>shall represent his dead brother</im>,<n><io>Literally “he shall stand upon the name of his brother the deceased”</io></n> so that his name is not blotted out from Israel. </vn><vn id="Dt 25:7">But if the man <sd>does</sd> not want to take his sister-in-law, then his sister-in-law shall go up to the gate, to the elders, and she shall say, ‘My brother-in-law refused to perpetuate his brother’s name<n><io>Literally “to cause a name to stand for his brother”</io></n> in Israel, <sd>for</sd> he is not willing <im>to marry me</im>.’<n><io>Literally “to consummate the marriage with the widow of a <sd>his</sd> brother”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 25:8">Then the elders of his town shall summon him and speak to him, and <sd>if</sd> he persists and says, ‘<im>I do not desire to</im><n><io>Literally “I do not delight in”</io></n> marry her’ </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 25:9">then</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 25:9"> his sister-in-law shall go near him before the eyes of the elders, and she shall pull off his sandal from his foot, and she shall spit in his face, and she shall <im>declare</im><n><io>Literally “respond/answer”</io></n> and she shall say, ‘This is how it is done to the man who does not build the house of his brother.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 25:10">And his <im>family</im><n><io>Literally “name”</io></n> shall be called in Israel, ‘The house where the sandal was pulled off.’<n><io>Or “the house <sd>of the man whose</sd> sandal was pulled off”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 25:11">“If a man and his brother fight each other and the wife of the one <sd>man</sd> comes near to rescue her husband from the hand of his attacker and she stretches <sd>out</sd> her hand and she seizes his genitals, </vn><vn id="Dt 25:12">then you shall cut off her hand; your eye shall not take pity. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 25:13">“There shall not be <im>for your use</im><n><io>Literally “to you”</io></n> in your bag two kinds of stone weights, a large one and a small one.<n><io>Literally “stone and stone large and small”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 25:14">There shall not be in your house <im>for your use</im><n><io>Literally “for you”</io></n> <im>two kinds of measures</im>.<n><io>Literally “ephah and ephah large and small”</io></n> </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 25:15">Rather</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 25:15"> a full and honest weight shall be <im>for your use</im>;<n><io>Literally “for you”</io></n> there shall be for you a full and honest <im>measure</im>,<n><io>Literally “an ephah”</io></n> so that your days on the land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you may be long. </vn><vn id="Dt 25:16">For detestable to<n><io>Or “for”</io></n> Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> everyone who <sd>is</sd> doing such things,<n><io>Or “<sd>are</sd> all <sd>who</sd><sd>are</sd> doing”</io></n> everyone who <sd>is</sd> acting<n><io>Or “all <sd>who</sd><sd>are</sd> acting”</io></n> dishonestly. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 25:17">“Remember what Amalek did to you on the journey when<n><io>Or “at/in”</io></n> you went out from Egypt, </vn><vn id="Dt 25:18">that he met you on the journey and attacked you, all those lagging behind you and <sd>when</sd> you were weary and worn out, and he did not fear God. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 25:19">And when</vn></im><n><io>Literally “And it will happen when”</io></n><vn id="Dt 25:19"> Yahweh your God gives rest to you from all your enemies from around <sd>about you</sd> in the land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you <sd>as an</sd> inheritance to take possession of it, you shall blot out the remembrance of Amalek from under the heavens; you shall not forget!” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 26"> <pa><vn id="Dt 26:1"> “<im>And then</im><n><io>Literally “And it shall happen”</io></n> when you come to the land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you <sd>as an</sd> inheritance, and you take possession of it and you settle in it, </vn><vn id="Dt 26:2">then you shall take from the firstfruit of all the fruit of the ground that you harvest from your land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you, and you shall put <sd>it</sd> in a basket, and you shall go to the place that Yahweh your God will choose to make his name to dwell there. </vn><vn id="Dt 26:3">And you shall go to the priest who is <sd>in office</sd> in those days, and you shall say, ‘I declare <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> to Yahweh your God that I have come into the land that Yahweh swore to our ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> to give to us.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 26:4">Then the priest takes the basket from your hand and places it <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> the altar of Yahweh your God. </vn><vn id="Dt 26:5">And <im>you shall declare</im><n><io>Literally “answer”</io></n> and you shall say <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> your God, ‘My ancestor<n><io>Or “father”</io></n> <sd>was</sd> a wandering Aramean, and he went down to Egypt, and there he dwelt as an alien <im>few in number</im>,<n><io>Literally “in people <sd>only</sd> a few”</io></n> and there he became a great nation, mighty and numerous. </vn><vn id="Dt 26:6">And the Egyptians treated us badly, and they oppressed us and imposed on us hard labor. </vn><vn id="Dt 26:7">And we cried to Yahweh, the God of our ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> and Yahweh heard our voice and saw our affliction and our toil and our oppression. </vn><vn id="Dt 26:8">And Yahweh brought us <sd>out</sd> from Egypt with a strong hand and an outstretched arm and with great terror and with signs and with wonders. </vn><vn id="Dt 26:9">And he brought us to this place and gave to us this land, a land flowing with milk and honey. </vn><vn id="Dt 26:10">And now, look, I am bringing<n><io>Hebrew “I bring”</io></n> the firstfruit of the fruit of the ground that you gave to me, Yahweh,’ and you shall place it <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> Yahweh your God, and you shall bow down <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> Yahweh your God. </vn><vn id="Dt 26:11">And you shall celebrate with all of the bounty that Yahweh your God gave to you and to your family, you and the Levite and the alien who <sd>is</sd> in your midst. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 26:12">“When you are finished <im>giving a tithe</im>,<n><io>Literally “to give a tenth”</io></n> all of the tithe of your produce in the third year, the year of the tithe, then you shall give to the Levite, to the alien, to the orphan, and to the widow, so that they may eat in your towns and they may be satisfied. </vn><vn id="Dt 26:13">And you shall say <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> Yahweh your God, ‘I have removed the sacred portion from the<n><io>Or “my” house since the definite article can show possession here</io></n> house and, moreover, I have given it to the Levite and to the alien and to the orphan and to the widow according to all your commandment that you commanded me; I have not transgressed any of your commandments, and I have not forgotten <sd>any of them</sd>. </vn><vn id="Dt 26:14">I have not eaten during my <sd>time of</sd> mourning, and I have not removed <sd>anything</sd> from it while <sd>being</sd> unclean, and I have not offered <im>any of it</im><n><io>Literally “from it”</io></n> to someone who <sd>has</sd> died. I have listened to the voice of Yahweh my God; I have done all that you commanded me <sd>to do</sd>. </vn><vn id="Dt 26:15">Look down from the dwelling place of your holiness, from heaven, and bless your people Israel, and the land that you have given to us, as you swore to our ancestors,<n><io>Or “our fathers”</io></n> a land flowing with milk and honey.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 26:16">“This day Yahweh your God is commanding you to do these rules and regulations, <im>and you must observe them diligently</im><n><io>Literally “and you shall observe and you shall do them”</io></n> with all your heart and with all your soul.<n><io>Or “inner self”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 26:17">Yahweh you <sd>have</sd> declared <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> to be for you as <sd>your</sd> God, and to go<n><io>Or “to walk”</io></n> in his ways and to observe his rules and his commandments and his regulations and to listen to his voice. </vn><vn id="Dt 26:18">And Yahweh <sd>has</sd> declared you <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> to be for him as a people, a treasured possession, as he <im>promised</im><n><io>Literally “spoke”</io></n> to you, and <sd>that you are</sd> to observe all his commandments, </vn><im><vn id="Dt 26:19">and that he then will set you</vn></im><n><io>Literally “and to set you”</io></n><vn id="Dt 26:19"> high above all the nations that he has made for his praise and <im>for fame</im><n><io>Literally “for a name”</io></n> and for honor and <im>for you to be a holy people</im><n><io>Literally “for you to be/your being a people holy”</io></n> to Yahweh your God, as he <im>promised</im>.”<n><io>Literally “spoke”</io></n> </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 27"> <pericope>Ceremonies</pericope> <pa><vn id="Dt 27:1">Then Moses and the elders of Israel charged the people, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> “Keep all of the commandment that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>today</im>.<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 27:2">And then on the day that you cross the Jordan to the land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you, then you shall set up <im>for yourselves</im><n><io>Literally “for you”</io></n> large stones, and you shall paint<n><io>Or “coat/cover them”</io></n> them with lime, </vn><vn id="Dt 27:3">and you shall write on them all the words of this law at your crossing, so that you may come into the land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you, a land flowing with milk and honey, as Yahweh, the God of your ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> <im>promised</im><n><io>Literally “spoke”</io></n> to you. </vn><vn id="Dt 27:4">And <im>when you cross the Jordan</im>,<n><io>Literally “at/in your crossing the Jordan”</io></n> you shall set up these stones that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <sd>about</sd> <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> on Mount Ebal, and you shall paint<n><io>Or “coat/cover”</io></n> them with lime. </vn><vn id="Dt 27:5">And you shall build an altar there for Yahweh your God, an altar of stone, but<n><io>Or “and”</io></n> <im>you shall not use an iron tool to shape the stones</im>.<n><io>Literally “and you shall not wave to and fro over them an iron tool”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 27:6">You must build the altar of your God <sd>with</sd> unhewn stones, and you shall sacrifice on it burnt offerings to Yahweh your God. </vn><vn id="Dt 27:7">And you shall sacrifice fellowship offerings, and you shall eat <sd>them</sd> there, and you shall rejoice <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> Yahweh your God. </vn><vn id="Dt 27:8">You shall write on the stone all of the words of this law very clearly.” </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 27:9">Then Moses and the priests, the Levites, spoke to all Israel, saying,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> “Be silent and hear, Israel, <sd>for</sd> this day you have become <im>a people</im><n><io>Literally “for a people”</io></n> for Yahweh your God. </vn><vn id="Dt 27:10">And listen to the voice of Yahweh your God, and observe his commandments and his rules that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>today</im>.”<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> </vn></pa>  <pericope>Blessings and Curses</pericope> <pa><vn id="Dt 27:11">And Moses charged the people on that day, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 27:12">“These <sd>tribes</sd> shall stand on Mount Gerizim to bless the people <im>when you cross</im><n><io>Literally “at/in crossing your”</io></n> the Jordan: Simeon and Levi and Judah and Issachar and Joseph and Benjamin. </vn><vn id="Dt 27:13">And these shall stand on Mount Ebal for <sd>delivering</sd> the curse: Reuben, Gad and Asher and Zebulun, Dan and Naphtali. </vn><vn id="Dt 27:14">And <im>the Levites shall declare</im>,<n><io>Literally “they shall answer the Levites”</io></n> and they shall say to each man of Israel <sd>with</sd> a loud voice, </vn><vn id="Dt 27:15">‘Cursed be the man that makes a divine image or a cast image, <sd>which is</sd> a detestable thing for Yahweh, the work of the hand of a skilled craftsman, and <sd>then</sd> sets <sd>it</sd> in a hiding place.’<n><io>Or “a secret place”</io></n> And <im>all the people shall respond</im>,<n><io>Literally “and they shall answer all of the people”</io></n> ‘Amen.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 27:16">‘Cursed be the one who dishonors his father or his mother.’ And all of the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 27:17">‘Cursed be the one who moves the boundary <sd>marker</sd> of his neighbor.’ And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 27:18">‘Cursed be the one who misleads a blind person on the road.’ And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 27:19">‘Cursed be the one who deprives <sd>the</sd> alien, <sd>the</sd> orphan, and <sd>the</sd> widow of justice.’ And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 27:20">‘Cursed be the one who lies with the wife of his father, because he has dishonored his father’s bed.’<n><io>Literally “because he uncovered the hem of his father”</io></n> And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 27:21">‘Cursed be the one who lies with any <sd>kind</sd> of animal.’ And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 27:22">‘Cursed be the one who lies with his sister, the daughter of his father or the daughter of his mother.’ And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 27:23">‘Cursed be the one who lies with his mother-in-law.’ And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 27:24">‘Cursed be the one who strikes down his neighbor in secret.’ And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 27:25">‘Cursed be the one who takes a bribe <im>to murder an innocent person</im>.’<n><io>Literally “to strike down an individual person in blood”</io></n> And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 27:26">‘Cursed be <sd>the one</sd> <im>who does not keep</im><n><io>Literally “who not keeps”</io></n> the words of this law, to observe them.’ And all the people shall say, ‘Amen.’ ” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 28"> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:1"> “And it will happen <sd>that</sd> if you indeed listen to the voice of Yahweh your God, <im>to diligently observe</im><n><io>Literally “to observe to do”</io></n> all his commandments that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>today</im>,<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> then Yahweh your God will set you above all the nations of the earth. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:2">And all of these blessings shall come upon you, and <im>they shall have an effect on you</im><n><io>Literally “they shall overtake you”</io></n> if you listen to the voice of Yahweh your God: </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:3">“You will be blessed in the city, and you will be blessed in the field. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:4">“Blessed will be the fruit of your womb and the fruit of your ground and the fruit of your livestock, <im>the calf of your cattle and the lambs of your flock</im>.<n><io>Literally “<sd>what</sd> is dropped of your cattle and the offspring of your flocks”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:5">“Blessed will be your basket and your kneading trough. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:6">“Blessed will you be <im>when you come in and blessed will you be when you go out</im>.<n><io>Literally “in/at your coming and you will be blessed in/at your going out”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:7">“Yahweh will cause your enemies <im>who rise up against you to be defeated before you</im>;<n><io>Literally “the ones rising against you being defeated to the face of you”</io></n> on one road<n><io>Or “way”</io></n> they shall come out <sd>against</sd> you, but on seven roads<n><io>Or “ways”</io></n> they shall flee <im>before you</im>.<n><io>Literally “to the face of you”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 28:8">Yahweh will command <im>concerning you</im><n><io>Literally “with you”</io></n> the blessing <sd>to be</sd> in your barns and <im>in all your endeavors</im>;<n><io>Literally “in all of the sending <sd>forth</sd> of your hand”</io></n> and he will bless you in the land that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> giving to you. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:9">Yahweh will establish you for <im>himself</im><n><io>Literally “to/for him”</io></n> as a holy people as he has sworn to you, if you keep the commandments of Yahweh your God and you walk in his ways. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:10">And all of the peoples of the earth shall see that <im>by the name of Yahweh you are called</im>,<n><io>Literally “that the name of Yahweh is called/assigned upon you”</io></n> and <im>they shall fear you</im>.<n><io>Literally “they shall be afraid/fearful from you”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 28:11">And <im>Yahweh will make you successful and prosperous</im>,<n><io>Literally “Yahweh will cause for you goodness”</io></n> in the fruit of your womb and on the land that Yahweh swore to your ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> to give to you. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:12">Yahweh shall open for you his <im>rich</im><n><io>Literally “good”</io></n> storehouse, <sd>even</sd> the heavens, to give the rain for<n><io>Hebrew “of”</io></n> your land in its time and to bless all of the work of your hand, and you will lend to many nations; you will not borrow <sd>from them</sd>. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:13">And Yahweh shall make you<n><io>Literally “place/set you up”</io></n> as head and not the tail, and you shall be only at the top <sd>of the nations</sd>, and you shall not be at the bottom, if you listen to the commandments of Yahweh your God that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> <im>and diligently observe them</im>.<n><io>Literally “to observe them and to do them”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 28:14">And you <sd>shall</sd> not turn aside from <im>any of</im><n><io>Literally “all of”</io></n> the words that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> <sd>to the</sd> right or left by going after other gods to serve them. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:15">“<im>And then</im><n><io>Literally “and it will happen”</io></n> if you do not listen to the voice of Yahweh your God <im>by diligently observing</im><n><io>Literally “to observe and to do”</io></n> all of his commandments and his statutes that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>today</im>,<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> then all of these curses shall come upon you, and they shall overtake you: </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:16">“You <sd>shall</sd><n><io>All of these curses have a future orientation that points to Israel in the land of Canaan</io></n> be cursed in the city, and <sd>you shall</sd> be cursed in the field. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:17">“Your basket <sd>shall</sd> be cursed and your kneading trough. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:18">“The fruit of your womb <sd>shall</sd> be cursed and the fruit of you ground, the calves of your cattle and the lambs of your flock. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:19">“You shall be cursed <im>when you come in</im>,<n><io>Literally “at/in your coming”</io></n> and you <sd>shall</sd> be cursed <im>when you go out</im>.<n><io>Literally “at/in your going out”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:20">“Yahweh will send upon you<n><io>Others translate as a wish: “may Yahweh send upon you …”</io></n> the curse,<n><io>These words are translated variously, e.g., “starvation,” “thirst,” “rebuke/dysentery” (NEB) or “curses,” “confusion,” “frustration” (NLT)</io></n> the panic,<n><io>Or “confusion”</io></n> and the threat<n><io>Or “rebuke”</io></n> <im>in everything that you undertake</im>,<n><io>Literally “in all the sending out of your hand that you do”</io></n> <im>until you are destroyed and until you perish quickly</im><n><io>Literally “until your to be destroyed and until your to perish quickly”</io></n> <im>because of</im><n><io>Literally “from the face of the evil of your deeds”</io></n> the evil of your deeds in that<n><io>Literally “which”</io></n> you have forsaken me. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:21">Yahweh will cause the plague to cling to you <im>until it consumes you</im><n><io>Literally “it to consume to”</io></n> from the land that you <sd>are</sd> going to,<n><io>Hebrew “to there”</io></n> to take possession of it. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:22">Yahweh will afflict you with the wasting diseases and with the fever and with the inflammation and with the scorching heat and with the sword<n><io>Others translate “drought” (NLT, NEB)</io></n> and with the blight and with the mildew, and they shall pursue you <im>until you perish</im>.<n><io>Literally “until your/you to perish”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 28:23">And your heavens that <sd>are</sd> over your heads shall be <sd>like</sd> bronze, and the earth that <sd>is</sd> under you <sd>shall be like</sd> iron. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:24">Yahweh will change the rain of your land <sd>to</sd> fine dust and <sd>to</sd> sand; from the heaven it shall come down upon you <im>until you are destroyed</im>.<n><io>Literally “until your being destroyed”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:25">“Yahweh shall cause you to be defeated <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> your enemies; on one road you shall go <im>against</im><n><io>Literally “to/toward”</io></n> them,<n><io>Hebrew “him”</io></n> but you will flee on seven roads <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> them,<n><io>Hebrew “him”</io></n> and you shall become a thing of horror to all of the kingdoms of the earth. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:26">And your dead bodies shall be as food for all of the birds of the heaven and to the animals of the earth, and there shall not be <im>anyone to frighten them away</im>.<n><io>Literally “one causing fright <sd>to them</sd>”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:27">“Yahweh shall afflict you with the boils of Egypt and with tumors and with the scurvy and with <im>the skin rash that cannot be healed</im>.<n><io>Literally “the skin rash that not it is able it to be healed”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 28:28">Yahweh shall afflict you with madness and with blindness and with confusion of heart. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:29">And you shall be groping at noon just as the blind person gropes in the dark, and you shall not succeed <sd>in finding</sd> your way, and you shall only be abused and robbed <im>all the time</im>,<n><io>Literally “all the days”</io></n> and there will not be <im>anyone who will rescue you</im>. <n><io>Literally “one who delivers/rescues <sd>you</sd>”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 28:30">You shall become engaged to a woman, but another man shall sleep<n><io>Or “ravish/violate”</io></n> with her; you shall build a house, but you shall not live in it; a vineyard you shall plant, but you shall not enjoy it. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:31">Your ox <sd>shall</sd> <sd>be</sd> slaughtered before your eyes, and you shall not eat it; your donkey <sd>shall be</sd> stolen <sd>right</sd> <im>before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “to the face of you”</io></n> and it shall not be returned to you; your sheep and your goats <sd>shall</sd> be given to your enemies, and <im>there shall not be anyone who rescues you</im>.<n><io>Literally “there shall not be for you one who rescues”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 28:32">Your sons and your daughters <sd>shall be</sd> given to other people, and <im>you will be looking on</im><n><io>Literally “your eyes <sd>will</sd> see/look”</io></n> <im>longingly</im><n><io>Literally “wearing out”</io></n> for<n><io>Hebrew “to”</io></n> them all day, <im>but you will be powerless to do anything</im>.<n><io>Literally “but there will not be for power of your hand”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 28:33">A people that you do not know shall consume the harvest of your land and all your labor, and you will be only oppressed and crushed <im>for the rest of your lives</im>.<n><io>Literally “all of the days”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 28:34">You shall become mad <im>because of what your eyes shall see</im>.<n><io>Literally “from/by the sight of your eyes”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 28:35">Yahweh shall strike you with grievous boils on the knees and on the upper thighs <sd>from which</sd> <im>you will not be able to be healed</im>,<n><io>Literally “which not you are able to heal”</io></n> from the sole of your foot and up to your crown. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:36">Yahweh will bring you and your king whom you set up over you to a nation that you or your ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> have not known, and there you will serve other gods <sd>of</sd> wood and stone. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:37">And you will become a horror and a proverb and ridicule among all the peoples where Yahweh drives you there. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:38">“You shall carry out much seed to the field, but you shall gather little <sd>produce</sd>, for the locust shall devour it. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:39">You shall plant vineyards and you shall dress<n><io>Or “cultivate”</io></n> <sd>them</sd>, but you shall not drink wine and you shall not gather grapes, for the worm shall eat it.<n><io>That is, the produce</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 28:40">There shall be olive trees for you in all of your territory, but you shall not anoint <sd>yourself</sd>, for your olives<n><io>Hebrew “olive”</io></n> shall drop off. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:41">You shall bear sons and daughters, but they shall not be <im>yours</im>,<n><io>Literally “for you”</io></n> for they shall go into captivity. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:42">The cricket shall take possession of all your trees and the fruit of your ground. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:43">The alien that <sd>is</sd> in your midst shall ascend over you, higher <sd>and</sd> higher, but you shall go down lower <sd>and</sd> lower. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:44">He shall lend to you, but you shall not lend to him; he shall be <sd>the</sd> head, but you shall be <sd>the</sd> tail. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:45">“And all of these curses shall come over you, and they shall pursue you, and they shall overtake you <im>until you are destroyed</im>,<n><io>Literally “until you to be destroyed”</io></n> because <im>you did not listen</im><n><io>Literally “not you listened”</io></n> to the voice of Yahweh your God, <im>by observing</im><n><io>Literally “to observe”</io></n> his commandments and his statutes that he commanded you. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:46">And they shall be among you as a sign and as a wonder and among your offspring <im>forever</im>.<n><io>Literally “until eternity,” but not in a timeless, philosophic sense</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:47">“<im>Because</im><n><io>Literally “Under”</io></n> <sd>of the fact</sd> that you did not serve Yahweh your God with joy and with gladness of heart for the abundance of everything, </vn><vn id="Dt 28:48">then you shall serve your enemies, whom Yahweh will send against you <sd>under conditions of</sd> famine, in thirst, in nakedness, and in <sd>a</sd> lack of everything; and he shall place<n><io>Literally “give”</io></n> a yoke of iron on your neck <im>until he has destroyed you</im>.<n><io>Literally “until his destroying of you”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 28:49">Yahweh will raise <sd>up</sd> against you a nation from far <sd>off</sd>, from the end of the earth, <sd>attacking</sd> as the eagle swoops <sd>down</sd>, <im>a nation whose language you will not understand</im>,<n><io>Literally “a nation who not you will understand its language”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 28:50">a grim-faced nation<n><io>Literally “a nation fierce/determined of face”</io></n> <im>who does not show respect</im><n><io>Literally “who not lifts up face<sd>s</sd>”</io></n> to <sd>the</sd> old and <sd>the</sd> young <sd>and</sd> does not show pity. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:51">And it<n><io>That is, the invading nation</io></n> shall consume the fruit of your livestock and the fruit of your ground <im>until you are destroyed</im>,<n><io>Literally “until your destroying”</io></n> <sd>and</sd> who will not leave for you <sd>any</sd> grain, wine, and olive oil, <im>calves of your herds</im>,<n><io>Literally “what is dropped of your herds”</io></n> and <im>lambs of</im><n><io>Literally “the offspring of small animals”</io></n> your flock <im>until it has destroyed you</im>.<n><io>Literally “until his to destroy you”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 28:52">And it shall besiege you in all your towns <im>until your high and fortified walls fall</im>,<n><io>Literally “until the coming down of your walls, high and fortified”</io></n> which you <sd>are</sd> trusting in<n><io>Hebrew “in them,” which is redundant</io></n> <im>throughout your land</im>;<n><io>Literally “in all of your land”</io></n> and it shall besiege you in all of your towns in all of your land that Yahweh your God has given to you. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:53">And you shall eat the fruit of your womb, the flesh of your sons and your daughters, whom Yahweh your God gave to you, <im>during the siege and during the distress</im><n><io>Literally “in siege and in distress”</io></n> your enemy inflicts upon you. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:54">The most refined and the very sensitive<n><io>Or “kindly disposed”</io></n> man among you <im>shall be mean with his brother</im><n><io>Literally “shall be bad/evil his eye against his brother”</io></n> and <im>against his beloved wife</im><n><io>Literally “against the wife of his lap”</io></n> and against the rest<n><io>Or “remainder”</io></n> of his children that he has left over, </vn><im><vn id="Dt 28:55">by refraining from giving</vn></im><n><io>Literally “from giving”</io></n><vn id="Dt 28:55"> to <sd>even</sd> one of them any of the meat of his children that he eats, because <sd>there is</sd> not anything <sd>that is</sd> left over for him <im>during the siege and distress</im><n><io>Literally “in the siege and distress”</io></n> that your enemy inflicts upon you. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:56">The most refined and the <sd>most</sd> delicate <sd>woman</sd> among you, who shall<n><io>Or “would”</io></n> not venture to put the sole of her foot on the ground from being <sd>so</sd> delicate and from <sd>such</sd> gentleness, <im>shall be mean to her beloved husband</im><n><io>Literally “shall be bad her eye against the husband of her lap”</io></n> and against her son and against her daughter, </vn><vn id="Dt 28:57">and <sd>even</sd> concerning her afterbirth <im>that goes out</im><n><io>Literally “the going out”</io></n> from between her feet and <sd>also</sd> concerning her children that she bears, because she eats them for lack of anything in secret <im>during the siege and during the distress</im><n><io>Literally “in the siege and in the distress”</io></n> that your enemy inflicts upon her in your <im>towns</im>.<n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 28:58">“If <im>you do not diligently observe</im><n><io>Literally “you observe to do”</io></n> all the words of this law written in this scroll by revering this glorious and awesome name, Yahweh your God, </vn><vn id="Dt 28:59">then Yahweh shall overwhelm <sd>you</sd> with your plagues and the plagues of your offspring, severe plagues and lasting illnesses, grievous and enduring. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:60">And he shall bring back upon you all the diseases of Egypt <sd>concerning</sd> which <im>you were in dread</im><n><io>Literally “you dreaded”</io></n> <im>because of them</im>.<n><io>Literally “from their presence”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 28:61">Also any illness and any plague<n><io>Or “each illness and each plague”</io></n> that <sd>is</sd> not written in the scroll of this law, he shall bring them, Yahweh, upon you until you are destroyed. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:62">And you shall remain <im>only a few people</im><n><io>Literally “with people of few”</io></n> in place of <sd>the fact</sd> you were <sd>formerly</sd> as the stars of heaven as far as number <sd>is concerned</sd>, because you did not listen to the voice of Yahweh your God. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 28:63">And then</vn></im><n><io>Literally “And it will happen”</io></n><vn id="Dt 28:63"> as Yahweh delighted over you <im>to make you prosperous</im><n><io>Literally “to do good with you”</io></n> to make you numerous, so Yahweh shall delight over you to exterminate you<n><io>Or “to cause you to perish”</io></n> and to destroy you, and <sd>so</sd> you shall be plucked from the land that you <sd>are</sd> going there to take possession of it. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:64">And Yahweh shall scatter you among all the nations from <sd>one</sd> end of the earth up to the <sd>other</sd> end of the earth, and there you shall serve other gods that you have not known nor<n><io>Hebrew “and”</io></n> your ancestors,<n><io>Or “your fathers”</io></n> <sd>gods of</sd> wood and stone. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:65">And among these nations you shall not find rest, and <sd>there</sd> shall not be a resting place for the sole of your foot, and Yahweh shall give you there an anxious heart and a weakening of eyes<n><io>Or “a failure of eyes”</io></n> and a languishing of <sd>your</sd> inner self.<n><io>Or “soul”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 28:66">And <im>your life shall hang in doubt before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “they shall be your life hanging for you in front”</io></n> and you shall be startled<n><io>Or “in fear”</io></n> night and day, and you shall not be confident of your life. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:67">In the morning you shall say, ‘<im>If only it was evening</im>!’<n><io>Literally “Who shall give evening?”</io></n> and in the evening you shall say ‘<im>If only it was morning</im>!’<n><io>Literally “Who shall give morning?”</io></n> because of the dread of your heart that you shall feel, and because of the sight of your eyes that you shall see. </vn><vn id="Dt 28:68">And Yahweh shall bring you back <sd>to</sd> Egypt in ships by the route that I <im>promised</im><n><io>Literally “spoke”</io></n> to you <sd>that</sd> ‘<im>You shall not see it again</im>!’<n><io>Literally “you shall not do again further to see it/her”</io></n> And you shall sell yourself there to your enemies as slaves and as female slaves, but there will not be a buyer.” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 29"> <pericope>Covenant Renewal, Oaths, Restoration, Charges to the Nation</pericope> <pa><n><io><ci title="BibleLEB2: Dt 29:1–29">Deuteronomy 29:1–29 </ci>in the English Bible is 28.69–29:28 in the Hebrew Bible</io></n><vn id="Dt 29:1"> These <sd>are</sd> the words of the covenant that Yahweh commanded Moses to make with the <im>Israelites</im><n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> in the land of Moab <im>besides</im><n><io>Literally “from to alone”</io></n> the covenant that he made with them at Horeb. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 29:2">And Moses summoned all of Israel and said to them, “You saw all that Yahweh did before your eyes in the land of Egypt and to Pharaoh and to all his servants and to all his land; </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 29:3">that is</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 29:3">, the great trials that your eyes saw, <sd>and</sd> those great signs and wonders. </vn><vn id="Dt 29:4">But Yahweh has not given to you a heart to understand, or eyes to see, or ears to hear, <sd>even</sd> <im>to this day</im>.<n><io>Literally “until the day the this”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 29:5">And I have led you forty years<n><io>Hebrew “year”</io></n> in the desert; your clothes <sd>have</sd> not worn out <im>on you</im>,<n><io>Literally “from on you”</io></n> and your sandal has not worn out <im>on your foot</im>.<n><io>Literally “from on your foot”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 29:6">You have not eaten bread, and you have not drunk wine and strong drink, so that you may know that I <sd>am</sd> Yahweh your God. </vn><vn id="Dt 29:7">And <sd>when</sd> you came to this place <sd>then</sd> Sihon the king of Heshbon, and Og the king of Bashan, came out to meet you for battle, and we defeated them. </vn><vn id="Dt 29:8">And we took their land and gave it as <sd>an</sd> inheritance to the Reubenites<n><io>Hebrew “Reubenite”</io></n> and to the Gadites<n><io>Hebrew “Gadite”</io></n> and to <sd>the</sd> half-tribe of Manasseh. </vn><vn id="Dt 29:9">And <im>you must diligently observe the words of this covenant</im>,<n><io>Literally “you must keep the words of the covenant the this and you must do them”</io></n> so that you may succeed in all that you do. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 29:10">“You <sd>are</sd> standing <im>today</im>,<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> all of you, <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> Yahweh your God, your leaders, your tribes, your elders, and your officials, all the men of Israel, </vn><vn id="Dt 29:11">your little children, your women and your aliens<n><io>Hebrew “alien”</io></n> who <sd>are</sd> in the midst of your camp, from the choppers<n><io>Hebrew “chopper”</io></n> of your wood to the drawers<n><io>Hebrew “drawer”</io></n> of your water, </vn><im><vn id="Dt 29:12">in order for you to enter into the covenant of Yahweh your God</vn></im><vn id="Dt 29:12">,<n><io>Literally “for you to go over into the covenant of Yahweh your God”</io></n> and into<n><io>Or “with”</io></n> his oath that Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> <im>making with you</im><n><io>Literally “cutting with you”</io></n> <im>today</im>,<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 29:13">in order to establish you <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> <im>to himself</im><n><io>Literally “for him”</io></n> as a people and <sd>so that</sd> he may be for you <sd>as</sd> God, <sd>just</sd> as he <im>promised</im><n><io>Literally “spoke”</io></n> to you and <im>just as</im><n><io>Literally “according to that which”</io></n> he swore to your ancestors,<n><io>Or “your fathers”</io></n> to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 29:14">“Now I am not <im>making this covenant</im><n><io>Literally “cutting this covenant”</io></n> and this oath <im>with you alone</im>.<n><io>Literally “with you to alone you”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 29:15">But with <im>whoever is standing here</im><n><io>Literally “with who he is here with us standing”</io></n> with us <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> Yahweh our God, and with <im>whoever is not standing here</im><n><io>Literally “with who he is not standing here with us”</io></n> with us <im>today</im>.<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 29:16">For you know how we lived in the land of Egypt and how we traveled through the midst of the nations that you traveled<n><io>Or “journeyed”</io></n> through. </vn><vn id="Dt 29:17">And you have seen their detestable things and their idols of wood and stone, silver, and gold that <sd>were</sd> among them, </vn><vn id="Dt 29:18">so that <im>there is not</im><n><io>Literally “lest there be/develop”</io></n> among you a man or a woman or a clan or a tribe <im>whose heart</im><n><io>Literally “his heart”</io></n> turns <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> from <sd>being</sd> with Yahweh our God to go to serve the gods of these nations, so that there is not among you a root sprouting poison and wormwood. </vn><vn id="Dt 29:19">And then when he hears the words of this oath, then<n><io>Or “and”</io></n> <im>he will assure himself</im><n><io>Literally “he will bless himself”; HALOT 160 suggests “to consider oneself fortunate”</io></n> in his heart, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘<im>Safety shall be mine even though I go in the stubbornness of my heart</im>,’<n><io>Literally “Peace shall happen/be for me, although/even if in the stubbornness of my heart I go”</io></n> thereby destroying the well-watered <sd>land</sd> <sd>along</sd> with the parched.<n><io>Some translators prefer to include the last clause as a part of the words of the wicked man (NASV vs. NEB)</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 29:20">Yahweh will not be willing to forgive him, for <sd>by then</sd> the anger of Yahweh will smoke, and his passion against that man and all the curses written in this scroll will descend on him, and Yahweh will blot out his name from under heaven. </vn><vn id="Dt 29:21">And Yahweh will single him out for calamity out of all the tribes of Israel, according to all the curses of the covenant written in the scroll of this law. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 29:22">“And the next generation, <sd>that is</sd>, your children who will rise <sd>up</sd> after you, and the foreigner who will come from a distant land, when<n><io>Hebrew “and”</io></n> they will see the plagues of that land and its diseases that Yahweh has inflicted upon it, will say, </vn><vn id="Dt 29:23">‘All its land is brimstone and salt left by fire, <im>none of its land will be sown</im>,<n><io>Literally “all of its land will not be sown”</io></n> and it will not make plants sprout out and it will not grow any vegetation; <sd>it is</sd> as the destruction of Sodom and Gomorrah, Adman and Zeboiim, which Yahweh overturned in his anger and in his wrath.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 29:24">And all the nations will say, ‘<im>Why</im><n><io>Literally “On what <sd>basis</sd>”</io></n> has Yahweh done <im>such a thing</im><n><io>Literally “so”</io></n> to this land? What <sd>caused</sd> the fierceness of this great anger?’ </vn><vn id="Dt 29:25">And they will say,<n><io>Or “answer/respond”</io></n> ‘<sd>It is</sd> because they abandoned the covenant of Yahweh, the God of their ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> which he <im>made</im><n><io>Literally “cut”</io></n> with them <im>when he brought them out</im><n><io>Literally “at/in his to bring them out from the land of Egypt”</io></n> from the land of Egypt. </vn><vn id="Dt 29:26">And they went and served other gods and bowed down to them, gods whom they did not know them and he<n><io>That is, Yahweh</io></n> had not allotted to them. </vn><vn id="Dt 29:27">So <im>the anger of Yahweh was kindled</im><n><io>Literally “became hot the nose of Yahweh”</io></n> against that land to bring upon it all the curses written in this scroll, </vn><vn id="Dt 29:28">and Yahweh uprooted them from their land in anger and in wrath and in great fury, and he cast them into another land, <im>just as it is today</im>.’<n><io>Literally “as the day the this”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 29:29">“The hidden <sd>things</sd> <im>belong to Yahweh</im><n><io>Literally “<sd>are</sd> for Yahweh”</io></n> our God, but the revealed <sd>things</sd> <im>belong to us</im><n><io>Literally “<sd>are</sd> for us”</io></n> <sd>to know</sd> and to our children <im>forever</im>,<n><io>Literally “until eternity”</io></n> <sd>in order</sd> to do all the words of this law.” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 30"> <pa><vn id="Dt 30:1"> “And then when all of these things come upon you, the blessing and the curse that I have set <im>before you</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of you”</io></n> <im>and you call them to mind</im><n><io>Literally “and you bring <sd>them</sd> back to your heart”</io></n> among the nations there where Yahweh your God <sd>has</sd> scattered you, </vn><vn id="Dt 30:2">and you return to Yahweh and you listen to his voice according to all that I am commanding you <im>today</im>,<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> <sd>both</sd> you and your children,<n><io>Or “sons”</io></n> with all your heart and with all your inner self,<n><io>Or “soul”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 30:3">and Yahweh your God will restore your fortunes, and he will have compassion <sd>upon</sd> you, and <im>he will again gather you together</im><n><io>Literally “he will do again and he will gather you together”</io></n> from all the peoples where Yahweh your God scattered you there. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 30:4">“<sd>Even</sd> if <im>you are outcasts</im><n><io>Literally “he/it shall be outcasting your”</io></n> at the end of the heavens, <sd>even</sd> from there Yahweh your God shall gather you, and from there <im>he shall bring you back</im>.<n><io>Literally “he shall take/fetch you”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 30:5">And Yahweh your God will bring you to the land that your ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> had taken possession of,<n><io>Hebrew “of it”</io></n> and he will make you successful, and he will make you more numerous than your ancestors.<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 30:6">“And Yahweh your God will circumcise your heart and the heart of your offspring to love Yahweh your God with all your heart and with all your inner self<n><io>Or “soul”</io></n> <im>so that you may live</im>.<n><io>Literally “for the sake of your life”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 30:7">And Yahweh your God will put all these curses on your enemies and <im>on those who hate you</im>,<n><io>Literally “the haters of you”</io></n> <sd>on</sd> <im>those who harassed you</im>.<n><io>Literally “who pursued after/persecuted you”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 30:8">And <im>you will again listen</im><n><io>Literally “you will return and you will listen”</io></n> to the voice of Yahweh, and you will do all his commandments that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>today</im>.<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 30:9">And Yahweh your God will make you prosperous <im>in all your undertakings</im>,<n><io>Literally “in all of the work of your hand”</io></n> and in the fruit of your livestock and in the fruit of your ground <im>abundantly</im>,<n><io>Literally “to/for good”</io></n> for Yahweh <im>will again rejoice</im><n><io>Literally “he will return ... to rejoice”</io></n> over you, <sd>just</sd> as he rejoiced over your ancestors.<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> </vn><sd><vn id="Dt 30:10">He will do this</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 30:10"> if you listen to<n><io>Or “if you obey/hearken to”</io></n> the voice of Yahweh your God by keeping his commandment and his statutes written in the scroll of this law <sd>and</sd> if you return to Yahweh your God with all your heart and with all your inner self.<n><io>Or “soul”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 30:11">“For this commandment that I <sd>am</sd> commanding you <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> <sd>is</sd> <im>not too wonderful for you</im>,<n><io>Literally “not <sd>is</sd> wonderful it from you”</io></n> and it <sd>is</sd> not <sd>too</sd> far <sd>from you</sd>. </vn><vn id="Dt 30:12">It is not in the heavens <im>so that you might say</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘Who will go up for us to the heavens and get it for us and cause us to hear it, so that we may do it?’ </vn><vn id="Dt 30:13">And <sd>it is</sd> <im>not beyond the sea</im>,<n><io>Literally “is not from beyond the sea”</io></n> <im>so that you might say</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘Who will cross for us to the other side of the sea and take it for us and cause us to hear it, so that we may do it?’ </vn><vn id="Dt 30:14">But the word is very near you, <sd>even</sd> in your mouth and in your heart, <im>so that you may do it</im>.<n><io>Literally “to do it”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 30:15">“See, I am setting <im>before you</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of you”</io></n> <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> life and prosperity and death and disaster; </vn><vn id="Dt 30:16">what I am commanding you <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> <sd>is</sd> to love Yahweh your God by going<n><io>Or “walking”</io></n> in his ways and by keeping his commandments and his statutes and his regulations, and then you will live, and you will become numerous, and Yahweh your God will bless you in the <im>land where you are going</im>.<n><io>Literally “the land where you <sd>are</sd> going there”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 30:17">However, if your heart turns aside and you <sd>do</sd> not listen and you are lured away and you bow down to other gods and you serve them, </vn><vn id="Dt 30:18">I declare to you <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> that you will certainly perish; <im>you will not extend your time</im><n><io>Literally “you will not make long days”</io></n> on the land that you are crossing the Jordan to go there to take possession of it. </vn><vn id="Dt 30:19">I invoke as a witness against you <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> the heaven and the earth: life and death I have set <im>before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “to the face of you”</io></n> blessing and curse. So choose life, so that you may live, you and your offspring,<n><io>Or “seed”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 30:20">by loving Yahweh your God by listening to his voice and by clinging to him, for he <sd>is</sd> your life and the length of your days <sd>in order for you</sd> to live on the land that Yahweh swore to your ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob, to give to them.” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 31"> <pericope>Succession, Deposition, and Recitation of Text</pericope> <pa><vn id="Dt 31:1">And Moses went and spoke these words to all Israel. </vn><vn id="Dt 31:2">And he said to them, “I am <sd>a</sd> hundred and twenty years old <im>today</im>;<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> I am not able to go out and to come <sd>in</sd> <sd>any</sd> longer, and Yahweh said to me, ‘You may not cross this Jordan.’ </vn><vn id="Dt 31:3">Yahweh your God <sd>is about to</sd> cross <im>before you</im>;<n><io>Literally “to the face of you”</io></n> he will destroy these nations <im>before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “to the face of you”</io></n> and you shall dispossess them. Joshua <sd>will be</sd> crossing <im>before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “to the face of you”</io></n> <sd>just</sd> as Yahweh <im>promised</im>.<n><io>Literally “spoke”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 31:4">And Yahweh will do to them <sd>just</sd> as he did to Sihon and to Og, kings of the Amorites, and to their land, which he destroyed with them. </vn><vn id="Dt 31:5">And Yahweh <im>will deliver them to you before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “will give them Yahweh to the face of you”</io></n> and you shall do to them according to every commandment that I have commanded you. </vn><vn id="Dt 31:6">Be strong and be courageous; you should not be afraid, and you <im>should not be in dread from their presence</im>,<n><io>Literally “not you should dread from their face”</io></n> for Yahweh your God <sd>is</sd> the <sd>one</sd> going with you; he will not leave you alone and he will not forsake you.” </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 31:7">Then Moses summoned Joshua, and he said to him <im>in the presence of all Israel</im>,<n><io>Literally “before the eyes of all Israel”</io></n> “Be strong and be courageous, for you will go with this people into the land that Yahweh swore to their ancestors<n><io>Or “their fathers”</io></n> to give to them, and you will give it to them as an inheritance. </vn><vn id="Dt 31:8">Yahweh <sd>is</sd> the <sd>one</sd> going <im>before you</im>;<n><io>Literally “to the face of you”</io></n> he will be with you, and he will not leave you alone, and he will not forsake you; you shall not be afraid, and you shall not be discouraged.” </vn><vn id="Dt 31:9">So Moses wrote this law, and he gave it to the priests, the descendants<n><io>Or “sons”</io></n> of Levi, the <sd>ones</sd> carrying the ark of the covenant of Yahweh, and to all the elders of Israel. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 31:10">Then Moses commanded them, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> “At the end of seven years, in the time of the year for canceling debts during the Feast of Booths, </vn><im><vn id="Dt 31:11">when all Israel comes to appear before</vn></im><n><io>Literally “at/in the coming of all of Israel to see”</io></n><vn id="Dt 31:11"> Yahweh their God at the place that he will choose, you shall read this law before all Israel <im>in their hearing</im>.<n><io>Literally “in their ears”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 31:12">Assemble the people, the men and the women and the little children and your aliens that are in your <im>towns</im>,<n><io>Literally “gates”</io></n> so that they may hear and so that they may learn and they may revere Yahweh your God, and <im>they shall diligently observe</im><n><io>Literally “they shall keep to do”</io></n> all the words of this law. </vn><vn id="Dt 31:13">And <sd>then</sd> their children,<n><io>Hebrew “child”</io></n> who have not known, they <sd>too</sd> may hear, and they may learn to revere Yahweh their God all the days <im>that you live</im><n><io>Literally “that you are alive”</io></n> on the land that you <sd>are</sd> crossing the Jordan <im>to get there</im><n><io>Literally “there”</io></n> to take possession of it.” </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 31:14">Then Yahweh said to Moses, “Look, <im>you are about to die</im>;<n><io>Literally “are near your days to die”</io></n> call Joshua and present yourselves in <sd>the</sd> tent of assembly,<n><io>Or “meeting”</io></n> so that I may instruct him.” So Moses and Joshua went and presented themselves in<n><io>Or “at”</io></n> <sd>the</sd> tent of assembly.<n><io>Or “meeting”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 31:15">And Yahweh appeared in the tent in a column of cloud, and the column of the cloud stood at the entrance of the tent. </vn><vn id="Dt 31:16">And Yahweh said to Moses, “Look, you <sd>are</sd> about to lie <sd>down</sd> with your ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> and this people will arise and they<n><io>Hebrew “he”</io></n> will play the prostitute after <im>the foreign gods</im><n><io>Literally “the gods of the foreigner/foreign person of the land”</io></n> of the land <im>to which they are going</im>.<n><io>Literally “which he is going to”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 31:17">And <im>my anger shall flare up against them</im><n><io>Literally “shall become my nose against it/him”</io></n> on that day, and I will forsake them, and I will hide my face from them, and they<n><io>Hebrew “he”</io></n> shall become as prey, and disasters and troubles shall find<n><io>Or “encounter”</io></n> them,<n><io>Hebrew “him”</io></n> and they<n><io>Hebrew “he”</io></n> shall say on that day, ‘<sd>Is it</sd> not because our<n><io>Hebrew “my” but represents all the people</io></n> God is not in our<n><io>Hebrew “my”</io></n> midst <sd>that</sd> these disasters have found<n><io>Or “encountered”</io></n> us?’<n><io>Hebrew “me”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 31:18">But I will certainly hide my face on that day, because <sd>of</sd> all of the evil that they<n><io>Hebrew “he”</io></n> did because they<n><io>Hebrew “he”</io></n> turned to other gods. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 31:19">“And so then write this song for yourselves and teach it to the <im>Israelites</im>;<n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> put it in their mouth, so that this song may be for me as a witness against the <im>Israelites</im>.<n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 31:20">For when I bring them<n><io>Hebrew “him,” referring to the people</io></n> into the land that I swore to their<n><io>Hebrew “his”</io></n> ancestors,<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> a land flowing with milk and honey, <im>they will eat their fill</im>,<n><io>Literally “he will eat and he will be satisfied”</io></n> and they<n><io>Hebrew “he”</io></n> will become fat, and <sd>then</sd> they<n><io>Hebrew “he”</io></n> will turn to other gods, and they will serve them, and they will spurn me, and they<n><io>Hebrew “he”</io></n> will break my covenant. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 31:21">And then</vn></im><n><io>Literally “And it shall happen”</io></n><vn id="Dt 31:21"> many disasters and troubles will come upon them,<n><io>Hebrew “him”</io></n> and this song will give evidence before them<n><io>Hebrew “him”</io></n> as a witness, because it will not be forgotten from <sd>out of</sd> the mouth of their descendants,<n><io>Hebrew “his offspring/descendant”</io></n> for I know their<n><io>Hebrew “his”</io></n> inclination that they<n><io>Hebrew “he”</io></n> <sd>are</sd> having <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> before I have brought them<n><io>Hebrew “him”</io></n> into the land that I swore.” </vn><vn id="Dt 31:22">And Moses wrote this song on that day and taught it <sd>to</sd> the <im>Israelites</im>.<n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 31:23">Then he<n><io>That is, Yahweh</io></n> told Joshua the son of Nun, and said <sd>to him</sd>, “Be strong and be courageous, for you shall bring the <im>Israelites</im><n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> into the land that I swore to them, and I will be with you.” </vn></pa> <pa><im><vn id="Dt 31:24">And then when Moses finished writing</vn></im><n><io>Literally “And it happened as/when to finish Moses to write”</io></n><vn id="Dt 31:24"> the words of this law on the scroll <im>until they were complete</im>,<n><io>Literally “until their to be complete/”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 31:25">then Moses commanded the Levites carrying the ark of the covenant of Yahweh, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 31:26">“Take the scroll of this law and put it at the side of the ark of the covenant of Yahweh your God, and it will be there as a witness against you. </vn><vn id="Dt 31:27">For I know your rebellion and your stiff neck <sd>even now</sd> while I <sd>am</sd> still alive with you <im>today</im>,<n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> rebelling against Yahweh, and <im>how much more</im><n><io>Literally “and also for/indeed”</io></n> after my death. </vn><vn id="Dt 31:28">Assemble to me all the elders of your tribes and your officials, so that I may speak in their ears these words, and <sd>that</sd> I may call as witness against them heaven and earth. </vn><vn id="Dt 31:29">For I know that after my death you will certainly act corruptly, and you will turn aside from the way that I have commanded you, and the disaster in the future days will befall you, because you will do evil<n><io>Hebrew “the evil”; the definite article indicates the general concept of evil</io></n> in the eyes of Yahweh, <im>provoking him with the work of your hands</im>.”<n><io>Literally “to provoke him with/by the work of your hands”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 31:30">So Moses spoke into the ears of the assembly of Israel the words of this song <im>until they were complete</im>.<n><io>Literally “until their to be complete”</io></n> </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 32"> <pericope>The Song of Moses</pericope>  <pa><ul> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:1">“Give ear, O heavens, and I will speak, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:1">and let the earth hear the words of my mouth. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:2">May my teaching trickle like the dew, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:2">my words like rain showers on tender grass, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:2">and like spring showers on new growth. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:3">For I will proclaim the name of Yahweh; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:3">ascribe greatness to our God! </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:4">The Rock, his work <sd>is</sd> perfect, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:4">for all his ways <sd>are</sd> just; </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><sd><vn id="Dt 32:4">he is</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 32:4"> a faithful God, and <im>without injustice</im>;<n><io>Literally “there is not injustice”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:4">righteous and upright <sd>is</sd> he. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:5">They <sd>have</sd> behaved corruptly toward<n><io>Or “with”</io></n> him; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><sd><vn id="Dt 32:5">they are</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 32:5"> not his children; <sd>this is</sd> their flaw, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:5">a generation crooked and perverse. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><sd><vn id="Dt 32:6">Like</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 32:6"> this do you treat Yahweh, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:6">foolish and <im>unwise</im><n><io>Literally “not wise”</io></n> people? </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><sd><vn id="Dt 32:6">Has</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 32:6"> he not, your father, created you? </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:6">He made you, and he established you. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:7">Remember <sd>the</sd> old days, <im>the years long past</im>;<n><io>Literally “<sd>the</sd> years of <sd>from</sd> generation to generation”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:7">ask your father, and he will inform you, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:7">your elders and they will tell you.<n><io>Hebrew “to you”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><im><vn id="Dt 32:8">When the Most High apportioned</vn></im><n><io>Literally “In/at the apportioning of the Most High”</io></n> <sd><vn id="Dt 32:8">the</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 32:8"> nations, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:8">at his dividing <sd>up</sd> of the sons of humankind, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:8">he fixed the boundaries of <sd>the</sd> peoples, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:8">according to the number of the children of Israel.<n><io>LXX reads “the number of the angels of God”; Dead Sea Scrolls reads “the number of the sons of God”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:9">For Yahweh’s portion <sd>was</sd> his people, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:9">Jacob the share of his inheritance. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:10">He found him in a desert land, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:10">and in a howling, desert wasteland; </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:10">he <im>encircled him</im>,<n><io>Literally “moved around him”</io></n> he cared for him, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:10">he protected him like the <im>apple</im><n><io>Literally “pupil”</io></n> of his eye. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:11">As an eagle stirs up its nest, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:11">hovers over its young, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:11">spreads out its wings, takes them,<n><io>Hebrew “it” but used poetically and with plural sense in context</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:11">carries them<n><io>Hebrew “it” but used poetically and with plural sense in context</io></n> on its pinions,<n><io>Hebrew “pinion”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><sd><vn id="Dt 32:12">so</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 32:12"> Yahweh alone guided him,<n><io>That is, Jacob, standing for Israel</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:12">and <im>there was no foreign god accompanying him</im>.<n><io>Literally “and there was not with him a god foreign/strange”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:13">And he set him on the high places of <sd>the</sd> land, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:13">and he fed <sd>him</sd> the crops<n><io>Hebrew “crop”</io></n> of <sd>the</sd> field, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:13">and he nursed him with honey from crags,<n><io>Hebrew “crag”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:13">and <sd>with</sd> oil from flinty rock, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><sd><vn id="Dt 32:14">With</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 32:14"> curds<n><io>Hebrew “curd”</io></n> from <sd>the</sd> herd, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:14">and <sd>with</sd> milk from <sd>the</sd> flock, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:14">with <sd>the</sd> fat of young rams, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:14">and rams, the offspring of Bashan, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:14">and with goats <sd>along</sd> with the finest kernels of wheat, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:14">and <sd>from</sd> the blood of grapes<n><io>Hebrew “grape”</io></n> you drank fermented wine.<n><io>Or “partially fermented wine”; others translate simply as wine (NASB, NEB); HALOT 330, “still fermenting wine”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:15">And Jeshurun grew fat, and he kicked; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:15">you grew fat, you bloated, and you became obstinate; </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:15">and he abandoned God, his maker, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:15">and he scoffed <sd>at</sd> the rock of his salvation. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:16">They made him jealous with strange <sd>gods</sd>; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:16">with detestable things they provoked him. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:17">They sacrificed to the demons, not God, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><sd><vn id="Dt 32:17">to</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 32:17"> gods whom<n><io>Hebrew “them”</io></n> they had not known, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:17">new <sd>gods</sd> <sd>who</sd><n><io>Hebrew “they,” understood in the verb form</io></n> came from recent times; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><im><vn id="Dt 32:17">their ancestors had not known them</vn></im><vn id="Dt 32:17">.<n><io>Literally “their fathers not knew them”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><sd><vn id="Dt 32:18">The</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 32:18"> rock who<n><io>Hebrew “he,” understood in verb form</io></n> bore you, you neglected, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:18">and you forgot God, <sd>the one</sd> giving you birth. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:19">Then Yahweh saw, and he spurned <sd>them</sd>, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:19">because of the provocation of his sons and his daughters. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:20">So he said, ‘I will hide my face from them; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:20">I will see what <sd>will be</sd> their end, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:20">for they <sd>are</sd> a generation of perversity, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><im><vn id="Dt 32:20">children in whom there is no faithfulness</vn></im><vn id="Dt 32:20">.<n><io>Literally “sons not faithfulness <sd>is</sd> in them”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:21">They annoyed me with <sd>what is</sd> not a god; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:21">they provoked me with their idols. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:21">So I will make them jealous with <sd>those</sd> not a people, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:21">with a foolish nation I will provoke them. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:22">For a fire was kindled<n><io>Or “ignited”</io></n> by my anger, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:22">and it burned <im>up to the depths of Sheol</im>,<n><io>Literally “up to Sheol depths”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:22">and it devoured <sd>the</sd> earth and its produce, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:22">and it set afire the foundation of <sd>the</sd> mountains. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:23">I will heap disasters upon them; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:23">my arrows I will spend on them. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><sd><vn id="Dt 32:24">They will become</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 32:24"> weakened by famine, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:24">and consumed by plague and bitter pestilence; </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:24">and the teeth of wild animals I will send against them, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:24">with <sd>the</sd> poison of <sd>the</sd> creeping <sd>things</sd> in <sd>the</sd> dust; </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:25">From outside <sd>her boundaries</sd> the sword will make <sd>her</sd> childless, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:25">and from inside, terror; </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:25">both <sd>for</sd> <sd>the</sd> young man <sd>and</sd> also the young woman, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:25">the infant <sd>along with</sd> the gray-headed man. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:26">I thought, “I will wipe them out; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><im><vn id="Dt 32:26">I will make people forget they ever existed</vn></im><vn id="Dt 32:26">.”<n><io>Literally “I will blot out from among human being their remembrance”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:27">If I had not feared a provocation of <sd>the</sd> enemy, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:27">lest their foes might misunderstand, <n><io>Or “so that they not make a false construal” of what has happened</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:27">lest they should say, <n><io>Or “so that they might not”</io></n> “Our hand is </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><im><vn id="Dt 32:27">triumphant</vn></im><vn id="Dt 32:27">,<n><io>Literally “raised/held high”</io></n> and Yahweh <sd>did</sd> not do all this.” ’ </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:28">For <im>they are a nation void of sense</im>,<n><io>Literally “they a nation perishing of counsel”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:28">and there is not <sd>any</sd> understanding in them. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:29">If only they were wise, they would understand this; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:29">they would discern <im>for themselves their end</im>.<n><io>Literally “they would discern for end their”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:30">How could one chase a thousand </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:30">and two could cause a myriad to flee, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:30">if their Rock had not sold them, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:30">and Yahweh had <sd>not</sd> given them up? </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:31">For the fact of the matter is, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:31">their rock <sd>is</sd> not like our Rock, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:31">and our enemies recognize<n><io>The meaning of this expression is uncertain, but “discerns” or “judges” seem good choices; see HALOT 932, which allows for “judges” or “in the estimation of our enemies”</io></n> <sd>this</sd>. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:32">For their vine <sd>is</sd> from the vine of Sodom, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:32">and from the terraces of Gomorrah; </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:32">their grapes <sd>are</sd> grapes of poison; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><im><vn id="Dt 32:32">their clusters are bitter</vn></im><vn id="Dt 32:32">.<n><io>Literally “clusters of bitter <sd>are</sd> for them”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:33">Their wine <sd>is</sd> the poison of snakes, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:33">and <sd>the</sd> deadly poison of horned vipers. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:34">‘<sd>Is</sd> not this stored up with me, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:34">sealed in my treasuries?’<n><io>Or “storehouses</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><im><vn id="Dt 32:35">Vengeance belongs to me</vn></im><n><io>Literally “To me <sd>is</sd> vengeance”</io></n><vn id="Dt 32:35"> and <sd>also</sd> recompense, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><im><vn id="Dt 32:35">for at the time their foot slips</vn></im><vn id="Dt 32:35">,<n><io>Literally “at <sd>the</sd> time <sd>when</sd> it shall slip foot their”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:35">because the day of their disaster <sd>is</sd> near, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><im><vn id="Dt 32:35">and fate comes quickly for them</vn></im><vn id="Dt 32:35">.’<n><io>Literally “and comes quickly/hurries events to come to them”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:36">For Yahweh will judge <sd>on behalf of</sd> his people, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:36">and concerning his servants; </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:36">he will change his mind when he sees that <sd>their</sd> power has disappeared, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:36">and <sd>there is</sd> no one left, confined<n><io>Or “bond/bound”</io></n> or free.<n><io>Or “freed”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:37">And he will say, ‘Where <sd>are</sd> their gods, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><sd><vn id="Dt 32:37">their</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 32:37"> rock in whom<n><io>Hebrew “in him”</io></n> they took refuge? </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:38">Who ate the fat of their sacrifices </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><sd><vn id="Dt 32:38">and</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 32:38"> drank the wine of their libations? </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:38">Let them rise <sd>up</sd>, and let them help you; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><im><vn id="Dt 32:38">Let them be to you a refuge</vn></im><vn id="Dt 32:38">.<n><io>Literally “let there be/him/them unto you <sd>as</sd> a shelter”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:39">See, now, that I, <sd>even</sd> I <sd>am</sd> he, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:39">and there is not a god besides me; </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:39">I put to death and I give life; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:39">I wound and I heal; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:39">there is not <sd>one</sd> who delivers from my hand! </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:40">For <sd>indeed</sd> I lift up my hand to heaven, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:40">And I promise <im>as I live forever</im>,<n><io>Literally “live I to eternity”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:41">When I sharpen<n><io>Or “have sharpened”</io></n> <im>my flashing sword</im>,<n><io>Literally “the flashing of my sword”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:41">and my hand takes hold<n><io>Or “seizes”</io></n> <sd>of it</sd> in judgment, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><im><vn id="Dt 32:41">I will take reprisals against my foes</vn></im><vn id="Dt 32:41">,<n><io>Literally “I will let return vengeance to foes my”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:41">and my haters I will repay. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:42">I will make my arrows drunk with blood, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:42">and my sword shall devour flesh with the blood of the slain, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:42">and captives<n><io>Hebrew “captive”</io></n> from the heads<n><io>Hebrew “head”</io></n> of the leaders of <sd>the</sd> enemy.’ </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 32:43">Call for songs of joy, O nations, <sd>concerning</sd> his people,<n><io>Dead Sea Scrolls reads: “Rejoice, O heavenly ones, with him! Bow down, all you gods, before him!”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:43">for the blood of his servants he will avenge, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><im><vn id="Dt 32:43">and he will take reprisals against his foes</vn></im><vn id="Dt 32:43">,<n><io>Literally “vengeance he will let return to his foes”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 32:43">and he will make atonement <sd>for</sd> his land, his people.” </vn></li> </ul></pa>  <pa><vn id="Dt 32:44">And Moses came, and he spoke<n><io>Or “recited”</io></n> all the words of this song in the ears of the people; <sd>that is</sd>, he and Joshua the son of Nun. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 32:45">And when Moses finished speaking</vn></im><n><io>Literally “And <sd>he</sd> finished Moses to speak”</io></n><vn id="Dt 32:45"> all these words to all Israel, </vn><vn id="Dt 32:46">then he said to them, “<im>Take to heart all the words</im><n><io>Literally “Put heart your to all the words”</io></n> that I <sd>am</sd> admonishing <sd>against</sd> you <im>today</im><n><io>Literally “the day”</io></n> <sd>concerning</sd> which you should instruct them <sd>with respect to</sd> your children<n><io>Or “sons”</io></n> <im>so that they will observe diligently</im><n><io>Literally “to keep to do”</io></n> all the words of this law, </vn><vn id="Dt 32:47">for it <sd>is</sd> not a trifling matter among you, but it <sd>is</sd> your life, and through this word <im>you will live long in the land</im><n><io>Literally “you will make long days on the land”</io></n> that you <sd>are about</sd> to cross the Jordan <sd>to get</sd> there to take possession of it.” </vn></pa>  <pericope>Instructions Concerning Moses’ Death</pericope> <pa><vn id="Dt 32:48">And Yahweh said to Moses on exactly this day, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 32:49">“Go up to this mountain of the Abarim <sd>range</sd>, Mount Nebo, which <sd>is</sd> <im>opposite Jericho</im>,<n><io>Literally “on the face of Jericho”</io></n> and see the land of Canaan that I <sd>am</sd> giving to the <im>Israelites</im><n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> as <sd>a</sd> possession. </vn><vn id="Dt 32:50">You shall die on that mountain that you <sd>are</sd> about to go up there, and <sd>you will</sd> be gathered to your people, <sd>just</sd> as your brother Aaron died on <im>Mount Hor</im><n><io>Literally “on Hor the mountain”</io></n> and he was gathered to his people, </vn><vn id="Dt 32:51">because <sd>of the fact</sd> that you broke faith with me in the midst of Israel at the waters of Meribah Kadesh, <sd>in</sd> the desert of Zin, because <im>you did not treat me as holy</im><n><io>Literally “that not you treated me as holy”</io></n> in the midst of the <im>Israelites</im>.<n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 32:52">Yes, from afar you may view the land, but there you shall not enter there, <sd>that is</sd>, into the land that I <sd>am</sd> giving to the <im>Israelites</im>.”<n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 33"> <pericope>Blessings of Moses on Israel</pericope> <pa><vn id="Dt 33:1">Now<n><io>Or “And”</io></n> this <sd>is</sd> the blessing <sd>with</sd> which Moses, the man of God, blessed the <im>Israelites</im><n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of”</io></n> his death. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 33:2">Then<n><io>Or “And”</io></n> he said, </vn><ul> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:2">“Yahweh came from Sinai, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:2">and he dawned upon them from Seir; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:2">he shone forth from Mount Paran, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:2">and he came with myriads of holy ones, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:2">at his right hand a fiery law for them.<n><io>This pointing of the MT is very difficult; here HALOT 93 suggests “fire a law for them” as a translation of the compound Hebrew word made up of “fire” + “law,” which I render as “<sd>a</sd> fiery law”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:3">Moreover,<n><io>Or “Indeed”</io></n> <im>he loves his people</im>,<n><io>Literally “a lover of peoples”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:3">all the holy ones <sd>were</sd> in your hand, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:3">and they bowed down to<n><io>Or “at”</io></n> your feet, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><im><vn id="Dt 33:3">each one accepted directions from you</vn></im><vn id="Dt 33:3">.<n><io>Literally “he takes up from your words”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:4">A law Moses instructed for us, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><sd><vn id="Dt 33:4">as a</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 33:4"> possession <sd>for</sd> the assembly of Jacob. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:5">And <sd>then</sd> a king arose in Jeshurun, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:5">at the gathering of the leaders of <sd>the</sd> people, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><im><vn id="Dt 33:5">united were the tribes of Israel</vn></im><vn id="Dt 33:5">.<n><io>Literally “together the tribes of Israel”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:6">“May Reuben live, and may he not die, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><im><vn id="Dt 33:6">and let his number not be few</vn></im><vn id="Dt 33:6">.”<n><io>Literally “let he be his people <sd>of</sd> number”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><im><vn id="Dt 33:7">And he said this of Judah</vn></im><vn id="Dt 33:7">,<n><io>Literally “and this concerning/to Judah, and he said”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:7">“Hear, O Yahweh, the voice of Judah, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:7">and bring him to his people; </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:7">his own hands strive<n><io>Or “is/are great” on his behalf</io></n> for him, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:7">and may you be a help <im>against</im><n><io>Literally “from”</io></n> his foes.” </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:8">And of Levi he said, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:8">“Your Thummim and your Urim </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><sd><vn id="Dt 33:8">are</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 33:8"> for <im>your faithful one</im>,<n><io>Literally “man, your faithful one”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><im><vn id="Dt 33:8">whom you tested at Massah</vn></im><vn id="Dt 33:8">;<n><io>Literally “whom you tested him at Massah”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:8">you contended <sd>with</sd> him </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:8">at the waters of Meribah. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:9">The <sd>one</sd> saying of his father and of his mother, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:9">‘I have not regarded them,’ </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:9">and his brothers he <sd>did</sd> not acknowledge, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:9">and his children<n><io>Or “sons”</io></n> <sd>he did</sd> not know, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:9">but <sd>rather</sd> they observed your word, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:9">and your covenant they kept. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:10">They taught<n><io>Or “teach/will teach”</io></n> your regulations to Jacob, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:10">and your law to Israel; </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:10">they placed incense smoke <im>before you</im>,<n><io>Literally “in your nose”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:10">and whole burnt offerings on your altar. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:11">Bless, O Yahweh, his substance, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:11">and with the work of his hands you must be pleased; </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:11">smite the loins of those who attack him, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:11">and those hating him, <im>so that they cannot arise</im>.”<n><io>Literally “so that not they stand up”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:12">Of Benjamin he said, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:12">“The beloved of Yahweh dwells <im>securely</im>,<n><io>Literally “in confidence”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:12">the Most High<n><io>This is the most likely reading in context (Most High God). Literally the Hebrew text reads “upon him,” so the NASV translates the first line as: dwell in security “by him”</io></n> shields <sd>all</sd> around him, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:12">all the day, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:12">and between his shoulders he dwells.” </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:13">And of Joseph he said, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:13">“Blessed by Yahweh <sd>is</sd> his land, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:13">with<n><io>Hebrew “from”</io></n> the choice things of heaven, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:13">with<n><io>Hebrew “from”</io></n> dew, and with<n><io>Hebrew “from”</io></n> the deep lying down beneath, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:14">and with<n><io>Hebrew “from”</io></n> <sd>the</sd> choice things of <sd>the</sd> fruits<n><io>Or “produce of”</io></n> of the <sd>the</sd> sun, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:14">and with the choice things of <sd>the</sd> yield of <sd>the</sd> <im>seasons</im>,<n><io>Literally “months”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:15">and with<n><io>Hebrew “from”</io></n> the finest things of <sd>the</sd> ancient mountains, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:15">and with<n><io>Hebrew “from”</io></n> <sd>the</sd> choice things of <sd>the</sd> <im>eternal hills</im>,<n><io>Literally “<sd>the</sd> hills of eternity <sd>never ending ages</sd>”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:16">and with<n><io>Hebrew “from”</io></n> the choice things of <sd>the</sd> earth and its fullness, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:16">and the favor of <sd>the one</sd> <im>who dwelt</im><n><io>Literally “dwells” but context puts the event into the past; literally “dweller of the bush”</io></n> in <sd>the</sd> bush.<n><io>Some scholars suggest that this expression must be read as: on Sinai</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:16">Let them come to the head of Joseph, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:16">and to the crown of the prince among his brothers. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><sd><vn id="Dt 33:17">As</vn></sd><vn id="Dt 33:17"> the firstborn of his ox, majesty <im>belongs to him</im>,<n><io>Literally “is for him”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:17">and his horns <sd>are</sd> <sd>the</sd> horns of a wild ox; </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:17">with them he drives people together,<n><io>Or “all at once” (NASB)</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:17">and they <sd>are</sd> the myriads of Ephraim, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:17">and they <sd>are</sd> the thousands of Manasseh.” </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:18">And of Zebulun he said, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:18">“Rejoice, Zebulun, in your going out, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:18">and <sd>rejoice</sd>, Issachar, in your tents; </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:19">They summon people <sd>to the</sd> mountains;<n><io>Hebrew “mountain”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:19">there they sacrifice the sacrifices of righteousness, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:19">because the affluence of <sd>the</sd> seas they suck <sd>out</sd>, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:19">and <im>the most hidden treasures of the sand</im>.”<n><io>Literally “<sd>the</sd> covered of <sd>the</sd> hidden of <sd>the</sd> sand”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:20">And of Gad he said, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:20">“Blessed <sd>be</sd> <im>the one who enlarges Gad</im>;<n><io>Literally “the enlarger of Gad”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:20">like a lion he dwells, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:20">and he tears an arm as well as a scalp. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:21">And he selected<n><io>Or “provided”</io></n> <sd>the</sd> best <sd>part</sd> for himself, <n><io>Hebrew “for him”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:21">for there <sd>the</sd> portion of a ruler <sd>is</sd> included, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:21">and he came <sd>with the</sd> heads of <sd>the</sd> people;<n><io>Or possibly, “the heads of the people came/assembled” (compare NEB)</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:21">he did<n><io>Or “worked”</io></n> the righteousness of Yahweh, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:21">and his regulations for Israel.” </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:22">And of Dan he said, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:22">“Dan <sd>is</sd> a cub of <sd>a</sd> lion; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:22">he leaps from Bashan.”<n><io>Hebrew “the Bashan,” referring to a well-known geographical and agricultural area</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:23">And of Naphtali, he said, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:23">“Oh, Naphtali, sated of favor, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:23">and full of the blessing of Yahweh; </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:23">take possession of <sd>the</sd> lake, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:23">and <sd>the land to the</sd> south.” </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:24">And of Asher he said, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:24">“Blessed <im>more than sons</im><n><io>Literally “blessed from/of sons <sd>is</sd>” features the comparative use the Hebrew preposition <i>min</i>, “than”</io></n> <sd>is</sd> Asher; </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><im><vn id="Dt 33:24">may he be the favorite</vn></im><n><io>Literally “may he be favored”</io></n><vn id="Dt 33:24"> of his brothers, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><im><vn id="Dt 33:24">dipping his feet in the oil</vn></im><vn id="Dt 33:24">.<n><io>Literally “and dipping in <sd>the</sd> oil his feet”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:25">Your bars <sd>are</sd><n><io>Or “will be”</io></n> iron and bronze, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:25">and as your days, <sd>so is</sd><n><io>Or “so will be/may be”</io></n> your strength.” </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:26">“There is no <sd>one</sd> like God, O, Jeshurun, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:26">who rides <sd>through</sd> the heavens to your help, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:26">and with his majesty <sd>through the</sd> skies. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:27">The God of <im>ancient time</im><n><io>Literally “before/earlier time<sd>s</sd>”</io></n> <sd>is</sd> a hiding place, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:27">and underneath <sd>are</sd> <sd>the</sd> arms of eternity,<n><io>Or “everlasting ages” or “everlasting arms”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:27">and he drove out <im>from before</im><n><io>Literally “from your face”</io></n> you your enemy, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:27">and he said, ‘Destroy <sd>them</sd>!’ </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:28">So Israel dwells alone <sd>and</sd> carefree, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:28">the spring of Jacob in a land of grain and wine; </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:28">his heavens even drip dew. </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:29">Blessed <sd>are</sd> you, O Israel. </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:29">Who is like you, a people who <sd>is</sd> saved by Yahweh, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:29">the shield of your help, </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:29">and who <sd>is</sd> the sword of your triumph, </vn></li> <li class="level-1"><vn id="Dt 33:29">and your enemies, they shall fawn before you,<n><io>Hebrew “to you”</io></n> </vn></li> <li class="level-2"><vn id="Dt 33:29">and you shall tread on their backs.” </vn></li> </ul></pa>   </chapter> <chapter id="Dt 34"> <pericope>The Death of Moses and the Commissioning of Joshua</pericope> <pa><vn id="Dt 34:1">Then Moses went up from the desert plateau<n><io>Or “plains/lowlands”</io></n> of Moab to Mount Nebo, to the top of Pisgah, <im>which is opposite</im><n><io>Literally “which is on the face of”</io></n> Jericho, and Yahweh showed him all of the land, Gilead <sd>all the way</sd> up to Dan, </vn><vn id="Dt 34:2">and all of Naphtali and the land of Ephraim and Manasseh and all of the land of Judah, up to the western sea,<n><io>That is, the Mediterranean Sea</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 34:3">and the Negev and the plain of the valley of Jericho, the city of palms, <sd>on</sd> up to Zoar. </vn><vn id="Dt 34:4">And Yahweh said to him, “This <sd>is</sd> the land that I swore to Abraham to Isaac and to Jacob, <im>saying</im>,<n><io>Literally “to say”</io></n> ‘To your offspring I will give it.’ I have let you see <sd>it</sd> with your eyes, but you shall not cross <im>into it</im>.”<n><io>Literally “to there”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 34:5">Then Moses, the servant of Yahweh, died there in the land of Moab <im>according to the command of Yahweh</im>.<n><io>Literally “at the mouth of Yahweh”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 34:6">And he<n><io>That is, Yahweh</io></n> buried him in the valley in the land of Moab opposite Beth Peor. But until this day no one knows his burial site. </vn><im><vn id="Dt 34:7">Now Moses was a hundred and twenty years old</vn></im><n><io>Literally “and Moses <sd>was</sd> a son of <sd>a</sd> hundred and twenty year”</io></n> <im><vn id="Dt 34:7">when he died</vn></im><vn id="Dt 34:7">;<n><io>Literally “at/in his dying”</io></n> <im>his sight was not impaired and his vigor had not abated</im>.<n><io>Literally “not faded his eyes and not had fled away his vitality”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Dt 34:8">And the <im>Israelites</im><n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> wept <sd>concerning</sd> Moses thirty days; <sd>finally</sd> the days of weeping and mourning for Moses were completed. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Dt 34:9">Now<n><io>Or “And”</io></n> Joshua the son of Nun was full of the spirit of wisdom because Moses had placed his hands on him, and the <im>Israelites</im><n><io>Literally “sons/children of Israel”</io></n> listened to him, and they did as Yahweh had commanded Moses. </vn><vn id="Dt 34:10">And not again<n><io>Or “since then”</io></n> has a prophet arisen in Israel like Moses, whom Yahweh knew<n><io>Hebrew “knew him”</io></n> face to face, </vn><vn id="Dt 34:11">as far as all the signs and the wonders Yahweh sent him to do in the land of Egypt, against<n><io>Hebrew “to”</io></n> Pharaoh and all of his servants and against<n><io>Hebrew “to”</io></n> all of his land, </vn><vn id="Dt 34:12">and as far as all of <im>the mighty deeds</im><n><io>Literally “the hand the strong”</io></n> and as far as <im>the great awesome wonders</im><n><io>Literally “the terrifying the great <sd>actions</sd>”</io></n> Moses did before the eyes of all Israel. </vn></pa> </chapter> </book>