<book id="Mal"> <chapter id="Mal 1"> <pa> <im><vn id="Mal 1:1">An oracle</vn></im><vn id="Mal 1:1">.<n><io>Literally “A burden”</io></n> The word of Yahweh to Israel <im>through</im><n><io>Literally “by the hand of”</io></n> Malachi.<n><io>The name “Malachi” means “my messenger” in Hebrew</io></n> </vn></pa>  <pericope>An Oracle Against Edom</pericope> <pa><vn id="Mal 1:2">“I have loved you,” says Yahweh, but you say, “How have you loved us?” “<sd>Is</sd> Esau not Jacob’s brother?” <im>declares</im><n><io>Literally “declaration of”</io></n> Yahweh. “I have loved Jacob, </vn><vn id="Mal 1:3">but Esau I have hated. I have made his<n><io>That is, “Esau’s”</io></n> mountain ranges a desolation, and <sd>given</sd> his inheritance to the jackals of <sd>the</sd> desert.” </vn><vn id="Mal 1:4">If Edom says, “We are shattered, but we will return and rebuild <sd>the</sd> ruins,” Yahweh of hosts says this: “They may build, but I will tear down; and they will be called a territory of wickedness, and the people <sd>with</sd> whom Yahweh is angry forever.” </vn><vn id="Mal 1:5">Your eyes will see <sd>this</sd>, and you will say, “Yahweh is great beyond the borders<n><io>Hebrew “boundary”</io></n> of Israel.” </vn></pa>  <pericope>An Oracle Against the Temple Priesthood</pericope> <pa><vn id="Mal 1:6">“A son honors <sd>his</sd> father, and a slave his master;<n><io>Hebrew “masters”</io></n> but if I <sd>am</sd> a father, where <sd>is</sd> my honor, and if I <sd>am</sd> a master,<n><io>Hebrew “masters”</io></n> where <sd>is</sd> my reverence?” says Yahweh of hosts to you, O priests, <im>who despise</im><n><io>Literally “despisers of”</io></n> my name. “But you say, ‘How have we despised your name?’ </vn><sd><vn id="Mal 1:7">You are</vn></sd><vn id="Mal 1:7"> presenting defiled food on my altar! But you ask, ‘How have we defiled you?’ By saying <sd>that</sd> the table of Yahweh is despised! </vn><vn id="Mal 1:8">When you offer a blind <sd>animal</sd> for sacrifice, is that not wrong?<n><io>Or “is there no wrong?”</io></n> And when you offer <sd>the</sd> lame and the one who is ill, is that not wrong?<n><io>Or “is there no wrong?”</io></n> Present it, please, to your governor! Will he be pleased with you? <im>Will he show you favor</im>?”<n><io>Literally “Will he lift your face?”</io></n> says Yahweh of hosts. </vn><vn id="Mal 1:9">So then, <im>implore the favor of God</im><n><io>Literally “appease, please, the face of God”</io></n> so that he will be gracious to us. “<im>This is what you have done</im>.<n><io>Literally “From your hand was this”</io></n> <im>Will he show favor to any of you</im>?”<n><io>Literally “will he lift up from you a face”</io></n> says Yahweh of hosts. </vn><vn id="Mal 1:10">“Who also among you will shut <sd>the temple</sd> doors <sd>so that</sd> you will not kindle fire in vain <sd>on</sd> my altar? I take no pleasure in you,” says Yahweh of hosts, “and <im>I will not accept</im><n><io>Literally “I will not take pleasure in”</io></n> an offering from your hand. </vn><vn id="Mal 1:11">From the rising of the sun to its setting, my name <sd>is</sd> great among the nations, and in every place incense <sd>is</sd> being presented to my name, and a pure offering. For my name <sd>is</sd> great among the nations,” says Yahweh of hosts. </vn><vn id="Mal 1:12">“But you <sd>are</sd> profaning it by saying the table of the Lord <sd>is</sd> defiled, and its fruit—its food<n><io>The Hebrew here is difficult; “its food” may function to explain “its fruit”</io></n>—is despised! </vn><vn id="Mal 1:13">And you say, ‘Look! <sd>This is</sd> a weariness,’ and you sniff <sd>with disdain</sd> at it,” says Yahweh of hosts. “And you bring <sd>the</sd> stolen, the lame, and the one that is sick—<sd>this</sd> you bring as the offering! Should I <im>accept it</im><n><io>Literally “take pleasure in it”</io></n> from your hand?” says Yahweh. </vn><vn id="Mal 1:14">“Cursed is the one who cheats, who has in his flock a male and vows <sd>it</sd>, but <sd>instead</sd> sacrifices a blemished one to the Lord! For I <sd>am</sd> a great king,” says Yahweh of hosts, “and my name <sd>is</sd> awesome among the nations.” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Mal 2"> <pa><vn id="Mal 2:1"> “And so then, O priests, this command <sd>is</sd> for you: </vn><vn id="Mal 2:2">If you will not listen, and if you will not <im>take it to heart</im><n><io>Literally, “place <sd>it</sd> on <sd>your</sd> heart”</io></n> to give glory to my name,” says Yahweh of hosts, “then I will send the curse on you, and I will curse your blessings; moreover I have <sd>already</sd> cursed them because <im>you are not taking it to heart</im>.<n><io>Literally “you <sd>are</sd> not placing <sd>it</sd> on <sd>your</sd> heart”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Mal 2:3">Look! I <sd>am</sd> going to rebuke <im>your offspring</im>,<n><io>Literally “for you the offspring”</io></n> and I will scatter offal on your faces, <sd>the</sd> offal of your religious feasts, and you will be carried to it.<n><io>The Hebrew is difficult. The subject is indefinite, and “it” likely refers to a refuse or waste pile</io></n> </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Mal 2:4">“Then you will know that I have sent to you this command, that my covenant with Levi <im>continues</im>,”<n><io>Literally “be”</io></n> says Yahweh of hosts. </vn><vn id="Mal 2:5">“My covenant with him was <sd>one of</sd> life and peace, and I gave them to him. <sd>This required</sd> reverence, and he revered<n><io>Or “feared”</io></n> me and stood in awe <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “from the face of”</io></n> my name. </vn><sd><vn id="Mal 2:6">The</vn></sd><vn id="Mal 2:6"> instruction of truth<n><io>Or “law of truth”</io></n> was in his mouth, and wickedness was not found on his lips. In peace and in uprightness<n><io>Or “rectitude,” or “fairness”</io></n> he walked with me, and he brought back many from sin.<n><io>Or “iniquity”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Mal 2:7">For the lips of <sd>the</sd> priest should guard knowledge, and they should seek instruction<n><io>Or “law”</io></n> from his mouth, for he <sd>is</sd> the messenger of Yahweh of hosts. </vn><vn id="Mal 2:8">But you, you have turned from the way; you have caused many to stumble by <sd>your</sd> instruction;<n><io>Or “<sd>the</sd> law”</io></n> you have ruined the covenant of Levi,” says Yahweh of hosts. </vn><vn id="Mal 2:9">“And in turn I have made you despised and humbled before all the people, inasmuch as you <sd>are</sd> not keeping<n><io>Or “observing”</io></n> my way, but are <im>favoring your own instruction</im>.”<n><io>Literally “lifting faces in the instruction/law”</io></n> </vn></pa>  <pericope>Yahweh Hates Faithlessness</pericope> <pa><im><vn id="Mal 2:10">Do we not all have</vn></im><n><io>Literally “<sd>Is</sd> for all of us not”</io></n><vn id="Mal 2:10"> one father? Has not one God created us? Why <sd>then</sd> are we unfaithful <im>to one another</im>,<n><io>Literally “each man to his brother”</io></n> profaning the covenant of our ancestors?<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Mal 2:11">Judah has been faithless, and a detestable thing has been done in Israel and in Jerusalem. Judah has profaned the sanctuary of Yahweh which he loves, and has married the daughter of a foreign<n><io>Or “pagan”</io></n> god. </vn><vn id="Mal 2:12">May Yahweh cut off from the tents of Jacob the man who does this, <sd>the</sd> one who is awake and <sd>who</sd> answers, and <sd>the one who</sd> brings an offering to Yahweh of hosts! </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Mal 2:13">And this you do <im>as well</im>:<n><io>Literally “a second time”</io></n> <sd>you</sd> cover the altar of Yahweh <sd>with</sd> tears, <sd>with</sd> weeping and <sd>with</sd> groaning, because he<n><io>Yahweh</io></n> <im>no longer regards the offering</im><n><io>Literally “there is no longer turning to the offering”</io></n> or accepts <sd>it</sd> <sd>with</sd> favor from your hand. </vn><vn id="Mal 2:14">But you ask, “<im>For what reason</im>?”<n><io>Literally “Because of what?”</io></n> Because Yahweh stands as a witness between you and the wife of your youth, against whom you have been unfaithful, even though she <sd>is</sd> your marriage partner and <im>your wife by covenant</im>.<n><io>Literally “the wife of your covenant”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Mal 2:15">Did not one God make them?<n><io>Literally “Not one did he make”</io></n> But a remnant of <sd>the</sd> spirit is his.<n><io>The meaning of this sentence is difficult; literally “And a remnant of the spirit to him”</io></n> And what does the one <sd>God</sd> desire? An offspring of God.<n><io>Or “a godly offspring”</io></n> <im>You must be attentive to</im><n><io>Literally “You must keep watch on”</io></n> your spirit, and you must not be unfaithful to the wife of your youth. </vn><vn id="Mal 2:16">“For <sd>I</sd> hate divorce,”<n><io>Hebrew “sending away”</io></n> says Yahweh, the God of Israel, “and he <sd>who</sd> covers his clothing <sd>with</sd> violence,” says Yahweh of hosts. “<im>You must be attentive to</im><n><io>Literally “You must keep watch on”</io></n> your spirit and you must not be unfaithful.” </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Mal 2:17">You have wearied Yahweh with your words, but you ask, “With what have we wearied <sd>him</sd>?” <sd>You have done so</sd> <im>when you say</im>,<n><io>Literally “at your saying”</io></n> “Everyone who does evil <sd>is</sd> good in the <im>sight</im><n><io>Literally “eyes”</io></n> of Yahweh, and in them he delights,” or “Where <sd>is</sd> the God of justice?” </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Mal 3"> <pericope>Yahweh’s Messenger is Coming</pericope> <pa><vn id="Mal 3:1">“Look! I <sd>am</sd> going to send my messenger,<n><io>Or “my angel”</io></n> and he will prepare<n><io>Or “clear”</io></n> <sd>the</sd> way <im>before me</im>.<n><io>Literally “before my face”</io></n> And the Lord whom you <sd>are</sd> seeking will come suddenly to his temple, and the messenger of the covenant, <sd>in</sd> whom you <sd>are</sd> taking pleasure—look!—<sd>he is</sd> about to come,” says Yahweh of hosts. </vn><vn id="Mal 3:2">And who <sd>can</sd> endure the day of his coming? And who <sd>is</sd> the one who can stand <im>when he appears</im>?<n><io>Literally “at his appearing”</io></n> For he <sd>is</sd> like a refiner’s fire, like launderers’ alkali.<n><io>Or “lye,” or “soap”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Mal 3:3">He will sit <sd>as</sd> a refiner and purifier of silver; he will purify the children of Levi, and he will refine them like gold and like silver, and they will present to Yahweh offerings<n><io>Hebrew “offering”</io></n> in righteousness. </vn><vn id="Mal 3:4">And the offering of Judah and Jerusalem will be pleasing to Yahweh, like <sd>in the</sd> days of old and like <sd>in</sd> former years. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Mal 3:5">“Then I will approach you for judgment, and I will be a swift witness against the sorcerers and against the adulterers, and against those who swear <im>falsely</im>,<n><io>Literally “as far as the falseness”</io></n> and against the oppressors of <sd>the</sd> hired worker <sd>with his</sd> wages, <sd>the</sd> widow and <sd>the</sd> orphan, and <im>the abusers of</im><n><io>Literally “<sd>those</sd> pushing aside”</io></n> <sd>the</sd> alien,<n><io>Or “sojourner”</io></n> and <sd>yet</sd> do not fear me,” says Yahweh of hosts. </vn></pa>  <pericope>An Overflowing Blessing</pericope> <pa><vn id="Mal 3:6">“For I, Yahweh, have not changed,<n><io>Or “I do not change”</io></n> and you, O children of Jacob, have not perished.<n><io>Or “are not destroyed”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Mal 3:7">From the days of your ancestors<n><io>Or “fathers”</io></n> you have turned aside from my rules, and have not kept<n><io>Or “observed”</io></n> <sd>them</sd>! Return to me and I will return to you,” says Yahweh of hosts, “but you say, ‘How shall we return?’ </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Mal 3:8">Will a human <sd>dare to</sd> rob God? Yet you <sd>are</sd> robbing me! And you say, ‘How have we robbed you?’ In the tithes and the contributions! </vn><vn id="Mal 3:9">You <sd>are</sd> being cursed with <sd>a</sd> curse, for you <sd>are</sd> robbing me, the whole nation <sd>of you</sd>! </vn><vn id="Mal 3:10">Bring the whole tithe to <im>the storehouse</im>,<n><io>Hebrew “the house of the treasure”</io></n> so that there will be food in my house, and test me please in this,” says Yahweh of hosts, “if I will not open for you the windows of heaven, and pour forth for you <im>an overflowing blessing</im>.<n><io>Literally, “a blessing up to not enough”</io></n> </vn><vn id="Mal 3:11">I will rebuke the devourer<n><io>NRSV, JPS interpret this word as “locust”</io></n> for you; it will not destroy the fruit of your soil; your vine in the field will not be unfruitful,” says Yahweh of hosts. </vn><vn id="Mal 3:12">“And all the nations will call you blessed, because you will be <im>a land in which one takes joy</im>,”<n><io>Literally “a land of desire”</io></n> says Yahweh of hosts. </vn><vn id="Mal 3:13">“Your words have been harsh<n><io>Hebrew “strong”</io></n> against me,” says Yahweh. “But you say, ‘How have we spoken together against you?’ </vn><vn id="Mal 3:14">You have said, ‘<sd>It is</sd> useless<n><io>Or “vain”</io></n> to serve God! What <sd>is the</sd> gain if we keep<n><io>Or “observe”</io></n> his requirements, and if we walk as mourners <im>before</im><n><io>Literally “from the face of”</io></n> Yahweh of hosts? </vn><vn id="Mal 3:15">And now we <sd>are</sd> calling <sd>the</sd> arrogant blessed! Not only do those who do wickedness prosper; they also test God and they escape!’ ” </vn></pa>  <pericope>A Book of Remembrance is Written</pericope> <pa><vn id="Mal 3:16">Then those who revered<n><io>Or “fear”</io></n> Yahweh spoke <im>with one another</im>.<n><io>Literally “each with his friend/companion”</io></n> And Yahweh listened attentively<n><io>Or “gave heed”</io></n> and heard, and a scroll of remembrance was written <im>before him</im><n><io>Literally “to the face of him”</io></n> of those who revere<n><io>Or “fear”</io></n> Yahweh and ponder his name. </vn><vn id="Mal 3:17">“They will be mine,” says Yahweh of hosts, “on the day that I <sd>am</sd> acting, <sd>my</sd> treasured possession. I will have compassion on them as a man has compassion on his son who serves him. </vn><vn id="Mal 3:18">You will return and see <sd>the difference</sd> between <sd>the</sd> righteous and <sd>the</sd> wicked, between <sd>the one who</sd> serves God and the one who does not serve him. </vn></pa> </chapter> <chapter id="Mal 4"> <pa> <n><io><ci ref="Mal 4:1–6">Malachi 4:1–6 </ci>in the English Bible is 3:19–24 in the Hebrew Bible</io></n><vn id="Mal 4:1"> “For look! The day <sd>is</sd> about to come, burning like an oven, and all the arrogant and every <im>evildoer</im><n><io>Literally “doer of wickedness”</io></n> will be stubble. The coming day will consume<n><io>Or “devour”</io></n> them,” says Yahweh of hosts. “It will not leave behind for them root or branch. </vn><vn id="Mal 4:2">But for you who revere<n><io>Or “fear”</io></n> my name, the sun of righteousness will rise, with healing in its wings, and you will go out and leap like <im>fattened calves</im>.<n><io>Literally “bull-calves of <sd>the</sd> animal stall” (on the idiom see HALOT 631 s.v.)</io></n> </vn><vn id="Mal 4:3">You will trample down the wicked, for they will be ashes under the soles of your feet on the day that I <sd>am</sd> going to act,” says Yahweh of hosts. </vn></pa> <pa><vn id="Mal 4:4">“Remember the instruction<n><io>Or “law”; Hebrew <i>torah</i></io></n> of my servant Moses, which I commanded him at Horeb to all Israel, the rules and regulations. </vn><vn id="Mal 4:5">Look! I <sd>am</sd> going to send to you Elijah the prophet before the coming of the great and awesome day of Yahweh! </vn><vn id="Mal 4:6">And he will bring back<n><io>Or “And he will restore”</io></n> <sd>the</sd> hearts of <sd>the</sd> fathers to <sd>the</sd> sons, and the hearts of <sd>the</sd> sons to their fathers, so that I will not come and strike the land <sd>with</sd> a ban.” </vn></pa> </chapter> </book>